<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Kings</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="1Kgs"><chapter sID="1Kgs.1" osisID="1Kgs.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Kings</title><div scope="1Kgs.1.1-1Kgs.1.4" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">David and Abishag</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.1" osisID="1Kgs.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King David had become very old. His servants covered him with blankets, but he couldn’t stay warm. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.2" osisID="1Kgs.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They said to him, <q type="x-complete">Allow us to find a young woman for our master the king. She will serve the king and take care of him by lying beside our master the king and keeping him warm.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.3" osisID="1Kgs.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So they looked in every corner of Israel until they found Abishag from Shunem. They brought her to the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.4" osisID="1Kgs.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">She was very beautiful. She cared for the king and served him, but the king didn’t have sex with her.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.1.5-1Kgs.1.53" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Adonijah’s rebellion</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.5" osisID="1Kgs.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Adonijah, Haggith’s son, bragged about himself and said, <q type="x-complete">I’ll rule as king myself.</q> He got his own chariot and horses with fifty runners to go in front. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.6" osisID="1Kgs.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Adonijah’s father had never given him direction; he never questioned why Adonijah did what he did. He was very handsome and was born after Absalom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.7" osisID="1Kgs.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He took advice from Joab, Zeruiah’s son, and from the priest Abiathar. They assisted Adonijah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.8" osisID="1Kgs.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Zadok the priest, Jehoiada’s son Benaiah, the prophet Nathan, Shimei and his friends, and David’s veterans didn’t join Adonijah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.9" osisID="1Kgs.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Adonijah prepared lamb, oxen, and fattened cattle at the Stone of Zoheleth, next to En-rogel. He invited his brothers (the royal princes) and all the citizens of Judah who were the royal servants to come. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.10" osisID="1Kgs.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But he didn’t invite the prophet Nathan, Benaiah, David’s veterans, or his brother Solomon.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.11" osisID="1Kgs.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nathan said to Bathsheba, Solomon’s mother, <q type="x-start">Did you hear that Adonijah, Haggith’s son, has become king, but our master David doesn’t know about it?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.12" osisID="1Kgs.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Let me give you some advice on how you and your son Solomon can survive this.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.13" osisID="1Kgs.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Go to King David and say, ‘Didn’t my master the king swear to your servant, </q><q type="x-complete">Your son Solomon will certainly rule after me. He will sit on my throne</q>? Why then has Adonijah become king?’ </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.14" osisID="1Kgs.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">While you are speaking there with the king, I’ll come along and support your words.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.15" osisID="1Kgs.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Bathsheba went to the king in his bedroom. The king was very old, and Abishag from Shunem was serving the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.16" osisID="1Kgs.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Bathsheba bowed down on her face before the king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.16" osisID="1Kgs.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king asked, <q type="x-complete">What do you want?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.17" osisID="1Kgs.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">She said to him, <q type="x-start">Your Majesty, you swore by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God to your servant, ‘Your son Solomon will certainly rule after me. He will sit on my throne.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.18" osisID="1Kgs.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But now, look, Adonijah has become king, and my master the king doesn’t know about it.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.19" osisID="1Kgs.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">He has prepared large quantities of oxen, fattened cattle, and lamb. He has invited all the royal princes as well as Abiathar the priest and Joab the general. However, he didn’t invite your servant Solomon.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.20" osisID="1Kgs.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">As for you, my master the king, the eyes of all Israel are upon you to tell them who will follow you on the throne of my master the king.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.21" osisID="1Kgs.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">When my master the king lies down with his ancestors, then I and my son Solomon will become outlaws.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.22" osisID="1Kgs.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While she was still speaking with the king, the prophet Nathan arrived. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.23" osisID="1Kgs.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king was informed, <q type="x-complete">The prophet Nathan is here.</q> Then Nathan came in before the king and bowed his face to the ground. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.24" osisID="1Kgs.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said, <q type="x-start">My master the king, you must have said, ‘Adonijah will become king after me and will sit on my throne.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.25" osisID="1Kgs.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Indeed, today he went down and prepared oxen, fattened cattle, and lamb in large numbers. He invited all the royal princes, the generals, and Abiathar the priest. They are eating and drinking with him, and they said, ‘Long live King Adonijah!’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.26" osisID="1Kgs.1.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Adonijah didn’t invite me, your servant, Zadok the priest, Jehoiada’s son Benaiah, or your servant Solomon.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.27" osisID="1Kgs.1.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">If this message was from my master the king, you didn’t make it known to your servant. Who should follow you on the throne of my master the king?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.28" osisID="1Kgs.1.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King David answered, <q type="x-complete">Bring me Bathsheba.</q> She came and stood before the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.29" osisID="1Kgs.1.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king made a solemn pledge and said, <q type="x-start">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> lives, who rescued me from every trouble,</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.30" osisID="1Kgs.1.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">regarding what I swore to you by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, ‘Your son Solomon will certainly succeed me; he will sit on the throne after me’—I’ll see that it happens today.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.31" osisID="1Kgs.1.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Bathsheba bowed down with her face to the ground. She honored the king and said, <q type="x-complete">May my master King David live forever!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.32" osisID="1Kgs.1.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King David said, <q type="x-complete">Bring me Zadok the priest, the prophet Nathan, and Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son.</q> They came to the king, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.33" osisID="1Kgs.1.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who said to them, <q type="x-start">Take with you the servants of your masters. Put my son Solomon on my mule and bring him down to Gihon.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.34" osisID="1Kgs.1.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">There Zadok the priest and the prophet Nathan will anoint him king over Israel. Blow the ram’s horn and say, ‘Long live King Solomon!’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.35" osisID="1Kgs.1.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">You will follow him. He will enter and sit on my throne, and so he will succeed me as king. I have appointed him to become ruler over Israel and Judah.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.36" osisID="1Kgs.1.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son, responded to the king, <q type="x-start">Yes, may it happen as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of my king, says.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.37" osisID="1Kgs.1.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was with my master the king, so may he be with Solomon. May his throne be even greater than the throne of my master King David.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.38" osisID="1Kgs.1.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zadok the priest, the prophet Nathan, Jehoiada’s son Benaiah, and the Cherethites and the Pelethites went down and put Solomon on King David’s mule. They led him to Gihon. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.39" osisID="1Kgs.1.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zadok the priest took the horn of oil from the tent and anointed Solomon. They blew the ram’s horn, and all the people said, <q type="x-complete">Long live King Solomon!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.40" osisID="1Kgs.1.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the people followed him playing flutes and celebrating. The ground shook at their noise.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.41" osisID="1Kgs.1.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Adonijah and all his invited guests heard this when they had finished eating. When Joab heard the sound of the ram’s horn, he said, <q type="x-complete">What’s that noise coming from the city?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.42" osisID="1Kgs.1.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">While he was still speaking, Jonathan, Abiathar the priest’s son, arrived.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.42" osisID="1Kgs.1.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Adonijah said, <q type="x-complete">Come on in! You are an honest man and will bring a good report.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.43" osisID="1Kgs.1.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jonathan replied to Adonijah, <q type="x-start">No! Our master King David has made Solomon king!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.44" osisID="1Kgs.1.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">To support him, the king sent along Zadok the priest; the prophet Nathan; Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son; and the Cherethites and the Pelethites. They’ve put Solomon on the royal mule.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.45" osisID="1Kgs.1.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Zadok the priest and the prophet Nathan have anointed him king at Gihon. They went up from there celebrating so that the city was thrown into a commotion. That is the sound you heard.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.46" osisID="1Kgs.1.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">There’s more: Solomon has taken over the throne of the kingdom.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.47" osisID="1Kgs.1.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">The royal attendants blessed our master King David: ‘May your God make Solomon’s name better than your name. May God elevate his throne above your throne.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.47" osisID="1Kgs.1.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king then worshipped on his bed </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.48" osisID="1Kgs.1.48" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and said, <q type="x-complete">Bless Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, who today has set my son<note osisRef="1Kgs.1.48" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.1.48!note.a">Heb lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">my son</hi>; other versions have it or something similar.</note> on my throne, and has allowed my eyes to see it.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.49" osisID="1Kgs.1.49" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Trembling with fear, all of Adonijah’s guests got up and fled, each going a different way. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.50" osisID="1Kgs.1.50" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Adonijah was afraid of Solomon, so he got up and went to grab hold of the horns of the altar. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.51" osisID="1Kgs.1.51" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon was told, <q type="x-complete">Look! Adonijah is afraid of King Solomon and has grabbed the horns of the altar. He’s saying, ‘King Solomon must swear to me first that he won’t execute his servant with the sword.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.1.52" osisID="1Kgs.1.52" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon said, <q type="x-complete">If he shows himself to be an honorable person, then not a hair of his head will be harmed. But if any evil is found in him, he will die.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.1.53" osisID="1Kgs.1.53" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon sent word and had him brought down from the altar. He came and bowed down to King Solomon. Solomon said to him, <q type="x-complete">Go home!</q></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.2" osisID="1Kgs.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="1Kgs.2.1-1Kgs.2.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">David’s last words</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.1" osisID="1Kgs.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">David’s time was coming to an end. So he commanded Solomon his son, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.2" osisID="1Kgs.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">I’m following the path that the whole earth takes. Be strong and be a man.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.3" osisID="1Kgs.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Guard what is owed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God, walking in his ways and observing his laws, his commands, his judgments, and his testimonies, just as it is written in the Instruction from Moses. In this way you will succeed in whatever you do and wherever you go.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.4" osisID="1Kgs.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">So also the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will confirm the word he spoke to me: ‘If your children will take care to walk before me faithfully, with all their heart and all their being, then one of your own children will never fail to be on the throne of Israel.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.5" osisID="1Kgs.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">You should know what Joab, Zeruiah’s son, has done to me and what he did to the two generals of Israel, Abner, Ner’s son, and Amasa, Jether’s son. He murdered them, spilling blood at peacetime and putting the blood of war on the belt around his waist and on the sandals on his feet.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.6" osisID="1Kgs.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">So act wisely: Don’t allow him to die a peaceful death.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.7" osisID="1Kgs.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">As for Barzillai’s sons from Gilead, show them kindness. Let them eat with you. When I was running away from your brother Absalom, they came to me.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.8" osisID="1Kgs.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Now as for this Shimei, Gera’s son—a Benjaminite from Bahurim—who is with you, he cursed me viciously when I went to Mahanaim. When he came down to meet me at the Jordan, I swore to him by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, ‘Surely I won’t execute you with the sword.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.9" osisID="1Kgs.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But you don’t need to excuse him. You are wise and know what to do to him. Give him a violent death.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.10" osisID="1Kgs.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then David lay down with his ancestors and was buried in David’s City. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.11" osisID="1Kgs.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ruled over Israel forty years—seven years in Hebron and thirty-three years in Jerusalem.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.2.12-1Kgs.2.46" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon secures his throne</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.12" osisID="1Kgs.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon sat on the throne of his father David, and his royal power was well established. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.13" osisID="1Kgs.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Adonijah, Haggith’s son, went to Bathsheba, Solomon’s mother. She said, <q type="x-complete">Are you coming in peace?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.13" osisID="1Kgs.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">He said, <q type="x-start">Yes.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.14" osisID="1Kgs.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">I have something to say to you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.14" osisID="1Kgs.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">She said, <q type="x-complete">Say it.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.15" osisID="1Kgs.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said, <q type="x-start">You know how the kingdom was mine. All Israel had appointed me as their king. Then suddenly the kingdom went to my brother as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> willed.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.16" osisID="1Kgs.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">Now I have just one request of you. Don’t refuse me!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.16" osisID="1Kgs.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">She said to him, <q type="x-complete">Go on.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.17" osisID="1Kgs.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Adonijah continued, <q type="x-start">Ask King Solomon to let me marry Abishag from Shunem—</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.17" osisID="1Kgs.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-end">he won’t refuse you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.18" osisID="1Kgs.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Bathsheba said, <q type="x-complete">Okay; I’ll speak to the king for you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.19" osisID="1Kgs.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Bathsheba went to King Solomon to talk with him about Adonijah. The king stood up to meet her and bowed low to her. Then he returned to his throne and had a throne set up for the queen mother. She sat to his right. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.20" osisID="1Kgs.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">She said, <q type="x-complete">I have just one small request for you. Don’t refuse me.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.20" osisID="1Kgs.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king said to her, <q type="x-complete">Mother, ask me. I won’t refuse you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.21" osisID="1Kgs.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Let Abishag from Shunem be married to your brother Adonijah,</q> she said.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.22" osisID="1Kgs.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon replied to his mother, <q type="x-complete">Why ask only for Abishag from Shunem for Adonijah? Why not ask for the entire kingdom for him? After all, he is my older brother and has the support of Abiathar the priest and Joab, Zeruiah’s son.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.23" osisID="1Kgs.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon swore by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, <q type="x-start">May God do to me as he sees fit! Adonijah has made this request at the cost of his life!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.24" osisID="1Kgs.2.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now, as surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> lives—the one who supported me, put me on the throne of my father David, and provided a royal house for me exactly as he promised—Adonijah will be executed today.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.25" osisID="1Kgs.2.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So King Solomon sent Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son. He attacked Adonijah, and Adonijah died.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.26" osisID="1Kgs.2.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king said to the priest Abiathar, <q type="x-complete">Go to your fields at Anathoth, because you are a condemned man. However, I won’t kill you today because you carried the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s chest in front of my father David and because you shared in all my father’s sufferings.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.27" osisID="1Kgs.2.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Solomon expelled Abiathar from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s priesthood in order to fulfill the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word that was spoken against Eli’s family at Shiloh.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.28" osisID="1Kgs.2.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now the news reached Joab because he had supported Adonijah, though he hadn’t supported Absalom. Joab ran to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s tent and grabbed the horns of the altar. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.29" osisID="1Kgs.2.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon was told that Joab had fled to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s tent and was now beside the altar. So Solomon sent Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son, instructing him, <q type="x-complete">Go. Attack Joab!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.30" osisID="1Kgs.2.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Benaiah came to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s tent and said to Joab, <q type="x-complete">The king says, ‘Come out!’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.30" osisID="1Kgs.2.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Joab said, <q type="x-complete">No! I’d rather die here.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.30" osisID="1Kgs.2.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Benaiah sent a report back to the king: <q type="x-complete">This is what Joab said and how he answered me.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.31" osisID="1Kgs.2.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king said to him, <q type="x-start">Do as he said. Attack him and then bury him. In doing this, you will remove from me and from my father’s royal house the guilt over the innocent blood that Joab shed.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.32" osisID="1Kgs.2.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">May the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> return that bloodguilt back on his own head for attacking the two men who were better and more righteous than he was. He murdered those two with the sword: Abner, Ner’s son and Israel’s general, and Amasa, Jether’s son and Judah’s general. But my father David didn’t know about it.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.33" osisID="1Kgs.2.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">May the bloodguilt for their deaths return on Joab’s head and on the head of his family line forever. But may the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s peace be on David, his family, and his royal house forever.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.34" osisID="1Kgs.2.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son, went and attacked Joab and killed him.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.34" osisID="1Kgs.2.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Joab was buried at his home in the wilderness. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.35" osisID="1Kgs.2.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In his place, the king gave leadership of the army to Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son. The king put the priest Zadok in Abiathar’s position. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.36" osisID="1Kgs.2.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he sent for Shimei and said, <q type="x-start">Build a house for yourself in Jerusalem and stay in the city. Don’t leave to go anywhere else.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.37" osisID="1Kgs.2.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">If you try to leave, be advised that on the day you cross the Kidron Valley you will most certainly die. Your bloodguilt will be on your own head.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.38" osisID="1Kgs.2.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Shimei said to the king, <q type="x-complete">This is a good idea. Your servant will do just what my master the king said.</q> So Shimei stayed in Jerusalem for a long time.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.39" osisID="1Kgs.2.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After three years, two of Shimei’s servants fled to the king of Gath, Achish, Maacah’s son. Shimei was informed, <q type="x-complete">Your servants are now in Gath.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.40" osisID="1Kgs.2.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Shimei saddled his donkey and went to Achish in Gath to look for his servants. Shimei then brought his servants back from Gath. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.41" osisID="1Kgs.2.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon was told that Shimei had left Jerusalem for Gath and then returned.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.42" osisID="1Kgs.2.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king sent for Shimei and asked him, <q type="x-start">Didn’t I make you swear a solemn pledge by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>? And didn’t I swear to you, ‘If you try to leave and go anywhere, be advised that on that very day you will most certainly die’? You said to me, ‘This is a good idea. I agree to it.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.43" osisID="1Kgs.2.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Why didn’t you keep your solemn promise to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and the command that I gave you?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.44" osisID="1Kgs.2.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king said further, <q type="x-start">You know quite well all the evil that you did to my father David. May the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> return your evil on your own head.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.45" osisID="1Kgs.2.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">However, may King Solomon be blessed and David’s throne be secure before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> forever.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.2.46" osisID="1Kgs.2.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Then the king commanded Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son, who went and attacked Shimei, and he died.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.2.46" osisID="1Kgs.2.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">In these ways royal power was handed over to Solomon.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.3" osisID="1Kgs.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="1Kgs.3.1-1Kgs.3.15" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon first meets God</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.1" osisID="1Kgs.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon became the son-in-law of Pharaoh, Egypt’s king, when he married Pharaoh’s daughter. He brought her to David’s City until he finished building his royal palace, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, and the wall around Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.2" osisID="1Kgs.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Unfortunately, the people were sacrificing at the shrines because a temple hadn’t yet been built for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s name in those days. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.3" osisID="1Kgs.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Solomon loved to walk in the laws of his father David, with the exception that he also sacrificed and burned incense at the shrines.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.4" osisID="1Kgs.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king went to the great shrine at Gibeon in order to sacrifice there. He used to offer a thousand entirely burned offerings on that altar. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.5" osisID="1Kgs.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> appeared to Solomon at Gibeon in a dream at night. God said, <q type="x-complete">Ask whatever you wish, and I’ll give it to you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.6" osisID="1Kgs.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon responded, <q type="x-start">You showed so much kindness to your servant my father David when he walked before you in truth, righteousness, and with a heart true to you. You’ve kept this great loyalty and kindness for him and have now given him a son to sit on his throne.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.7" osisID="1Kgs.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">And now, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God, you have made me, your servant, king in my father David’s place. But I’m young and inexperienced. I know next to nothing.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.8" osisID="1Kgs.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But I’m here, your servant, in the middle of the people you have chosen, a large population that can’t be numbered or counted due to its vast size.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.9" osisID="1Kgs.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Please give your servant a discerning mind in order to govern your people and to distinguish good from evil, because no one is able to govern this important people of yours without your help.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.10" osisID="1Kgs.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It pleased the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> that Solomon had made this request. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.11" osisID="1Kgs.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God said to him, <q type="x-start">Because you have asked for this instead of requesting long life, wealth, or victory over your enemies—asking for discernment so as to acquire good judgment—</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.12" osisID="1Kgs.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I will now do just what you said. Look, I hereby give you a wise and understanding mind. There has been no one like you before now, nor will there be anyone like you afterward.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.13" osisID="1Kgs.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I now also give you what you didn’t ask for: wealth and fame. There won’t be a king like you as long as you live.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.14" osisID="1Kgs.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">And if you walk in my ways and obey my laws and commands, just as your father David did, then I will give you a very long life.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.15" osisID="1Kgs.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon awoke and realized it was a dream. He went to Jerusalem and stood before the chest containing the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s covenant. Then he offered entirely burned offerings and well-being sacrifices, and held a celebration for all his servants.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.3.16-1Kgs.3.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon and the prostitutes</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.16" osisID="1Kgs.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Sometime later, two prostitutes came and stood before the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.17" osisID="1Kgs.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">One of them said, <q type="x-start">Please, Your Majesty, listen: This woman and I have been living in the same house. I gave birth while she was there.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.18" osisID="1Kgs.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">This woman gave birth three days after I did. We stayed together. Apart from the two of us, there was no one else in the house.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.19" osisID="1Kgs.3.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">This woman’s son died one night when she rolled over him.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.20" osisID="1Kgs.3.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">She got up in the middle of the night and took my son from my side while I was asleep. She laid him on her chest and laid her dead son on mine.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.21" osisID="1Kgs.3.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">When I got up in the morning to nurse my son, he was dead! But when I looked more closely in the daylight, it turned out that it wasn’t my son—not the baby I had birthed.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.22" osisID="1Kgs.3.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The other woman said, <q type="x-complete">No! My son is alive! Your son is the dead one.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.22" osisID="1Kgs.3.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">But the first woman objected, <q type="x-complete">No! Your son is dead! My son is alive!</q> In this way they argued back and forth in front of the king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.23" osisID="1Kgs.3.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king said, <q type="x-start">This one says, ‘My son is alive and your son is dead.’ The other one says, ‘No! Your son is dead and my son is alive.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.24" osisID="1Kgs.3.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Get me a sword!</q> They brought a sword to the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.3.25" osisID="1Kgs.3.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king said, <q type="x-complete">Cut the living child in two! Give half to one woman and half to the other woman.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.26" osisID="1Kgs.3.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Then the woman whose son was still alive said to the king, <q type="x-complete">Please, Your Majesty, give her the living child; please don’t kill him,</q> for she had great love for her son.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.26" osisID="1Kgs.3.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">But the other woman said, <q type="x-complete">If I can’t have him, neither will you. Cut the child in half.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.27" osisID="1Kgs.3.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king answered, <q type="x-complete">Give the first woman the living newborn. Don’t kill him. She is his mother.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.3.28" osisID="1Kgs.3.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All Israel heard about the judgment that the king made. Their respect for the king grew because they saw that God’s wisdom was in him so he could execute justice.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.4" osisID="1Kgs.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="1Kgs.4.1-1Kgs.4.34" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s administration</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.1" osisID="1Kgs.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon became king of all Israel.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.2" osisID="1Kgs.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These were his officials: the priest Azariah, Zadok’s son; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.3" osisID="1Kgs.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the scribes Elihoreph and Ahijah, the sons of Shisha; Jehoshaphat, the recorder, Ahilud’s son; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.4" osisID="1Kgs.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the general Benaiah, Jehoiada’s son; the priests Zadok and Abiathar; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.5" osisID="1Kgs.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Azariah, Nathan’s son, who was in charge of the officials; Zabud, Nathan’s son, a priest and royal friend; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.6" osisID="1Kgs.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahishar, who was in charge of the palace; and Adoniram, Abda’s son, who was supervisor of the work gangs.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.7" osisID="1Kgs.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon had twelve officers over all Israel. They supplied the king and his palace with food. Each would provide the supplies for one month per year. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.8" osisID="1Kgs.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Here are their names:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.8" osisID="1Kgs.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Ben-hur in the highlands of Ephraim;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.9" osisID="1Kgs.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-deker in Makaz, Shaalbim, Beth-shemesh, and Elon-bethhanan;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.10" osisID="1Kgs.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-hesed in Arubboth, who had Socoh and all the land of Hepher;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.11" osisID="1Kgs.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-abinadab in all of Naphath-dor (Taphath, Solomon’s daughter, was his wife);</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.12" osisID="1Kgs.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baana, Ahilud’s son, in Taanach, Megiddo, and all Beth-shean beside Zarethan and below Jezreel, from Beth-shean to Abel-meholah and over to the region opposite Jokmeam;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.13" osisID="1Kgs.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-geber in Ramoth-gilead, who controlled the villages of Jair, Manasseh’s son, which were in Gilead, and who had the Argob region that was in Bashan—sixty large walled cities with bronze bars;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.14" osisID="1Kgs.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahinadab, Iddo’s son, in Mahanaim;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.15" osisID="1Kgs.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahimaaz in Naphtali, who also took Solomon’s daughter Basemath as his wife;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.16" osisID="1Kgs.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baana, Hushai’s son, in Asher and Bealoth;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.17" osisID="1Kgs.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Jehoshaphat, Paruah’s son, in</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.17" osisID="1Kgs.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Issachar;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.18" osisID="1Kgs.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Shimei, Ela’s son, in Benjamin;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.19" osisID="1Kgs.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Geber, Uri’s son, in the land of Gilead, the land of the Amorite king Sihon and of King Og of Bashan;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.19" osisID="1Kgs.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and there was a single officer who was in the land of Judah.<note osisRef="1Kgs.4.19" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.4.19!note.b">LXX; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">of Judah</hi>.</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.20" osisID="1Kgs.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Judah and Israel grew numerous like the sand alongside the sea. They ate, drank, and celebrated.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.21" osisID="1Kgs.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="1Kgs.4.21" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.4.21!note.c">5:1 in Heb</note> Solomon ruled over all the states from the Euphrates River through the Philistines’ land and as far as the border of Egypt. These areas brought tribute to Solomon and served him all the days of his life. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.22" osisID="1Kgs.4.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon’s food requirements for a single day included thirty kors<note osisRef="1Kgs.4.22" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.4.22!note.d">One kor is possibly equal to fifty gallons.</note> of refined flour; sixty kors of flour; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.23" osisID="1Kgs.4.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">ten head of grain-fattened cattle; twenty head of pastured cattle; one hundred sheep; as well as deer, gazelles, roebucks, and the best of fowl. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.24" osisID="1Kgs.4.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ruled over all the lands west of the Euphrates River, from Tiphsah to Gaza, and over all the kings west of the Euphrates. He had peace on all sides. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.25" osisID="1Kgs.4.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people of Judah and Israel from Dan all the way to Beer-sheba lived securely under their vines and fig trees throughout the days of Solomon.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.4.26" osisID="1Kgs.4.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon had forty thousand horse stalls for his chariots and twelve thousand additional horses. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.27" osisID="1Kgs.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The officials provided King Solomon and all who joined him at the royal table with monthly food rations. They left out nothing. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.28" osisID="1Kgs.4.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each brought their share of barley and straw for the horses and for the chariot horses, bringing it to its proper place. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.29" osisID="1Kgs.4.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And God gave Solomon wisdom and very great understanding—insight as long as the seashore itself. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.30" osisID="1Kgs.4.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon’s wisdom was greater than all the famous Easterners, greater even than all the wisdom of Egypt. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.31" osisID="1Kgs.4.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He was wiser than anyone, more wise than Ethan the Ezrahite or Mahol’s sons: Heman, Calcol, and Darda. His reputation was known throughout the region. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.32" osisID="1Kgs.4.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon spoke three thousand proverbs and one thousand five songs. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.33" osisID="1Kgs.4.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He described the botany of trees, whether the cedar in Lebanon or the hyssop that grows out of the wall. He also described cattle, birds, anything that crawls on the ground, and fish. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.4.34" osisID="1Kgs.4.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People came from everywhere to listen to Solomon’s wisdom; even the earth’s kings who had heard about his wisdom came!</verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.5" osisID="1Kgs.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="1Kgs.5.1-1Kgs.5.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Wood and stone for the temple</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.5.1" osisID="1Kgs.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="1Kgs.5.1" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.5.1!note.e">5:15 in Heb</note> Because King Hiram<note osisRef="1Kgs.5.1" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.5.1!note.f">Chronicles spells the king’s name <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Huram</hi>, for example, 2 Chron 2:3, 11–12; but cf 1 Chron 14:1 Kethib.</note> of Tyre was loyal to David throughout his rule, Hiram sent his servants to Solomon when he heard that Solomon had become king after his father. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.2" osisID="1Kgs.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon sent the following message to Hiram: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.3" osisID="1Kgs.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">You know that my father David wasn’t able to build a temple for the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God. This was because of the enemies that fought him on all sides until the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> put them under the soles of his feet.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.4" osisID="1Kgs.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Now the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God has given me peace on every side, without enemies or misfortune.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.5" osisID="1Kgs.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">So I’m planning to build a temple for the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> indicated to my father David, ‘I will give you a son to follow you on your throne. He will build the temple for my name.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.6" osisID="1Kgs.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now give the order and have the cedars of Lebanon cut down for me. My servants will work with your servants. I’ll pay your servants whatever price you set, because you know we have no one here who is skilled in cutting wood like the Sidonians.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.5.7" osisID="1Kgs.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hiram was thrilled when he heard Solomon’s message. He said, <q type="x-complete">Today the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is blessed because he has given David a wise son who is in charge of this great people.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.8" osisID="1Kgs.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hiram sent word back to Solomon: <q type="x-start">I have heard your message to me. I will do as you wish with the cedar and pinewood.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.9" osisID="1Kgs.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">My servants will bring the wood down the Lebanon Mountains to the sea. I’ll make rafts out of them and float them on the sea to the place you specify. There I’ll dismantle them, and you can carry them away. Now, as for what you must do for me in return, I ask you to provide for my royal house.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.5.10" osisID="1Kgs.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Hiram gave Solomon all the cedar and pinewood that he wanted. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.11" osisID="1Kgs.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In return, Solomon gave an annual gift to Hiram of twenty thousand kors<note osisRef="1Kgs.5.11" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.5.11!note.g">One kor is possibly equal to fifty gallons.</note> of wheat to eat, and twenty thousand kors of pure oil for his palace use. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.12" osisID="1Kgs.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made Solomon wise, just as he had promised. Solomon and Hiram made a covenant and had peace.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.5.13" osisID="1Kgs.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon called up a work gang of thirty thousand workers from all over Israel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.14" osisID="1Kgs.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He sent ten thousand to work in Lebanon each month. Then they would spend two months at home. Adoniram was in charge of the work gang. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.15" osisID="1Kgs.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon had 70,000 laborers and 80,000 stonecutters in the highlands. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.16" osisID="1Kgs.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This doesn’t include Solomon’s 3,300 supervisors in charge of the work, who had oversight over the laborers. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.17" osisID="1Kgs.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the king’s command, they quarried huge stones of the finest quality in order to lay the temple’s foundation with carefully cut stone. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.5.18" osisID="1Kgs.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The craftsmen of Solomon and Hiram, along with those of Byblos, prepared the timber and the stones for the construction of the temple.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.6" osisID="1Kgs.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="1Kgs.6.1-1Kgs.6.38" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon builds the temple</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.6.1" osisID="1Kgs.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the four hundred eightieth year after the Israelites left Egypt, in the month of Ziv, the second month,<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.1" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.1!note.h">April–May, Iyar; Ziv is a month from a Canaanite calendar.</note> in the fourth year of Solomon’s rule over Israel, he built the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.2" osisID="1Kgs.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The temple that King Solomon built for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was ninety feet long, thirty feet wide, and forty-five feet high. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.3" osisID="1Kgs.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The porch in front of the temple’s main hall was thirty feet long. It ran across the whole width of the temple and extended fifteen feet in front of the temple. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.4" osisID="1Kgs.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made recessed and latticed windows<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.4" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.4!note.i">Heb architectural and decorative terminology in 6:4–6 and elsewhere in chaps 6–7 is often uncertain.</note> for the temple </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.5" osisID="1Kgs.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and built side rooms against the temple walls around both the main hall and the most holy place. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.6" osisID="1Kgs.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The lower walls were seven and a half feet wide. At the second floor the walls were nine feet wide, and at the third floor they were ten and a half feet wide. He made niches around the outside of the temple so the beams wouldn’t be inserted into the temple walls.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.6" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.6!note.j">Heb uncertain; Heb lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the beams.</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.7" osisID="1Kgs.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the temple was built, they did all the stonecutting at the quarry. No hammers, axes, or any iron tools were heard in the temple during its construction. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.8" osisID="1Kgs.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The door to the stairs was at the south side of the temple. Winding stairs went up to the second floor and from there to the third floor. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.9" osisID="1Kgs.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He completed the temple with a roof of cedar beams and cross-planks.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.9" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.9!note.k">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.10" osisID="1Kgs.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he built the side rooms all around the temple. They were seven and a half feet high. He attached them to the temple with cedarwood.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.6.11" osisID="1Kgs.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Solomon, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.12" osisID="1Kgs.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Regarding this temple that you are building: If you follow my laws, enact my regulations, and keep all my commands faithfully, then I will fulfill for you my promise that I made to your father David. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.13" osisID="1Kgs.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I will live among the Israelites. I won’t abandon my people Israel.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.6.14" osisID="1Kgs.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Solomon constructed the temple and completed it. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.15" osisID="1Kgs.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built the walls within the temple with cedar planks, paneled from the floor to the ceiling. He overlaid the floor of the temple with pine planks. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.16" osisID="1Kgs.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the back of the temple he built thirty feet of cedar panels from the floor to the ceiling. Solomon built the inner sanctuary, the most holy place. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.17" osisID="1Kgs.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In front of this, the main hall was sixty feet. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.18" osisID="1Kgs.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The cedar inside the temple was carved with gourds and blossoming flowers. The whole thing was cedar. No stone was seen. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.19" osisID="1Kgs.6.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He set up the inner sanctuary inside the temple so that he could put the chest containing the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s covenant there. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.20" osisID="1Kgs.6.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The inner sanctuary was thirty feet in length, width, and height. Solomon overlaid it with pure gold and covered the altar with cedar.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.20" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.20!note.l">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.21" osisID="1Kgs.6.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon covered the temple’s interior with pure gold. He placed gold chains in front of the inner sanctuary and covered it with gold. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.22" osisID="1Kgs.6.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He overlaid the whole temple inside with gold until the temple was completely covered. He covered the whole altar that was in the inner sanctuary with gold. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.23" osisID="1Kgs.6.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made two winged creatures of olive wood for the inner sanctuary, each fifteen feet high. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.24" osisID="1Kgs.6.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The wings of the first winged creature were each seven and a half feet long. It was fifteen feet from the end of one wing to the end of the other. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.25" osisID="1Kgs.6.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The second winged creature also measured fifteen feet. Both winged creatures had identical measurements and form. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.26" osisID="1Kgs.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The height of both winged creatures was fifteen feet. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.27" osisID="1Kgs.6.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon placed the winged creatures inside the temple. Their wings spread out so that the wing of the one touched one wall and the wing of the other touched the other wall. In the middle of the temple, the wings of the two winged creatures touched each other. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.28" osisID="1Kgs.6.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He covered the winged creatures with gold.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.6.29" osisID="1Kgs.6.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon carved all the walls of the temple—inner and outer rooms—with engravings of winged creatures, palm trees, and blossoming flowers. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.30" osisID="1Kgs.6.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also covered the floor of the temple with gold, in both the inner and the outer rooms. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.31" osisID="1Kgs.6.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made the doors of the inner sanctuary from olive wood and carved the doorframes with five recesses.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.31" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.31!note.m">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.32" osisID="1Kgs.6.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He overlaid the two olive-wood doors with gold-plated carvings of winged creatures, palm trees, and blossoming flowers. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.33" osisID="1Kgs.6.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made the door of the main hall with doorframes of olive wood with four recesses.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.33" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.33!note.n">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.34" osisID="1Kgs.6.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The two doors of pinewood each pivoted on a socket. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.35" osisID="1Kgs.6.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon carved winged creatures, palm trees, and blossoming flowers, and covered them with gold. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.36" osisID="1Kgs.6.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built the inner courtyard with three rows of cut stone followed by one row of trimmed cedar.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.6.37" osisID="1Kgs.6.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon laid the foundation of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple in the fourth year in the month of Ziv.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.37" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.37!note.o">April–May, Iyar; Ziv is a month in the Canaanite calendar.</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.6.38" osisID="1Kgs.6.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He finished the temple in all its details and measurements in the eleventh year during the eighth month, the month of Bul.<note osisRef="1Kgs.6.38" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.6.38!note.p">October–November, Heshvan; Bul is a month in the Canaanite calendar.</note> He built it in seven years.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.7" osisID="1Kgs.7" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="7"><div scope="1Kgs.7.1-1Kgs.7.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon builds palaces</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.1" osisID="1Kgs.7.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now as for Solomon’s palace, it took thirteen years for him to complete its construction. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.2" osisID="1Kgs.7.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built the Forest of Lebanon Palace one hundred fifty feet in length, seventy-five feet in width, and forty-five feet in height. It had four rows of cedar columns with cedar engravings above the columns. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.3" osisID="1Kgs.7.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The palace’s cedar roof stood above forty-five beams resting on the columns, fifteen beams to each row. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.4" osisID="1Kgs.7.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Three sets of window frames faced each other. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.5" osisID="1Kgs.7.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the doorframes were rectangular, facing each other in three sets. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.6" osisID="1Kgs.7.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made a porch with columns seventy-five feet long and forty-five feet wide. Another porch was in front of these with roofed columns in front of them.<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.6" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.6!note.q">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.7" osisID="1Kgs.7.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made the throne room the Hall of Justice, where he would judge. It was covered with cedar from the lower to the upper levels. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.8" osisID="1Kgs.7.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The royal residence where Solomon lived was behind this hall. It had a similar design. Solomon also made a similar palace for his wife, Pharaoh’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.9" osisID="1Kgs.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built all these with the best stones cut to size, sawed with saws, back and front, from the foundation to the highest points and from the outer boundary to the great courtyard. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.10" osisID="1Kgs.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The foundation was laid with large stones of high quality, some of fifteen feet and some of twelve feet. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.11" osisID="1Kgs.7.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Above them were high-quality stones cut to measure, as well as cedar. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.12" osisID="1Kgs.7.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The surrounding great courtyard had three rows of cut stones and a row of trimmed cedar just like the inner courtyard of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and its porch.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.7.13-1Kgs.7.51" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s temple equipment</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.13" osisID="1Kgs.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then King Solomon sent a message and brought Hiram from Tyre. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.14" osisID="1Kgs.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hiram’s mother was a widow from the tribe of Naphtali. His father was a Tyrian skilled in bronze work. He was amazingly skillful in the techniques and knowledge for doing all kinds of work in bronze. He came to King Solomon and did all his work.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.15" osisID="1Kgs.7.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.15" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.15!note.r">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he</hi>, either Solomon or Hiram; this ambiguity continues in the following verses, but cf 1 Kgs 7:1, 8, 13; 1 Kgs 7:40.</note> cast two bronze pillars. Each one was twenty-seven feet high and required a cord of eighteen feet to reach around it.<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.15" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.15!note.s">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the second</hi>; cf Jer 52:21</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.16" osisID="1Kgs.7.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made two capitals of cast bronze for the tops of the columns. They were each seven and a half feet high. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.17" osisID="1Kgs.7.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made an intricate network of chains for the capitals on top of the columns, seven for each capital. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.18" osisID="1Kgs.7.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made the pillars and two rows of pomegranates for each network to adorn each of the capitals. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.19" osisID="1Kgs.7.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The capitals on top of the columns in the porch were made like lilies, each six feet high. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.20" osisID="1Kgs.7.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Above the round-shaped part and next to the network were two hundred pomegranates. These were placed in rows around both of the capitals on top of the columns. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.21" osisID="1Kgs.7.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He set up the columns at the temple’s porch. He named the south column Jachin. The north column he named Boaz. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.22" osisID="1Kgs.7.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After putting the lily shapes on top of the columns, he was finished with the columns.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.23" osisID="1Kgs.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also made a tank of cast metal called the Sea. It was circular in shape, fifteen feet from rim to rim, seven and a half feet high, forty-five feet in circumference. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.24" osisID="1Kgs.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Under the rim were two rows of gourds completely encircling it, ten every eighteen inches, each cast in its mold. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.25" osisID="1Kgs.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Sea rested on twelve oxen with their backs toward the center, three facing north, three facing west, three facing south, and three facing east. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.26" osisID="1Kgs.7.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Sea was as thick as the width of a hand. Its rim was shaped like a cup or an open lily blossom. It could hold two thousand baths.<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.26" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.26!note.t">One bath is approximately twenty quarts or five gallons.</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.27" osisID="1Kgs.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also made ten bronze stands. Each was six feet long, six feet wide, and four and a half feet high. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.28" osisID="1Kgs.7.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is how each stand was made: There were panels connected between the legs. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.29" osisID="1Kgs.7.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Lions, bulls, and winged otherworldly creatures appeared on the panels between the legs. On the legs above and below the lions and bulls were wreaths on panels hanging off the stands. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.30" osisID="1Kgs.7.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There were four bronze wheels with bronze axles for each stand. There were four feet and supports cast for each basin with wreaths on their sides.<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.30" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.30!note.u">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.31" osisID="1Kgs.7.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Inside the bowl was an opening eighteen inches deep. The opening was round, measuring twenty-seven inches, with engravings. The panels of the stands were square rather than round. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.32" osisID="1Kgs.7.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There were four wheels beneath the panels. The axles of the wheels were attached to the stand. Each wheel was twenty-seven inches in height. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.33" osisID="1Kgs.7.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The construction of the wheels resembled chariot wheels. The axles, rims, spokes, and hubs were all made of cast metal. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.34" osisID="1Kgs.7.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was a handle on each of the four corners of every stand, projecting from the side of the stand. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.35" osisID="1Kgs.7.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The top of the stand had a band running around the perimeter that was nine inches deep. The stand had its own supports and panels. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.36" osisID="1Kgs.7.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the surfaces of the supports and panels he carved winged otherworldly creatures, lions, and palm trees with wreaths everywhere.<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.36" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.36!note.v">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.37" osisID="1Kgs.7.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In this manner he made ten stands, each one cast in a single mold of the same size and shape.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.38" osisID="1Kgs.7.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made ten bronze washbasins, each able to hold forty baths.<note osisRef="1Kgs.7.38" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.7.38!note.w">One bath is approximately twenty quarts or five gallons.</note> Every washbasin was six feet across, and there was one for each of the ten stands. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.39" osisID="1Kgs.7.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He placed five stands on the south of the temple and five on the north of the temple. He placed the Sea at the southeast corner of the temple.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.40" osisID="1Kgs.7.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Hiram made the basins, shovels, and bowls.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.40" osisID="1Kgs.7.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">And so Hiram finished his work on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple for King Solomon:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.41" osisID="1Kgs.7.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">two columns;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.41" osisID="1Kgs.7.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">two circular capitals on top of the columns;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.41" osisID="1Kgs.7.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">two networks, adorning the two circular capitals on top of the columns;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.42" osisID="1Kgs.7.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">four hundred pomegranates for the two networks, with two rows of pomegranates for each network that adorned the two circular capitals on top of the columns;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.43" osisID="1Kgs.7.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">ten stands with ten basins on them;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.44" osisID="1Kgs.7.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">one Sea;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.44" osisID="1Kgs.7.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">twelve oxen beneath the Sea;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.45" osisID="1Kgs.7.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">and the pots, shovels, and bowls.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.45" osisID="1Kgs.7.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">All the equipment that Hiram made for King Solomon for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple was made from polished bronze. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.46" osisID="1Kgs.7.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king cast it in clay molds in the Jordan Valley between Succoth and Zarethan. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.47" osisID="1Kgs.7.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Due to the very large number of objects, Solomon didn’t even try to weigh the bronze.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.7.48" osisID="1Kgs.7.48" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon also made all the equipment for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple: the golden altar; the golden table for the bread of the presence; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.49" osisID="1Kgs.7.49" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the lampstands of pure gold, five on the right and five on the left in front of the inner sanctuary; the flowers, the lamps, and the tongs of gold; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.50" osisID="1Kgs.7.50" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the cups, wick trimmers, bowls, ladles, and censers of pure gold; and the gold sockets for the doors to the most holy place and for the doors to the main hall. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.7.51" osisID="1Kgs.7.51" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When all King Solomon’s work on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple was finished, he brought the silver, gold, and all the objects his father David had dedicated and put them in the treasuries of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.8" osisID="1Kgs.8" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="8"><div scope="1Kgs.8.1-1Kgs.8.66" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon dedicates the temple</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.1" osisID="1Kgs.8.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon assembled Israel’s elders, all the tribal leaders, and the chiefs of Israel’s clans at Jerusalem to bring up the chest containing the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s covenant from David’s City Zion. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.2" osisID="1Kgs.8.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everyone in Israel assembled before King Solomon in the seventh month, the month of Ethanim,<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.2" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.2!note.x">September–October, Tishrei; Ethanim is a month from a Canaanite calendar.</note> during the festival. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.3" osisID="1Kgs.8.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When all of Israel’s elders had arrived, the priests picked up the chest. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.4" osisID="1Kgs.8.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They brought the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s chest, the meeting tent, and all the holy equipment that was in the tent. The priests and the Levites brought them up, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.5" osisID="1Kgs.8.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">while King Solomon and the entire Israelite assembly that had joined him before the chest sacrificed countless sheep and oxen. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.6" osisID="1Kgs.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests brought the chest containing the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s covenant to its designated spot beneath the wings of the winged creatures in the inner sanctuary of the temple, the most holy place. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.7" osisID="1Kgs.8.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The winged creatures spread their wings over the place where the chest rested, covering the chest and its carrying poles. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.8" osisID="1Kgs.8.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The carrying poles were so long that their tips could be seen from the holy place in front of the inner sanctuary, though they weren’t visible from outside. They are still there today. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.9" osisID="1Kgs.8.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nothing was in the chest except the two stone tablets Moses had placed there while at Horeb, where the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made a covenant with the Israelites after they left Egypt. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.10" osisID="1Kgs.8.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the priests left the holy place, the cloud filled the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.11" osisID="1Kgs.8.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and the priests were unable to carry out their duties due to the cloud because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s glory filled the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.12" osisID="1Kgs.8.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon said, <q type="x-start">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said that he would live in a dark cloud,</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.13" osisID="1Kgs.8.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">but I have indeed built you a lofty temple as a place where you can live forever.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.14" osisID="1Kgs.8.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king turned around, and while the entire assembly of Israel was standing there, he blessed them, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.15" osisID="1Kgs.8.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">saying, “Bless Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, who spoke directly to my father David and now has kept his promise: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.16" osisID="1Kgs.8.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">‘From the day I brought my people Israel out of Egypt I haven’t selected a city from any Israelite tribe as a site for the building of a temple for my name. But now I have chosen David to be over my people Israel.’ </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.17" osisID="1Kgs.8.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My father David wanted to build a temple for the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.18" osisID="1Kgs.8.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said to my father David, ‘It is very good that you thought to build a temple for my name.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.19" osisID="1Kgs.8.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Nevertheless, you yourself won’t build that temple. Instead, your very own son will build the temple for my name.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.20" osisID="1Kgs.8.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has kept his promise—I have succeeded my father David on Israel’s throne just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said, and I have built the temple for the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.21" osisID="1Kgs.8.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">There I’ve placed the chest that contains the covenant that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made with our ancestors when he brought them out of Egypt.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.22" osisID="1Kgs.8.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon stood before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar in front of the entire Israelite assembly and, spreading out his hands toward the sky, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.23" osisID="1Kgs.8.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">he said:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.23" osisID="1Kgs.8.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel, there’s no god like you in heaven above or on earth below. You keep the covenant and show loyalty to your servants who walk before you with all their heart. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.24" osisID="1Kgs.8.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is the covenant you kept with your servant David, my father, which you promised him. Today, you have fulfilled what you promised. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.25" osisID="1Kgs.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, keep what you promised my father David, your servant, when you said to him, <q type="x-complete">You will never fail to have a successor sitting on Israel’s throne as long as your descendants carefully walk before me just as you walked before me.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.26" osisID="1Kgs.8.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now, God of Israel, may your promise to your servant David, my father, come true.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.27" osisID="1Kgs.8.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But how could God possibly live on earth? If heaven, even the highest heaven, can’t contain you, how can this temple that I’ve built contain you? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.28" osisID="1Kgs.8.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God, listen to your servant’s prayer and request, and hear the cry and prayer that your servant prays to you today. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.29" osisID="1Kgs.8.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Constantly watch over this temple, the place about which you said, <q type="x-complete">My name will be there,</q> and listen to the prayer that your servant is praying toward<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.29" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.29!note.y">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">for, regarding</hi>; also used in several verses that follow</note> this place. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.30" osisID="1Kgs.8.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen to the request of your servant and your people Israel when they pray toward this place. Listen from your heavenly dwelling place, and when you hear, forgive!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.31" osisID="1Kgs.8.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If someone wrongs another and must make a solemn pledge asserting innocence before your altar in this temple,<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.31" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.31!note.z">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.32" osisID="1Kgs.8.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven, act, and decide which of your servants is right. Condemn the guilty party, repaying them for their conduct, but justify the innocent person, repaying them for their righteousness.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.33" osisID="1Kgs.8.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If your people Israel are defeated by an enemy because they have sinned against you, but then they change their hearts and lives, give thanks to your name, and ask for mercy before you at this temple, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.34" osisID="1Kgs.8.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven and forgive the sin of your people Israel. Return them to the land you gave their ancestors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.35" osisID="1Kgs.8.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the sky holds back its rain because Israel has sinned against you, but they then pray toward this place, give thanks to your name, and turn away from their sin because you have punished them for it,<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.35" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.35!note.a">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">answered them</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.36" osisID="1Kgs.8.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven and forgive the sin of your servants, your people Israel. Teach them the best way for them to follow, and send rain on your land that you gave to your people as an inheritance.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.37" osisID="1Kgs.8.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whenever there is a famine or plague in the land; or whenever there is blight, mildew, locust, or grasshopper; or whenever someone’s enemy attacks them in their cities;<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.37" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.37!note.b">LXX <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">one of</hi>; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the land of their gates</hi></note> or any plague or illness comes; </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.38" osisID="1Kgs.8.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">whatever prayer or petition is made by any individual or by all of your people Israel—because people will recognize their own pain and spread out their hands toward this temple—</verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.39" osisID="1Kgs.8.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven where you live. Forgive, act, and repay each person according to all their conduct, because you know their hearts. You alone know the human heart. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.40" osisID="1Kgs.8.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Do this so that they may revere you all the days they live on the land that you gave to our ancestors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.41" osisID="1Kgs.8.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen also to the immigrant who isn’t from your people Israel but who comes from a distant country because of your reputation—</verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.42" osisID="1Kgs.8.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">because they will hear of your great reputation, your great power, and your outstretched arm. When the immigrant comes and prays toward this temple, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.43" osisID="1Kgs.8.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven, where you live, and do everything the immigrant asks. Do this so that all the people of the earth may know your reputation and revere you, as your people Israel do, and recognize that this temple I have built bears your name.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.44" osisID="1Kgs.8.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When your people go to war against their enemies, wherever you may send them, and they pray to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> toward the city you have chosen and toward this temple that I have built for your name, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.45" osisID="1Kgs.8.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven to their prayer and request and do what is right for them.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.46" osisID="1Kgs.8.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they sin against you (for there is no one who doesn’t sin) and you become angry with them and hand them over to an enemy who takes them away as prisoners to enemy territory, whether distant or nearby, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.47" osisID="1Kgs.8.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">if they change their heart in whatever land they are held captive, changing their lives and begging for your mercy,<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.47" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.47!note.c">Heb adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the land they are held captive.</hi></note> saying, <q type="x-complete">We have sinned, we have done wrong, we have acted wickedly!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.48" osisID="1Kgs.8.48" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and if they return to you with all their heart and all their being in the enemy territory where they’ve been taken captive, and pray to you, toward their land, which you gave their ancestors, toward the city you have chosen, and toward the temple I have built for your name, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.49" osisID="1Kgs.8.49" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen to their prayer and request from your heavenly dwelling place. Do what is right for them, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.50" osisID="1Kgs.8.50" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and forgive your people who have sinned against you. Forgive all their wrong that they have done against you. See to it that those who captured them show them mercy. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.51" osisID="1Kgs.8.51" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These are your people and your inheritance. You brought them out of Egypt, from the iron furnace.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.52" osisID="1Kgs.8.52" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Open your eyes to your servant’s request and to the request of your people Israel. Hear them whenever they cry out to you. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.53" osisID="1Kgs.8.53" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You set them apart from all the earth’s peoples as your own inheritance, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, just as you promised through your servant Moses when you brought our ancestors out of Egypt.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.54" osisID="1Kgs.8.54" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as Solomon finished praying and making these requests to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, he got up from before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar, where he had been kneeling with his hands spread out to heaven. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.55" osisID="1Kgs.8.55" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He stood up and blessed the whole Israelite assembly in a loud voice: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.56" osisID="1Kgs.8.56" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">May the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> be blessed! He has given rest to his people Israel just as he promised. He hasn’t neglected any part of the good promise he made through his servant Moses.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.57" osisID="1Kgs.8.57" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">May the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God be with us, just as he was with our ancestors. May he never leave us or abandon us.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.58" osisID="1Kgs.8.58" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">May he draw our hearts to him to walk in all his ways and observe his commands, his laws, and his judgments that he gave our ancestors.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.59" osisID="1Kgs.8.59" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">And may these words of mine that I have cried out before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> remain near to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God day and night so that he may do right by his servant and his people Israel for each day’s need,</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.60" osisID="1Kgs.8.60" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">and so that all the earth’s peoples may know that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is God. There is no other God!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.61" osisID="1Kgs.8.61" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now may you be committed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God with all your heart by following his laws and observing his commands, just as you are doing right now.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.8.62" osisID="1Kgs.8.62" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king and all Israel with him sacrificed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.63" osisID="1Kgs.8.63" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon offered well-being sacrifices to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>: twenty-two thousand oxen and one hundred twenty thousand sheep when the king and all Israel dedicated the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.64" osisID="1Kgs.8.64" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On that day the king made holy the middle of the courtyard in front of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. He had to offer the entirely burned offerings, grain offerings, and the fat of well-being sacrifices there, because the bronze altar that was in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s presence was too small to contain the entirely burned offerings, the grain offerings, and the fat of the well-being sacrifices. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.65" osisID="1Kgs.8.65" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time Solomon, together with all Israel, held a celebration. It was a large assembly from Lebo-hamath to the border of Egypt. They celebrated for seven days and then for another seven days in the presence of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God: fourteen days in all. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.8.66" osisID="1Kgs.8.66" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the eighth day,<note osisRef="1Kgs.8.66" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.8.66!note.d">The second seven-day celebration (see 2 Chron 7:8–9); but contrast LXX.</note> Solomon dismissed the people. They blessed the king and went back to their tents happy and pleased about all the good that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had done for his servant David and for his people Israel.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.9" osisID="1Kgs.9" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="9"><div scope="1Kgs.9.1-1Kgs.9.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon again meets God</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Kgs.9.1" osisID="1Kgs.9.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now once Solomon finished building the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, the royal palace, and everything else he wanted to accomplish, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.2" osisID="1Kgs.9.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> appeared to him a second time in the same way he had appeared to him at Gibeon. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.3" osisID="1Kgs.9.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said to him, <q type="x-start">I have heard your prayer and your cry to me. I have set apart this temple that you built, to put my name there forever. My eyes and my heart will always be there.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.4" osisID="1Kgs.9.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">As for you, if you walk before me just as your father David did, with complete dedication and honesty, and if you do all that I have commanded, and keep my regulations and case laws,</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.5" osisID="1Kgs.9.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">then I will establish your royal throne over Israel forever, just as I promised your father David, ‘You will never fail to have a successor on the throne of Israel.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.6" osisID="1Kgs.9.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">However, if you or your sons turn away from following me and don’t observe the commands and regulations that I gave you, and go to serve other gods, and worship them,</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.7" osisID="1Kgs.9.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">then I will remove Israel from the land I gave them and I will reject the temple that I dedicated for my name. Israel will become a joke, insulted by everyone.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.8" osisID="1Kgs.9.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Everyone who passes by this temple, so lofty now,<note osisRef="1Kgs.9.8" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.9.8!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">will become high</hi>; OL, Syr, Tg <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">will become a ruin</hi></note> will be shocked and will whistle, wondering, Why has the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> done such a thing to this land and this temple?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.9" osisID="1Kgs.9.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">The answer will come: Because they deserted the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> their God, who brought their ancestors out of Egypt’s land. They embraced other gods, worshipping and serving them. That is why the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> brought all this disaster on them.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="1Kgs.9.10-1Kgs.9.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s buildings and prosperity</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.9.10" osisID="1Kgs.9.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It took twenty years for Solomon to build the two structures, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and the royal palace. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.11" osisID="1Kgs.9.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Hiram of Tyre gave Solomon all the cedar, pinewood, and gold that he wanted. Then King Solomon gave Hiram twenty towns in the region of Galilee. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.12" osisID="1Kgs.9.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hiram went from Tyre to inspect the towns Solomon had given him. They didn’t seem adequate in his view. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.13" osisID="1Kgs.9.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Hiram remarked, <q type="x-complete">My brother, are these towns you’ve given me good for anything?</q> The cities are thus called the land of Cabul to this very day. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.14" osisID="1Kgs.9.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Hiram sent the king one hundred twenty gold kikkars, nevertheless.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.9.15" osisID="1Kgs.9.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is the story of the labor gang that King Solomon put together to build the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and his own palace, as well as the stepped structure, the wall of Jerusalem, Hazor, Megiddo, and Gezer: (</verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.16" osisID="1Kgs.9.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pharaoh, Egypt’s king, had attacked and captured Gezer, setting it on fire. He killed the Canaanites who lived in the city and gave it as a dowry to his daughter, Solomon’s wife.) </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.17" osisID="1Kgs.9.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon built Gezer, Lower Beth-horon, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.18" osisID="1Kgs.9.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baalath, and Tamar in the wilderness (within the land), </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.19" osisID="1Kgs.9.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">along with all the storage cities that belonged to Solomon, as well as the cities used for storing chariots and cavalry and whatever he wanted to build in Jerusalem, Lebanon, and throughout his kingdom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.20" osisID="1Kgs.9.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Any non-Israelite people who remained of the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites—</verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.21" osisID="1Kgs.9.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">that is, the descendants of such people who were still in the land because the Israelites weren’t able to wipe them out—Solomon forced into the labor gangs that are still in existence today. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.22" osisID="1Kgs.9.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, Solomon didn’t force the Israelites to work as slaves; instead, they became warriors, his servants, his leaders, his officers, and those in charge of his chariots and cavalry.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.9.23" osisID="1Kgs.9.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These were the chief officers over Solomon’s work: five hundred fifty had charge of the people who did the work. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.24" osisID="1Kgs.9.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Pharaoh’s daughter went up from David’s City to the palace he had built for her, Solomon built the stepped structure. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.25" osisID="1Kgs.9.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Three times a year Solomon would offer entirely burned offerings and well-being sacrifices on the altar that he had built for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. Along with this he would burn incense to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. In this way, he completed the temple.<note osisRef="1Kgs.9.25" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.9.25!note.f">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.26" osisID="1Kgs.9.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon built a fleet near Eloth in Ezion-geber, on the coast of the Reed Sea<note osisRef="1Kgs.9.26" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.9.26!note.g">Traditionally <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Red Sea</hi></note> in the land of Edom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.27" osisID="1Kgs.9.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hiram sent his expert sailors on the fleet along with Solomon’s workers. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.9.28" osisID="1Kgs.9.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They went to Ophir for four hundred twenty kikkars of gold, which they brought back to King Solomon.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.10" osisID="1Kgs.10" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="10"><div scope="1Kgs.10.1-1Kgs.10.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Queen of Sheba</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.1" osisID="1Kgs.10.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the queen of Sheba heard reports about Solomon, due to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s name,<note osisRef="1Kgs.10.1" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.10.1!note.h">Heb uncertain</note> she came to test him with riddles. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.2" osisID="1Kgs.10.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Accompanying her to Jerusalem was a huge entourage with camels carrying spices, a large amount of gold, and precious stones. After she arrived, she told Solomon everything that was on her mind. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.3" osisID="1Kgs.10.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon answered all her questions; nothing was too difficult for him to answer. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.4" osisID="1Kgs.10.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the queen of Sheba saw how wise Solomon was, the palace he had built, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.5" osisID="1Kgs.10.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the food on his table, the servants’ quarters, the function and dress of his attendants, his cupbearers, and the entirely burned offerings that he offered at the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, it took her breath away.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.6" osisID="1Kgs.10.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">The report I heard about your deeds and wisdom when I was still at home is true,</q> she said to the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.7" osisID="1Kgs.10.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">I didn’t believe it until I came and saw it with my own eyes. In fact, the half of it wasn’t even told to me! You have far more wisdom and wealth than I was told.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.8" osisID="1Kgs.10.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Your people and these servants who continually serve you and get to listen to your wisdom are truly happy!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.9" osisID="1Kgs.10.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Bless the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God because he was pleased to place you on Israel’s throne. Because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> loved Israel with an eternal love, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made you king to uphold justice and righteousness.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.10" osisID="1Kgs.10.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The queen gave the king one hundred twenty kikkars of gold, a great quantity of spice, and precious stones. Never again has so much spice come to Israel as when the queen of Sheba gave this gift to King Solomon. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.11" osisID="1Kgs.10.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hiram’s fleet went to Ophir and brought back gold, much almug wood, and precious stones. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.12" osisID="1Kgs.10.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king used the almug wood to make parapets for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and for the royal palace as well as lyres and harps for the musicians. To this day, that much almug wood hasn’t come into or been seen in Israel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.13" osisID="1Kgs.10.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon gave the queen of Sheba everything she wanted and all that she had asked for, in addition to what he had already given her from his own personal funds. Then she and her servants returned to her homeland.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.10.14-1Kgs.10.29" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s wealth</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.14" osisID="1Kgs.10.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon received an annual income of six hundred sixty-six kikkars of gold, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.15" osisID="1Kgs.10.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">not including income from the traders, the merchants and their profits, all the Arabian kings, and the officials of the land. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.16" osisID="1Kgs.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon made two hundred body-sized shields of hammered gold, using fifteen pounds<note osisRef="1Kgs.10.16" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.10.16!note.i">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">six hundred </hi>(shekels)</note> of gold in each shield, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.17" osisID="1Kgs.10.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and three hundred small shields of hammered gold, using sixty ounces<note osisRef="1Kgs.10.17" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.10.17!note.j"><hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">three manehs</hi></note> of gold in each shield. The king placed these in the Forest of Lebanon Palace.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.18" osisID="1Kgs.10.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king also made a large ivory throne and covered it with pure gold. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.19" osisID="1Kgs.10.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Six steps led up to the throne, and the back of the throne was rounded at the top. Two lions stood beside the armrests on both sides of the throne. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.20" osisID="1Kgs.10.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Another twelve lions stood on both sides of the six steps. No other kingdom had anything like this. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.21" osisID="1Kgs.10.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All of King Solomon’s drinking cups were made of gold, and all the items in the Forest of Lebanon Palace were made of pure gold, not silver, since even silver wasn’t considered good enough in Solomon’s time! </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.22" osisID="1Kgs.10.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The royal fleet of Tarshish-style ships was at sea with Hiram’s fleet, returning once every three years with gold, silver, ivory, monkeys, and peacocks.<note osisRef="1Kgs.10.22" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.10.22!note.k">Heb uncertain</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.23" osisID="1Kgs.10.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon far exceeded all the earth’s kings in wealth and wisdom, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.24" osisID="1Kgs.10.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and so the whole earth wanted an audience with Solomon in order to hear his God-given wisdom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.25" osisID="1Kgs.10.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Year after year they came with tribute: objects of silver and gold, clothing, weapons, spices, horses, and mules.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.10.26" osisID="1Kgs.10.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon acquired more and more chariots and horses until he had fourteen hundred chariots and twelve thousand horses that he kept in chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.27" osisID="1Kgs.10.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In Jerusalem, the king made silver as common as stones and cedar as plentiful as sycamore trees that grow in the foothills. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.28" osisID="1Kgs.10.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon’s horses were imported from Egypt and Kue, purchased from Kue by the king’s agents at the going price. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.10.29" osisID="1Kgs.10.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They would import a chariot from Egypt for six hundred pieces of silver and a horse for one hundred fifty, and then export them to all the Hittite and Aramean kings.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.11" osisID="1Kgs.11" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="11"><div scope="1Kgs.11.1-1Kgs.11.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon meets God a third time</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.1" osisID="1Kgs.11.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In addition to Pharaoh’s daughter, King Solomon loved many foreign women, including Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites, Sidonians, and Hittites. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.2" osisID="1Kgs.11.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These came from the nations that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had commanded the Israelites about: <q type="x-complete">Don’t intermarry with them. They will definitely turn your heart toward their gods.</q> Solomon clung to these women in love. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.3" osisID="1Kgs.11.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He had seven hundred royal wives and three hundred secondary wives. They turned his heart. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.4" osisID="1Kgs.11.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As Solomon grew old, his wives turned his heart after other gods. He wasn’t committed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God with all his heart as was his father David. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.5" osisID="1Kgs.11.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon followed Astarte the goddess of the Sidonians, and Milcom the detestable god of the Ammonites. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.6" osisID="1Kgs.11.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes and wasn’t completely devoted to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> like his father David. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.7" osisID="1Kgs.11.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the hill east of Jerusalem, Solomon built a shrine to Chemosh the detestable god of Moab, and to Molech the detestable god of the Ammonites. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.8" osisID="1Kgs.11.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did the same for all his foreign wives, who burned incense and sacrificed to their gods. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.9" osisID="1Kgs.11.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> grew angry with Solomon, because his heart had turned away from being with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of Israel, who had appeared to him twice. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.10" osisID="1Kgs.11.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had commanded Solomon about this very thing, that he shouldn’t follow other gods. But Solomon didn’t do what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> commanded.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.11" osisID="1Kgs.11.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said to Solomon, <q type="x-start">Because you have done all this instead of keeping my covenant and my laws that I commanded you, I will most certainly tear the kingdom from you and give it to your servant.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.12" osisID="1Kgs.11.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Even so, on account of your father David, I won’t do it during your lifetime. I will tear the kingdom out of your son’s hands.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.13" osisID="1Kgs.11.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Moreover, I won’t tear away the entire kingdom. I will give one tribe to your son on account of my servant David and on account of Jerusalem, which I have chosen.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="1Kgs.11.14-1Kgs.11.22" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon and Hadad</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.14" osisID="1Kgs.11.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> raised up an opponent for Solomon: Hadad the Edomite from the royal line of Edom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.15" osisID="1Kgs.11.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When David was fighting against Edom, Joab the general had gone up to bury the Israelite dead, and he had killed every male in Edom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.16" osisID="1Kgs.11.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Joab and all the Israelites stayed there six months, until he had finished off every male in Edom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.17" osisID="1Kgs.11.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While still a youth, Hadad escaped to Egypt along with his father’s Edomite officials. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.18" osisID="1Kgs.11.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They set out from Midian and went to Paran. They took men with them from Paran and came to Egypt and to Pharaoh its king. Pharaoh assigned him a home, food, and land. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.19" osisID="1Kgs.11.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pharaoh was so delighted with Hadad that he gave him one of his wife’s sisters for marriage, a sister of Queen Tahpenes. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.20" osisID="1Kgs.11.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This sister of Tahpenes bore Hadad a son, Genubath. Tahpenes weaned him in Pharaoh’s house. So it was that Genubath was raised in Pharaoh’s house, among Pharaoh’s children. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.21" osisID="1Kgs.11.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While in Egypt, Hadad heard that David had lain down with his ancestors and that Joab the general was also dead. Hadad said to Pharaoh, <q type="x-complete">Let me go to my homeland.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.22" osisID="1Kgs.11.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Pharaoh said to him, <q type="x-complete">What do you lack here with me that would make you want to go back to your homeland?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.22" osisID="1Kgs.11.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Hadad said, <q type="x-complete">Nothing, but please let me go!</q></verse></p></div><div scope="1Kgs.11.23-1Kgs.11.25" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon and Rezon</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.23" osisID="1Kgs.11.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God raised up another opponent for Solomon: Rezon, Eliada’s son, who had escaped from Zobah’s King Hadadezer. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.24" osisID="1Kgs.11.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rezon recruited men and became leader of a band when David was killing them. They went to Damascus, stayed there, and ruled it. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.25" osisID="1Kgs.11.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Throughout Solomon’s lifetime, Rezon was Israel’s opponent and added to the problems caused by Hadad. Rezon hated Israel while he ruled as king of Aram.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.11.26-1Kgs.11.40" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon and Jeroboam</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.26" osisID="1Kgs.11.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Nebat’s son Jeroboam was an Ephraimite from Zeredah. His mother’s name was Zeruah; she was a widow. Although he was one of Solomon’s own officials, Jeroboam fought against the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.27" osisID="1Kgs.11.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">This is the story of why Jeroboam fought against the king:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.27" osisID="1Kgs.11.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Solomon had built the stepped structure and repaired the broken wall in his father David’s City. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.28" osisID="1Kgs.11.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Jeroboam was a strong and honorable man. Solomon saw how well this youth did his work. So he appointed him over all the work gang of Joseph’s house.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.29" osisID="1Kgs.11.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time, when Jeroboam left Jerusalem, Ahijah the prophet of Shiloh met him along the way. Ahijah was wearing a new garment. The two of them were alone in the country. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.30" osisID="1Kgs.11.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahijah tore his new garment into twelve pieces. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.31" osisID="1Kgs.11.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said to Jeroboam, <q type="x-start">Take ten pieces, because Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, has said, ‘Look, I am about to tear the kingdom from Solomon’s hand. I will give you ten tribes.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.32" osisID="1Kgs.11.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But I will leave him one tribe on account of my servant David and on account of Jerusalem, the city I have chosen from all the tribes of Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.33" osisID="1Kgs.11.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I am doing this because they have abandoned me<note osisRef="1Kgs.11.33" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.11.33!note.l">LXX, Syr, Vulg <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he has abandoned me</hi></note> and worshipped the Sidonian goddess Astarte, the Moabite god Chemosh, and the Ammonite god Milcom. They haven’t walked in my ways by doing what is right in my eyes—keeping my laws and judgments—as Solomon’s father David did.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.34" osisID="1Kgs.11.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But I won’t take the whole kingdom from his hand. I will keep him as ruler throughout his lifetime on account of my servant David, who did keep my commands and my laws.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.35" osisID="1Kgs.11.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I will take the kingdom from the hand of Solomon’s son, and I will give you ten tribes.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.36" osisID="1Kgs.11.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I will give his son a single tribe so that my servant David will always have a lamp before me in Jerusalem, the city that I chose for myself to place my name.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.37" osisID="1Kgs.11.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But I will accept you, and you will rule over all that you could desire. You will be king of Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.38" osisID="1Kgs.11.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">If you listen to all that I command and walk in my ways, if you do what is right in my eyes, keeping my laws and my commands just as my servant David did, then I will be with you and I will build you a lasting dynasty just as I did for David. I will give you Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.39" osisID="1Kgs.11.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">I will humble David’s descendants by means of all this, though not forever.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.40" osisID="1Kgs.11.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon tried to kill Jeroboam. But Jeroboam fled to Egypt and its king Shishak. Jeroboam remained in Egypt until Solomon died.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.11.41-1Kgs.11.43" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s remaining days</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.11.41" osisID="1Kgs.11.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Solomon’s deeds, including all that he did and all his wisdom, aren’t they written in the official records of Solomon? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.42" osisID="1Kgs.11.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The amount of time Solomon ruled over all Israel in Jerusalem was forty years. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.11.43" osisID="1Kgs.11.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon lay down with his ancestors. He was buried in his father David’s City, and Rehoboam his son succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.12" osisID="1Kgs.12" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="12"><div scope="1Kgs.12.1-1Kgs.12.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">How Rehoboam lost the kingdom</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.1" osisID="1Kgs.12.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam went to Shechem where all Israel had come to make him king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.2" osisID="1Kgs.12.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, heard the news, he returned from Egypt where he had fled from King Solomon. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.3" osisID="1Kgs.12.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people sent and called for Jeroboam, who along with the entire Israelite assembly went and said to Rehoboam, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.4" osisID="1Kgs.12.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Your father made our workload<note osisRef="1Kgs.12.4" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.12.4!note.m">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">our yoke</hi>; also in the verses that follow</note> very hard for us. If you will lessen the demands your father made of us and lighten the heavy workload he demanded from us, then we will serve you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.5" osisID="1Kgs.12.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He answered them, <q type="x-complete">Come back in three days.</q> So the people left.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.6" osisID="1Kgs.12.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Rehoboam consulted the elders who had served his father Solomon when he was alive. <q type="x-complete">What do you advise?</q> Rehoboam asked. <q type="x-complete">How should I respond to these people?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.7" osisID="1Kgs.12.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">If you will be a servant to this people by answering them and speaking good words today,</q> they replied, <q type="x-complete">then they will be your servants forever.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.8" osisID="1Kgs.12.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Rehoboam ignored the advice the elders gave him and instead sought the counsel of the young advisors who had grown up with him and now served him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.9" osisID="1Kgs.12.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">What do you advise?</q> he asked them. <q type="x-complete">How should we respond to these people who have said to me, ‘Lighten the workload your father demanded of us’?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.10" osisID="1Kgs.12.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The young people who had grown up with him said to him, <q type="x-start">This people said to you, ‘Your father made our workload heavy; lighten it for us!’ Now this is what you should say to them: ‘My baby finger<note osisRef="1Kgs.12.10" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.12.10!note.n">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">pinky finger</hi>, perhaps a euphemism</note> is thicker than my father’s entire waist!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.11" osisID="1Kgs.12.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">So if my father made your workload heavy, I’ll make it even heavier! If my father disciplined you with whips, I’ll do it with scorpions!’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.12" osisID="1Kgs.12.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam and all the people returned to Rehoboam on the third day, just as the king had specified when he said, <q type="x-complete">Come back to me in three days.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.13" osisID="1Kgs.12.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king then answered the people harshly. He ignored the elders’ advice </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.14" osisID="1Kgs.12.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and instead followed the young people’s advice. He said, <q type="x-complete">My father made your workload heavy, but I’ll make it even heavier! My father disciplined you with whips, but I’ll do it with scorpions!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.15" osisID="1Kgs.12.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king didn’t listen to the people because this turn of events came from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> so that he might keep the promise he delivered through Ahijah from Shiloh concerning Jeroboam, Nebat’s son. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">When all Israel saw that the king wouldn’t listen to them, the people answered the king:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-start">Why should we care about David?</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">We have no stake in Jesse’s son!</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">Go back to your homes, Israel!</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">You better look</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-end">after your own house now, David!</q></verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.16" osisID="1Kgs.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Then the Israelites went back to their homes, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.17" osisID="1Kgs.12.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and Rehoboam ruled over only the Israelites who lived in the cities of Judah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.18" osisID="1Kgs.12.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When King Rehoboam sent Adoram to them (he was the leader of the work gang), all Israel stoned him to death. King Rehoboam quickly got into his chariot and fled to Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.19" osisID="1Kgs.12.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel has been in rebellion against the house of David to this day. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.20" osisID="1Kgs.12.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">When all Israel heard that Jeroboam had returned, they sent for him. They called him to the assembly and crowned him king of all Israel.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.20" osisID="1Kgs.12.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Nothing was left to the house of David except the tribe of Judah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.21" osisID="1Kgs.12.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Rehoboam arrived at Jerusalem, he assembled the whole house of Judah and the tribe of Benjamin—one hundred eighty thousand select warriors—to fight against the house of Israel and restore the kingdom for Rehoboam, Solomon’s son. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.22" osisID="1Kgs.12.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But God’s word came to Shemaiah the man of God, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.23" osisID="1Kgs.12.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">Tell Judah’s King Rehoboam, Solomon’s son, and all the house of Judah and Benjamin, and the rest of the people,</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.24" osisID="1Kgs.12.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">‘This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: Don’t make war against your relatives the Israelites. Go home, every one of you, because this is my plan.’</q> When they heard the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s words, they went back home, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had said.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.12.25-1Kgs.12.33" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jeroboam I and the shrines</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.12.25" osisID="1Kgs.12.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam fortified Shechem at Mount Ephraim and lived there. From there he also fortified Penuel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.26" osisID="1Kgs.12.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam thought to himself, The kingdom is in danger of reverting to the house of David. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.27" osisID="1Kgs.12.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If these people continue to sacrifice at the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple in Jerusalem, they will again become loyal to their master Rehoboam, Judah’s king, and they will kill me so they can return to Judah’s King Rehoboam. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.28" osisID="1Kgs.12.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the king asked for advice and then made two gold calves. He said to the people, <q type="x-complete">It’s too far for you to go all the way up to Jerusalem. Look, Israel! Here are your gods who brought you out from the land of Egypt.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.29" osisID="1Kgs.12.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He put one calf in Bethel, and the other he placed in Dan. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.30" osisID="1Kgs.12.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This act was sinful. The people went to worship before the one calf at Bethel and before the other one as far as Dan.<note osisRef="1Kgs.12.30" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.12.30!note.o">Cf LXX; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">before the one at Bethel.</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.31" osisID="1Kgs.12.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam made shrines on the high places and appointed priests from all sorts of people, but none were Levites. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.32" osisID="1Kgs.12.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam set a date for a celebration on the fifteenth day of the eighth month.<note osisRef="1Kgs.12.32" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.12.32!note.p">October–November</note> It was just like the celebration in Judah. He sacrificed on the altar. At Bethel he sacrificed to the calves he had made. There also he installed the priests for the shrines he had made. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.12.33" osisID="1Kgs.12.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the fifteenth day of the eighth month—the time he alone had decided—Jeroboam went up<note osisRef="1Kgs.12.33" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.12.33!note.q">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">offered sacrifices</hi></note> to the altar he had built in Bethel. He made a celebration for the Israelites and offered sacrifices on the altar by burning them up.<note osisRef="1Kgs.13.33" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.13.33!note.r">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">went up on the altar to burn incense</hi></note></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.13" osisID="1Kgs.13" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="13"><div scope="1Kgs.13.1-1Kgs.13.34" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jeroboam I and the man of God</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.1" osisID="1Kgs.13.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A man of God came from Judah by God’s command to Bethel. Jeroboam was standing at the altar burning incense. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.2" osisID="1Kgs.13.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">By the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word, the man of God cried out to the altar: <q type="x-complete">Altar! Altar! The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says this: Look! A son will be born to the house of David. His name will be Josiah. He will sacrifice on you, Altar, the very priests of the shrines who offer incense on you. They will burn human bones on you.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.3" osisID="1Kgs.13.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time the man of God gave a sign: <q type="x-complete">This is the sign that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> mentioned: ‘Look! The altar will be broken apart, and its ashes will spill out.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.4" osisID="1Kgs.13.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the king heard the word of the man of God and how he cried out to the altar at Bethel, Jeroboam stretched his hand from the altar and said, <q type="x-complete">Seize him!</q> But the hand that Jeroboam stretched out against the man of God grew stiff. Jeroboam wasn’t able to bend it back to himself. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.5" osisID="1Kgs.13.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The altar broke apart, and the ashes spilled out from the altar, just like the sign that the man of God gave by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.6" osisID="1Kgs.13.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king said to the man of God, <q type="x-complete">Plead before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God and pray for me so that I can bend my hand back again.</q> So the man of God pleaded before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, and the king’s hand returned to normal and was like it used to be. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.7" osisID="1Kgs.13.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king spoke to the man of God: <q type="x-complete">Come with me to the palace and refresh yourself. Let me give you a gift.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.8" osisID="1Kgs.13.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The man of God said to the king, <q type="x-start">Even if you gave me half your palace, I wouldn’t go with you, nor would I eat food or drink water in this place.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.9" osisID="1Kgs.13.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">This is what God commanded me by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word: Don’t eat food! Don’t drink water! Don’t return by the way you came!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.10" osisID="1Kgs.13.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the man of God went by a different way. He didn’t return by the way he came to Bethel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.11" osisID="1Kgs.13.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now there was an old prophet living in Bethel. His sons came and told him everything that the man of God had done that day at Bethel. They also told their father the words that he spoke to the king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.12" osisID="1Kgs.13.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Which way did he go?</q> their father asked them. His sons had seen the way the man of God went when he came from Judah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.13" osisID="1Kgs.13.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The old prophet said to his sons, <q type="x-complete">Saddle my donkey.</q> So they saddled his donkey, and he got on it. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.14" osisID="1Kgs.13.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He went after the man of God and found him sitting underneath a terebinth tree. He said to him, <q type="x-complete">Are you the man of God who came from Judah?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.14" osisID="1Kgs.13.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">I am,</q> he replied.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.15" osisID="1Kgs.13.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The old prophet then said to him, <q type="x-complete">Come home with me and eat some food.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.16" osisID="1Kgs.13.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the man of God answered, <q type="x-start">I can’t return or go with you, and I can’t eat food or drink water with you in this place</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.17" osisID="1Kgs.13.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">because of the message that came to me from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word: Don’t eat food! Don’t drink water! Don’t return by the way you came!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.18" osisID="1Kgs.13.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The old prophet said to the man of God, <q type="x-complete">I’m also a prophet like you. A messenger spoke to me with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word, ‘Bring him back with you to your house so that he may eat food and drink water.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.18" osisID="1Kgs.13.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">But the old prophet was lying to him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.19" osisID="1Kgs.13.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the man of God went back with the old prophet. He ate food in his home and drank water. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.20" osisID="1Kgs.13.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then as they were sitting at the table, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to the prophet who had brought him back. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.21" osisID="1Kgs.13.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He cried out to the man of God who had come from Judah:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.21" osisID="1Kgs.13.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">“The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says this:</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.21" osisID="1Kgs.13.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">You rebelled against the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.21" osisID="1Kgs.13.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">You didn’t keep the command</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.21" osisID="1Kgs.13.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God gave you!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.22" osisID="1Kgs.13.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">You came back and ate food</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.22" osisID="1Kgs.13.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">and drank water in this place.</verse> </l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.22" osisID="1Kgs.13.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">But he had commanded you: ‘Don’t eat food! Don’t drink water!’ Now your body won’t go to the grave of your ancestors.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.23" osisID="1Kgs.13.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After he ate food and drank, the old prophet saddled the donkey for the prophet he had brought back. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.24" osisID="1Kgs.13.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The man of God departed, and a lion found him on the road and killed him. His body was thrown down on the road. The donkey stood beside it, and the lion also stood beside the body. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.25" osisID="1Kgs.13.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some people were traveling nearby, and they discovered the body thrown down on the road and the lion standing beside it. They entered the town where the old prophet lived and were talking about it. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.26" osisID="1Kgs.13.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The prophet who brought the man of God back from the road overheard. He thought: That’s the man of God who rebelled against the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s command. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has given him to that lion that tore him apart, killing him in agreement with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word that was spoken to him.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.27" osisID="1Kgs.13.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The old prophet told his sons, <q type="x-complete">Saddle the donkey.</q> They did so, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.28" osisID="1Kgs.13.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and he went and found the body thrown down on the road. The donkey and the lion were still standing beside the body. The lion hadn’t eaten the body, nor had it torn the donkey apart. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.29" osisID="1Kgs.13.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The prophet lifted the body of the man of God and put it on the donkey. He brought it back, arriving in the old prophet’s town to mourn and bury the man of God. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.30" osisID="1Kgs.13.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He placed the body in his own grave, and they mourned over him, <q type="x-complete">Oh, my brother!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.31" osisID="1Kgs.13.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After the old prophet buried him, he said to his sons, <q type="x-start">When I die, bury me in the grave where the man of God is. Put my bones beside his bones.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.32" osisID="1Kgs.13.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">The message he gave by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word concerning the altar of Bethel and all the shrines in the towns of Samaria will most certainly come true.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.13.33" osisID="1Kgs.13.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Even after this happened, Jeroboam didn’t change his evil ways. Instead, he continued to appoint all sorts of people as priests of the shrines. Anyone who wanted to be a priest Jeroboam made a priest for the shrines. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.13.34" osisID="1Kgs.13.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In this way the house of Jeroboam acted sinfully, leading to its downfall and elimination from the earth.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.14" osisID="1Kgs.14" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="14"><div scope="1Kgs.14.1-1Kgs.14.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Abijah’s illness</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.1" osisID="1Kgs.14.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time, Jeroboam’s son Abijah became sick. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.2" osisID="1Kgs.14.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam said to his wife, <q type="x-start">Please go with a disguise so no one will recognize you as Jeroboam’s wife. Go to Shiloh where the prophet Ahijah is. He told me I would be king of this people.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.3" osisID="1Kgs.14.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Take ten loaves of bread, cakes, and a bottle of honey with you. Go to him. He will tell you what will happen to the boy.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.4" osisID="1Kgs.14.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam’s wife did precisely this. She left and went to Shiloh and came to Ahijah’s house. Now Ahijah had become blind in his old age.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.5" osisID="1Kgs.14.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said to Ahijah, <q type="x-complete">Look! Jeroboam’s wife has come seeking a word from you about her son. He is sick. Say this and that to her. When she comes, she will be disguised.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.6" osisID="1Kgs.14.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Ahijah heard the sound of her feet coming through the doorway, he said, “Come in, Jeroboam’s wife! Why have you disguised yourself? I have hard news for you. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.7" osisID="1Kgs.14.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tell Jeroboam: This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, says: When I lifted you up from among the people, I appointed you as a leader over my people Israel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.8" osisID="1Kgs.14.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I tore the kingdom from David’s house and gave it to you. But you haven’t been like my servant David, who kept my commands and followed me with all his heart by doing only what is right in my eyes. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.9" osisID="1Kgs.14.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, you have done more evil than any who were before you. You have made other gods and metal images to anger me. You have turned your back on me. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.10" osisID="1Kgs.14.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, I’m going to bring disaster on Jeroboam’s house! Because of Jeroboam, I will eliminate everyone who urinates on a wall, whether slave or free. Then I will set fire to the house of Jeroboam, as one burns dung until it is gone. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.11" osisID="1Kgs.14.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Dogs will eat any of Jeroboam’s family who die in town. Birds will eat those who die in the field. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has spoken!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.12" osisID="1Kgs.14.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">As for you, get up and go back home. When your feet enter the town, the boy will die.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.13" osisID="1Kgs.14.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">All Israel will mourn for him and will bury him. Out of the whole line of Jeroboam, he alone will have a tomb, because only in him did Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, find something good.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.14" osisID="1Kgs.14.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">For this reason the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will raise up a king over Israel who will eliminate the house of Jeroboam. This begins today. What’s that? Even now!<note osisRef="1Kgs.14.14" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.14.14!note.s">Heb uncertain</note></q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.15" osisID="1Kgs.14.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will strike Israel so that it shakes like a reed in water. He will uproot Israel from this fertile land that he gave to their ancestors and their offspring, and he will scatter them across the Euphrates River, because they made the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> angry by making their sacred poles.<note osisRef="1Kgs.14.15" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.14.15!note.t">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim</hi>, perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note></q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.16" osisID="1Kgs.14.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Because of the sins Jeroboam committed, and because he made Israel sin too, God will give Israel up.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.17" osisID="1Kgs.14.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Jeroboam’s wife left and went to Tirzah. When she stepped across the threshold of the house, the boy died. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.18" osisID="1Kgs.14.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All Israel buried him and mourned him in agreement with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word spoken through his servant the prophet Ahijah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.19" osisID="1Kgs.14.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Jeroboam’s deeds—how he fought and how he ruled—are written in the official records of Israel’s kings. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.20" osisID="1Kgs.14.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam ruled twenty-two years and he lay down with his ancestors. His son Nadab succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.14.21-1Kgs.14.31" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Rehoboam rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.21" osisID="1Kgs.14.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam, Solomon’s son, ruled over Judah. Rehoboam was 41 years old when he became king. He ruled for seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> chose from among all the tribes of Israel to set his name. Rehoboam’s mother’s name was Naamah from Ammon. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.22" osisID="1Kgs.14.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Judah did evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes. The sins they committed made the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> angrier than anything their ancestors had done. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.23" osisID="1Kgs.14.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They also built shrines, standing stones, and sacred poles<note osisRef="1Kgs.14.23" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.14.23!note.u">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim</hi>, perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> on top of every high hill and under every green tree. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.24" osisID="1Kgs.14.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Moreover, the consecrated workers<note osisRef="1Kgs.14.24" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.14.24!note.v">Traditionally <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">cultic prostitutes</hi></note> in the land did detestable things, just like those nations that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had removed among the Israelites.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.14.25" osisID="1Kgs.14.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">During King Rehoboam’s fifth year, King Shishak of Egypt attacked Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.26" osisID="1Kgs.14.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He seized the treasures of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and the royal palace. He took everything, even all the gold shields that Solomon had made. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.27" osisID="1Kgs.14.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Rehoboam replaced them with bronze shields and assigned them to the officers of the guard who protected the entrance to the royal palace. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.28" osisID="1Kgs.14.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whenever the king entered the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, the guards would carry the shields and then return them to the guardroom. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.29" osisID="1Kgs.14.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Rehoboam’s deeds and all that he accomplished, aren’t they written in the official records of Judah’s kings? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.30" osisID="1Kgs.14.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was continual warfare between Rehoboam and Jeroboam. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.14.31" osisID="1Kgs.14.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Rehoboam died, he was buried with his ancestors in David’s City. His mother’s name was Naamah from Ammon. His son Abijam<note osisRef="1Kgs.14.31" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.14.31!note.w">Spelled <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Abijah </hi>in 2 Chron 12:16; LXX, Syr, Targ <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Abijah </hi>in 1 Kgs</note> succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.15" osisID="1Kgs.15" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="15"><div scope="1Kgs.15.1-1Kgs.15.8" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Abijam rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.15.1" osisID="1Kgs.15.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijam<note osisRef="1Kgs.15.1" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.15.1!note.x">Spelled <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Abijah </hi>in 2 Chron 12</note> became king of Judah in the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam, Nebat’s son. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.2" osisID="1Kgs.15.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ruled for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Maacah, and she was Abishalom’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.3" osisID="1Kgs.15.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijam followed all the sinful ways of his father before him. He didn’t follow the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God with all his heart like his ancestor David. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.4" osisID="1Kgs.15.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Even so, on account of David, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God gave Abijam a lamp in Jerusalem by supporting his son who succeeded him and by preserving Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.5" osisID="1Kgs.15.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This was because David did the right thing in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes. David didn’t deviate from anything the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> commanded him throughout his life—except in the matter of Uriah the Hittite. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.6" osisID="1Kgs.15.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam as long as Abijam lived. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.7" osisID="1Kgs.15.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Abijam’s deeds and all that he did, aren’t they written in the official records of Judah’s kings? There was war between Abijam and Jeroboam. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.8" osisID="1Kgs.15.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijam lay down with his ancestors; he was buried in David’s City. His son Asa succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.15.9-1Kgs.15.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Asa rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.15.9" osisID="1Kgs.15.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the twentieth year of Israel’s King Jeroboam, Asa became king of Judah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.10" osisID="1Kgs.15.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ruled in Jerusalem for forty-one years. His grandmother’s<note osisRef="1Kgs.15.10" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.15.10!note.y">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mother</hi>; also in 15:13; cf 2 Chron 13:2</note> name was Maacah; she was Abishalom’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.11" osisID="1Kgs.15.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa did the right things in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, just like his father David. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.12" osisID="1Kgs.15.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He removed the consecrated workers<note osisRef="1Kgs.15.12" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.15.12!note.z">Traditionally <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">cultic prostitutes</hi></note> from the land, and he did away with all the worthless idols that his predecessors had made. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.13" osisID="1Kgs.15.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He even removed his grandmother Maacah from the position of queen mother because she had made an image of Asherah. Asa cut down her image and burned it in the Kidron Valley. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.14" osisID="1Kgs.15.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Though the shrines weren’t eliminated, nevertheless Asa remained committed with all his heart to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> throughout his life. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.15" osisID="1Kgs.15.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He brought into the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple the silver and gold equipment that he and his father had dedicated. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.16" osisID="1Kgs.15.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was war between Asa and Israel’s King Baasha throughout their lifetimes. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.17" osisID="1Kgs.15.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s King Baasha attacked Judah and fortified Ramah to prevent Judah’s King Asa from moving into that area.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.15.18" osisID="1Kgs.15.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa took all the silver and gold that remained in the treasuries of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and the royal palace, and he gave them to his officials. Then King Asa sent them with the following message to Aram’s King Ben-hadad, Tabrimmon’s son and Hezion’s grandson, who ruled from Damascus: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.19" osisID="1Kgs.15.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Let’s make a covenant similar to the one between our fathers. Since I have already sent you a gift of silver and gold, break your covenant with Israel’s King Baasha so that he will leave me alone.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.20" osisID="1Kgs.15.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-hadad agreed with King Asa and sent his army commanders against the cities of Israel, attacking Ijon, Dan, Abel-beth-maacah, and all Chinneroth, along with all the land of Naphtali. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.21" osisID="1Kgs.15.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as Baasha learned this, he stopped building Ramah and stayed in Tirzah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.22" osisID="1Kgs.15.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Asa issued an order to every Judean without exception: all the people carried away the stone and timber that Baasha was using to build Ramah, and King Asa used it to build Geba of Benjamin and Mizpah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.23" osisID="1Kgs.15.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Asa’s deeds, his strength, and all that he did, as well as the towns that he built, aren’t they written in the official records of Judah’s kings? When he was old, Asa developed a severe foot disease. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.24" osisID="1Kgs.15.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He died and was buried with his ancestors in David’s City.<note osisRef="1Kgs.15.24" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.15.24!note.a">Heb adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">his father</hi>.</note> His son Jehoshaphat succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.15.25-1Kgs.15.32" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Nadab rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.15.25" osisID="1Kgs.15.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam’s son Nadab became king of Israel in the second year of Judah’s King Asa. He ruled over Israel for two years. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.26" osisID="1Kgs.15.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes by walking in the way of his father Jeroboam and the sin Jeroboam had caused Israel to commit. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.27" osisID="1Kgs.15.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baasha, Ahijah’s son from the house of Issachar, plotted against him and attacked him at Gibbethon, which belonged to the Philistines. Nadab and all Israel were laying siege against Gibbethon. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.28" osisID="1Kgs.15.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baasha killed Nadab in the third year of Judah’s King Asa and ruled in Nadab’s place.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.15.29" osisID="1Kgs.15.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When he became king, Baasha attacked the entire house of Jeroboam. He didn’t allow any living person to survive in Jeroboam’s family; he wiped them out according to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word spoken by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s servant Ahijah of Shiloh. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.30" osisID="1Kgs.15.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This happened because of Jeroboam’s sins that he committed and that he caused Israel to commit, and because he angered the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.31" osisID="1Kgs.15.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Nadab’s deeds and all that he did, aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s kings? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.32" osisID="1Kgs.15.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was war between Asa and Israel’s King Baasha throughout their lifetimes.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.15.33-1Kgs.15.34" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Baasha rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.15.33" osisID="1Kgs.15.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the third year of Judah’s King Asa, Baasha, Ahijah’s son, became king over all Israel. He ruled in Tirzah for twenty-four years. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.15.34" osisID="1Kgs.15.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes by walking in Jeroboam’s ways and the sin he had caused Israel to commit.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.16" osisID="1Kgs.16" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="16"><div scope="1Kgs16.1-1Kgs.16.7" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.1" osisID="1Kgs.16.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Jehu, Hanani’s son, against Baasha: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.2" osisID="1Kgs.16.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I raised you up from the dust and made you a leader over my people Israel, but you walked in Jeroboam’s ways, making my people Israel sin, making me angry with their sins. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.3" osisID="1Kgs.16.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So look, I am about to set fire to Baasha and his household, and I will make your house like the house of Jeroboam, Nebat’s son. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.4" osisID="1Kgs.16.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Dogs will eat any of Baasha’s family who die in town. Birds will eat any who die in the country.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.5" osisID="1Kgs.16.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now the rest of Baasha’s deeds, what he did, and his powerful acts, aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s kings? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.6" osisID="1Kgs.16.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baasha lay down with his ancestors and was buried in Tirzah. His son Elah succeeded him as king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.7" osisID="1Kgs.16.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came through the prophet Jehu, Hanani’s son, concerning Baasha and his house. It concerned everything evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes that Baasha had done, angering the Lord by his actions so that he would end up just like the house of Jeroboam. The message was also about how the Lord attacked Baasha.<note osisRef="1Kgs.16.7" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.16.7!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and also about how he attacked him </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and because Baasha had attacked Jeroboam</hi></note></verse></p></div><div scope="1Kgs.16.8-1Kgs.16.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Elah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.8" osisID="1Kgs.16.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the twenty-sixth year of Judah’s King Asa, Elah, Baasha’s son, became king over Israel. He ruled in Tirzah for two years. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.9" osisID="1Kgs.16.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zimri, his officer who led half the chariots, plotted against him. Elah was at Tirzah, getting drunk at the house of Arza, who had charge over the palace at Tirzah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.10" osisID="1Kgs.16.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zimri came, attacked, and killed Elah in the twenty-seventh year of Judah’s King Asa. Zimri succeeded him as king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.11" osisID="1Kgs.16.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Once Zimri became king and sat on the throne, he attacked all of Baasha’s house. He didn’t spare anyone who urinates on a wall, whether relative or friend. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.12" osisID="1Kgs.16.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zimri destroyed the entire house of Baasha in agreement with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word that had been spoken by the prophet Jehu to Baasha. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.13" osisID="1Kgs.16.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This happened because of all Baasha’s sins, as well as the sins of his son Elah and because they caused Israel to sin. They angered Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, with their insignificant idols. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.14" osisID="1Kgs.16.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Elah’s deeds and all that he did, aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s kings?</verse></p></div><div scope="1Kgs.16.15-1Kgs.16.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Zimri rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.15" osisID="1Kgs.16.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the twenty-seventh year of Judah’s King Asa, Zimri became king. He ruled in Tirzah for seven days. The army was camped at Gibbethon in Philistia. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.16" osisID="1Kgs.16.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They heard the news: <q type="x-complete">Zimri has plotted against the king and killed him.</q> Right then, in the camp, the whole Israelite army made their general Omri king of Israel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.17" osisID="1Kgs.16.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Omri and the entire army then went up from Gibbethon and laid siege to Tirzah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.18" osisID="1Kgs.16.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Zimri saw that the city was captured, he went into the fort of the royal palace and burned it down on top of himself. So he died. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.19" osisID="1Kgs.16.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This happened because of the sins Zimri had committed by doing evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes and by walking in Jeroboam’s ways and the sin he had done by causing Israel to sin. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.20" osisID="1Kgs.16.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Zimri’s deeds and the plot he carried out, aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s kings?</verse></p></div><div scope="1Kgs.16.21-1Kgs.16.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Omri rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.21" osisID="1Kgs.16.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At this time the people of Israel were split in two. One half of the people followed Tibni, Ginath’s son, making him king; the other half followed Omri. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.22" osisID="1Kgs.16.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Omri’s side was stronger than those who followed Tibni, Ginath’s son. So Tibni died and Omri became king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.23" osisID="1Kgs.16.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the thirty-first year of Judah’s King Asa, Omri became king of Israel. He ruled for twelve years, six of which were in Tirzah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.24" osisID="1Kgs.16.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He bought the hill of Samaria from Shemer for two kikkars of silver. He fortified the hill and named the town that he built there after Shemer, the previous owner of the hill of Samaria. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.25" osisID="1Kgs.16.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Omri did evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, more evil than anyone who preceded him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.26" osisID="1Kgs.16.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He walked in all the ways and sins of Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, because he caused Israel to sin. They angered Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, with their worthless idols. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.27" osisID="1Kgs.16.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Omri’s deeds and his powerful acts, aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s kings? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.28" osisID="1Kgs.16.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Omri lay down with his ancestors and was buried in Samaria. His son Ahab succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.16.29-1Kgs.16.34" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Ahab rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.16.29" osisID="1Kgs.16.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the thirty-eighth year of Judah’s King Asa, Ahab, Omri’s son, became king of Israel. He ruled over Israel in Samaria for twenty-two years </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.30" osisID="1Kgs.16.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and did evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, more than anyone who preceded him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.31" osisID="1Kgs.16.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab found it easy to walk in the sins of Jeroboam, Nebat’s son. He married Jezebel the daughter of Ethbaal, who was the king of the Sidonians. He served and worshipped Baal. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.32" osisID="1Kgs.16.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made an altar for Baal in the Baal temple he had constructed in Samaria. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.33" osisID="1Kgs.16.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab also made a sacred pole<note osisRef="1Kgs.16.33" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.16.33!note.c">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherah</hi>, perhaps an object devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> and did more to anger the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of Israel, than any of Israel’s kings who preceded him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.16.34" osisID="1Kgs.16.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">During Ahab’s time, Hiel from Bethel rebuilt Jericho. He set up its foundations at the cost of his oldest son Abiram. He hung its gates at the cost of his youngest son Segub. This fulfilled the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word spoken through Joshua, Nun’s son.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.17" osisID="1Kgs.17" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="17"><div scope="1Kgs.17.1-1Kgs.17.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Elijah and the ravens</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.1" osisID="1Kgs.17.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah from Tishbe, who was one of the settlers in Gilead, said to Ahab, <q type="x-complete">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> lives, Israel’s God, the one I serve, there will be neither dew nor rain these years unless I say so.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.2" osisID="1Kgs.17.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Elijah: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.3" osisID="1Kgs.17.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Go from here and turn east. Hide by the Cherith Brook that faces the Jordan River. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.4" osisID="1Kgs.17.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You can drink from the brook. I have also ordered the ravens to provide for you there. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.5" osisID="1Kgs.17.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah went and did just what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said. He stayed by the Cherith Brook that faced the Jordan River. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.6" osisID="1Kgs.17.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The ravens brought bread and meat in the mornings and evenings. He drank from the Cherith Brook. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.7" osisID="1Kgs.17.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After a while the brook dried up because there was no rain in the land.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.17.8-1Kgs.17.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Elijah and the widow from Zarephath</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.8" osisID="1Kgs.17.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Elijah: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.9" osisID="1Kgs.17.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Get up and go to Zarephath near Sidon and stay there. I have ordered a widow there to take care of you. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.10" osisID="1Kgs.17.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah left and went to Zarephath. As he came to the town gate, he saw a widow collecting sticks. He called out to her, <q type="x-complete">Please get a little water for me in this cup so I can drink.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.11" osisID="1Kgs.17.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">She went to get some water. He then said to her, <q type="x-complete">Please get me a piece of bread.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.12" osisID="1Kgs.17.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God lives,</q> she replied, <q type="x-complete">I don’t have any food; only a handful of flour in a jar and a bit of oil in a bottle. Look at me. I’m collecting two sticks so that I can make some food for myself and my son. We’ll eat the last of the food and then die.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.13" osisID="1Kgs.17.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah said to her, <q type="x-start">Don’t be afraid! Go and do what you said. Only make a little loaf of bread for me first. Then bring it to me. You can make something for yourself and your son after that.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.14" osisID="1Kgs.17.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">This is what Israel’s God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, says: The jar of flour won’t decrease and the bottle of oil won’t run out until the day the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> sends rain on the earth.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.15" osisID="1Kgs.17.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The widow went and did what Elijah said. So the widow, Elijah, and the widow’s household ate for many days. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.16" osisID="1Kgs.17.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The jar of flour didn’t decrease nor did the bottle of oil run out, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> spoke through Elijah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.17" osisID="1Kgs.17.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After these things, the son of the widow, who was the matriarch of the household, became ill. His sickness got steadily worse until he wasn’t breathing anymore. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.18" osisID="1Kgs.17.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">She said to Elijah, <q type="x-complete">What’s gone wrong between us, man of God? Have you come to me to call attention to my sin and kill my son?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.19" osisID="1Kgs.17.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah replied, <q type="x-complete">Give your son to me.</q> He took her son from her and carried him to the upper room where he was staying. Elijah laid him on his bed. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.20" osisID="1Kgs.17.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah cried out to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, <q type="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God, why is it that you have brought such evil upon the widow that I am staying with by killing her son?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.21" osisID="1Kgs.17.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he stretched himself over the boy three times and cried out to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, <q type="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God, please give this boy’s life back to him.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.22" osisID="1Kgs.17.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> listened to Elijah’s voice and gave the boy his life back. And he lived. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.17.23" osisID="1Kgs.17.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah brought the boy down from the upper room of the house and gave him to his mother. Elijah said, <q type="x-complete">Look, your son is alive!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.17.24" osisID="1Kgs.17.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Now I know that you really are a man of God,</q> the woman said to Elijah, <q type="x-complete">and that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word is truly in your mouth.</q></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.18" osisID="1Kgs.18" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="18"><div scope="1Kgs.18.1-1Kgs.18.46" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Elijah versus Baal’s prophets</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.1" osisID="1Kgs.18.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After many days, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Elijah (it was the third year of the drought): Go! Appear before Ahab. I will then send rain on the earth. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.2" osisID="1Kgs.18.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So Elijah went to appear before Ahab.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.2" osisID="1Kgs.18.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Now the famine had become especially bad in Samaria. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.3" osisID="1Kgs.18.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab had called Obadiah, who was in charge of the palace affairs. (Obadiah greatly feared the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.4" osisID="1Kgs.18.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Jezebel killed the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s prophets, Obadiah took one hundred of them and hid them, fifty each in two caves. He supplied them with food and water.) </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.5" osisID="1Kgs.18.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab said to Obadiah, <q type="x-complete">Go throughout the land and check every spring of water and every brook. Perhaps we can find some grass to keep our horses and mules alive so we don’t have to kill any of them.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.6" osisID="1Kgs.18.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">To search, they divided the land between themselves. Ahab went one way by himself, while Obadiah went a different way by himself.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.7" osisID="1Kgs.18.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While Obadiah was out searching, suddenly Elijah met up with him. When Obadiah saw him, he fell on his face. <q type="x-complete">My master!</q> he said. <q type="x-complete">Are you Elijah?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.8" osisID="1Kgs.18.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah replied, <q type="x-complete">I am. Go and say to your master, ‘Elijah is here!’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.9" osisID="1Kgs.18.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Obadiah said, <q type="x-start">How have I sinned that you are handing me, your servant, over to Ahab so he can kill me?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.10" osisID="1Kgs.18.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God lives, there’s no nation or kingdom where my master Ahab hasn’t looked for you. They would insist, ‘He’s not here,’ but Ahab would make them swear that they couldn’t find you.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.11" osisID="1Kgs.18.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">And now you are commanding me: ‘Go and say to your master, <q type="x-complete">Elijah is here</q>?’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.12" osisID="1Kgs.18.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But here’s what will happen: As soon as I leave you, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s spirit will carry you off somewhere—I don’t know where—then I’ll report to Ahab, but he won’t be able to find you. Then he will kill me! But your servant has feared the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> from my youth.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.13" osisID="1Kgs.18.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Wasn’t my master told what I did when Jezebel killed the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s prophets? I hid one hundred of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s prophets, fifty each in two caves. I also supplied them with food and water.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.14" osisID="1Kgs.18.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But even after all that, you tell me, ‘Say to your master, <q type="x-complete">Elijah is here!</q>’ Ahab will kill me!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.15" osisID="1Kgs.18.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah said, <q type="x-complete">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> of heavenly forces lives, the one I serve, I will appear before Ahab today.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.16" osisID="1Kgs.18.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Obadiah went to meet Ahab. He told him what had happened. Then Ahab went to meet Elijah. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.17" osisID="1Kgs.18.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Ahab saw Elijah, Ahab said to him, <q type="x-complete">Is that you, the one who troubles Israel?</q></verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.18" osisID="1Kgs.18.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah answered, <q type="x-start">I haven’t troubled Israel; you and your father’s house have! You did as much when you deserted the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s commands and followed the Baals.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.19" osisID="1Kgs.18.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now send a message and gather all Israel to me at Mount Carmel. Gather the four hundred fifty prophets of Baal and the four hundred prophets of Asherah who eat at Jezebel’s table.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.20" osisID="1Kgs.18.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab sent the message to all the Israelites. He gathered the prophets at Mount Carmel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.21" osisID="1Kgs.18.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah approached all the people and said, <q type="x-complete">How long will you hobble back and forth between two opinions? If the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName><note osisRef="1Kgs.18.21" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.18.21!note.d">The contrast between the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s divine name (<hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">YHWH</hi>) and Baal’s name is crucial throughout this passage.</note> is God, follow God. If Baal is God, follow Baal.</q> The people gave no answer.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.22" osisID="1Kgs.18.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah said to the people, <q type="x-start">I am the last of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s prophets, but Baal’s prophets number four hundred fifty.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.23" osisID="1Kgs.18.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Give us two bulls. Let Baal’s prophets choose one. Let them cut it apart and set it on the wood, but don’t add fire. I’ll prepare the other bull, put it on the wood, but won’t add fire.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.24" osisID="1Kgs.18.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Then all of you will call on the name of your god, and I will call on the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. The god who answers with fire—that’s the real God!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.24" osisID="1Kgs.18.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">All the people answered, <q type="x-complete">That’s an excellent idea.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.25" osisID="1Kgs.18.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Elijah said to the prophets of Baal, <q type="x-complete">Choose one of these bulls. Prepare it first since there are so many of you. Call on the name of your god, but don’t add fire.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.26" osisID="1Kgs.18.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So they took one of the bulls that had been brought to them. They prepared it and called on Baal’s name from morning to midday. They said, <q type="x-complete">Great Baal, answer us!</q> But there was no sound or answer. They performed a hopping dance around the altar that had been set up.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.27" osisID="1Kgs.18.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Around noon, Elijah started making fun of them: <q type="x-complete">Shout louder! Certainly he’s a god! Perhaps he is lost in thought or wandering or traveling somewhere.<note osisRef="1Kgs.18.27" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.18.27!note.e">Heb uncertain</note> Or maybe he is asleep and must wake up!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.28" osisID="1Kgs.18.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the prophets of Baal cried with a louder voice and cut themselves with swords and knives as was their custom. Their blood flowed all over them. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.29" osisID="1Kgs.18.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As noon passed they went crazy with their ritual until it was time for the evening offering. Still there was no sound or answer, no response whatsoever.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.30" osisID="1Kgs.18.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Elijah said to all the people, <q type="x-complete">Come here!</q> All the people closed in, and he repaired the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar that had been damaged. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.31" osisID="1Kgs.18.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah took twelve stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob—to whom the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came: <q type="x-complete">Your name will be Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.32" osisID="1Kgs.18.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built the stones into an altar in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s name, and he dug a trench around the altar big enough to hold two seahs<note osisRef="1Kgs.18.32" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.18.32!note.f">One seah is approximately seven and a half quarts.</note> of dry grain. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.33" osisID="1Kgs.18.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He put the wood in order, butchered the bull, and placed the bull on the wood. <q type="x-complete">Fill four jars with water and pour it on the sacrifice and on the wood,</q> he commanded. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.34" osisID="1Kgs.18.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Do it a second time!</q> he said. So they did it a second time. <q type="x-complete">Do it a third time!</q> And so they did it a third time. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.35" osisID="1Kgs.18.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The water flowed around the altar, and even the trench filled with water. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.36" osisID="1Kgs.18.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the time of the evening offering, the prophet Elijah drew near and prayed: <q type="x-start"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, let it be known today that you are God in Israel and that I am your servant. I have done all these things at your instructions.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.37" osisID="1Kgs.18.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Answer me, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>! Answer me so that this people will know that you, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, are the real God and that you can change their hearts.</q><note osisRef="1Kgs.18.37" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.18.37!note.g">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.38" osisID="1Kgs.18.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s fire fell; it consumed the sacrifice, the wood, the stones, and the dust. It even licked up the water in the trench!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.39" osisID="1Kgs.18.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the people saw this and fell on their faces. <q type="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is the real God! The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is the real God!</q> they exclaimed.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.40" osisID="1Kgs.18.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah said to them, <q type="x-complete">Seize Baal’s prophets! Don’t let any escape!</q> The people seized the prophets, and Elijah brought them to the Kishon Brook and killed them there. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.41" osisID="1Kgs.18.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah then said to Ahab, <q type="x-complete">Get up! Celebrate with food and drink because I hear the sound of a rainstorm coming.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.42" osisID="1Kgs.18.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Ahab got up to celebrate with food and drink. But Elijah went up to the top of Mount Carmel. He bowed down to the ground and put his face between his knees. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.43" osisID="1Kgs.18.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He said to his assistant, <q type="x-complete">Please get up and look toward the sea.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.43" osisID="1Kgs.18.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">So the assistant did so. He said, <q type="x-complete">I don’t see anything.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.43" osisID="1Kgs.18.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Seven times Elijah said, <q type="x-complete">Do it again.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.44" osisID="1Kgs.18.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The seventh time the assistant said, <q type="x-complete">I see a small cloud the size of a human hand coming up from the sea.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.18.44" osisID="1Kgs.18.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Elijah said, <q type="x-complete">Go and tell Ahab, ‘Pull yourself together, go down the mountain, and don’t let the rain hold you back.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.45" osisID="1Kgs.18.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After a little while, the sky became dark with clouds, and a wind came up with a huge rainstorm. Ahab was already riding on his way to Jezreel, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.18.46" osisID="1Kgs.18.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s power strengthened Elijah. He gathered up his clothes and ran in front of Ahab until he came to Jezreel.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.19" osisID="1Kgs.19" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="19"><div scope="1Kgs.19.1-1Kgs.19.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Elijah runs to Mount Horeb</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.1" osisID="1Kgs.19.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab told Jezebel all that Elijah had done, how he had killed all Baal’s prophets with the sword. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.2" osisID="1Kgs.19.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jezebel sent a messenger to Elijah with this message: <q type="x-complete">May the gods do whatever they want to me if by this time tomorrow I haven’t made your life like the life of one of them.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.3" osisID="1Kgs.19.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah was terrified. He got up and ran for his life. He arrived at Beer-sheba in Judah and left his assistant there. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.4" osisID="1Kgs.19.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He himself went farther on into the desert a day’s journey. He finally sat down under a solitary broom bush. He longed for his own death: <q type="x-complete">It’s more than enough, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>! Take my life because I’m no better than my ancestors.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.5" osisID="1Kgs.19.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He lay down and slept under the solitary broom bush.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.5" osisID="1Kgs.19.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Then suddenly a messenger tapped him and said to him, <q type="x-complete">Get up! Eat something!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.6" osisID="1Kgs.19.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah opened his eyes and saw flatbread baked on glowing coals and a jar of water right by his head. He ate and drank, and then went back to sleep. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.7" osisID="1Kgs.19.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s messenger returned a second time and tapped him. <q type="x-complete">Get up!</q> the messenger said. <q type="x-complete">Eat something, because you have a difficult road ahead of you.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.8" osisID="1Kgs.19.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah got up, ate and drank, and went refreshed by that food for forty days and nights until he arrived at Horeb, God’s mountain. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.9" osisID="1Kgs.19.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">There he went into a cave and spent the night.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.9" osisID="1Kgs.19.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to him and said, <q type="x-complete">Why are you here, Elijah?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.10" osisID="1Kgs.19.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah replied, <q type="x-complete">I’ve been very passionate for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of heavenly forces because the Israelites have abandoned your covenant. They have torn down your altars, and they have murdered your prophets with the sword. I’m the only one left, and now they want to take my life too!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.11" osisID="1Kgs.19.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said, <q type="x-complete">Go out and stand at the mountain before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is passing by.</q> A very strong wind tore through the mountains and broke apart the stones before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> wasn’t in the wind. After the wind, there was an earthquake. But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> wasn’t in the earthquake. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.12" osisID="1Kgs.19.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After the earthquake, there was a fire. But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> wasn’t in the fire. After the fire, there was a sound. Thin. Quiet. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.13" osisID="1Kgs.19.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Elijah heard it, he wrapped his face in his coat. He went out and stood at the cave’s entrance. A voice came to him and said, <q type="x-complete">Why are you here, Elijah?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.14" osisID="1Kgs.19.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said, <q type="x-complete">I’ve been very passionate for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of heavenly forces because the Israelites have abandoned your covenant. They have torn down your altars, and they have murdered your prophets with the sword. I’m the only one left, and now they want to take my life too.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.15" osisID="1Kgs.19.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said to him, <q type="x-start">Go back through the desert to Damascus and anoint Hazael as king of Aram.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.16" osisID="1Kgs.19.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Also anoint Jehu, Nimshi’s son, as king of Israel; and anoint Elisha from Abel-meholah, Shaphat’s son, to succeed you as prophet.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.17" osisID="1Kgs.19.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Whoever escapes from the sword of Hazael, Jehu will kill. Whoever escapes from the sword of Jehu, Elisha will kill.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.18" osisID="1Kgs.19.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But I have preserved those who remain in Israel, totaling seven thousand—all those whose knees haven’t bowed down to Baal and whose mouths haven’t kissed him.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.19" osisID="1Kgs.19.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Elijah departed from there and found Elisha, Shaphat’s son. He was plowing with twelve yoke of oxen before him. Elisha was with the twelfth yoke. Elijah met up with him and threw his coat on him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.20" osisID="1Kgs.19.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Elisha immediately left the oxen and ran after Elijah. <q type="x-complete">Let me kiss my father and my mother,</q> Elisha said, <q type="x-complete">then I will follow you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.19.20" osisID="1Kgs.19.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Elijah replied, <q type="x-complete">Go! I’m not holding you back!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.19.21" osisID="1Kgs.19.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elisha turned back from following Elijah, took the pair of oxen, and slaughtered them. Then with equipment from the oxen, Elisha boiled the meat, gave it to the people, and they ate it. Then he got up, followed Elijah, and served him.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.20" osisID="1Kgs.20" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="20"><div scope="1Kgs.20.1-1Kgs.20.43" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Ben-hadad’s wars with Ahab</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.1" osisID="1Kgs.20.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Ben-hadad of Aram brought together all his army along with thirty-two kings plus horses and chariots. He went up, surrounded Samaria, and made war against it. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.2" osisID="1Kgs.20.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He sent messengers to Ahab, Israel’s king, inside Samaria. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.3" osisID="1Kgs.20.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The message said, <q type="x-complete">This is what Ben-hadad says: ‘Your silver and your gold are mine. Your good-looking wives and children are mine.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.4" osisID="1Kgs.20.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s king answered, <q type="x-complete">Whatever you say, my master, great king. I am yours and so is everything I have.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.5" osisID="1Kgs.20.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The messengers came back again: <q type="x-start">This is what Ben-hadad says: ‘I sent you the message: Give me your silver and gold, your wives and your sons.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.6" osisID="1Kgs.20.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">However, at this time tomorrow I will send my officers to you, and they will search your palace and the houses of your officers. Everything that you find valuable they will seize and take away.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.7" osisID="1Kgs.20.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Israel’s king called all the elders of the land and he said, <q type="x-complete">Please know and understand the evil this man wants to do! He demanded from me my wives and sons, and my silver and gold; and I didn’t refuse him.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.8" osisID="1Kgs.20.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All of the elders and the people said to him, <q type="x-complete">Don’t obey and don’t give in!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.9" osisID="1Kgs.20.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So the king said to Ben-hadad’s messengers, <q type="x-complete">Say to my master the king: ‘Everything that you first ordered your servant, I will do. But I can’t comply with this new command.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.9" osisID="1Kgs.20.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The messengers took this response to Ben-hadad, </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.10" osisID="1Kgs.20.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who sent back this reply: <q type="x-complete">May the gods do whatever they want to me if there is even a handful of dust left in Samaria for the armies under me!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.11" osisID="1Kgs.20.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Israel’s king replied, <q type="x-complete">The one who prepares for battle shouldn’t brag like one returning from battle.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.12" osisID="1Kgs.20.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Ben-hadad heard this message, he and the other kings were drinking in their tents. Ben-hadad said to his officers, <q type="x-complete">Take your positions!</q> So they took up their positions against the city.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.13" osisID="1Kgs.20.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Suddenly a prophet approached Israel’s King Ahab. He said, <q type="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: Do you see that great army? Today I am handing it over to you. Then you will know that I am the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.14" osisID="1Kgs.20.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Ahab said, <q type="x-complete">Who will do it?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.14" osisID="1Kgs.20.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">The prophet answered, <q type="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: The servants of the district officials will do it.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.14" osisID="1Kgs.20.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-complete">Who should start the battle?</q> Ahab asked.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.14" osisID="1Kgs.20.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">You should,</q> the prophet replied.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.15" osisID="1Kgs.20.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Ahab assembled the servants of the district officials. There were two hundred thirty-two of them. Next he assembled the entire Israelite army, seven thousand total. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.16" osisID="1Kgs.20.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At noon they marched for battle. Meanwhile, Ben-hadad and the thirty-two kings allied with him were getting drunk in their tents. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.17" osisID="1Kgs.20.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The servants of the district officials were at the head of the march. Ben-hadad sent for information and was told, <q type="x-complete">Some men have marched out of Samaria.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.18" osisID="1Kgs.20.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said, <q type="x-complete">If they have come out in peace, take them alive; if they have come out for war, take them alive as well.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.19" osisID="1Kgs.20.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the servants of the district governors with the army behind them marched out from the city. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.20" osisID="1Kgs.20.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each one struck down his opponent, so that the Arameans fled. Israel chased after them. Ben-hadad, Aram’s king, escaped with some horses and chariots. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.21" osisID="1Kgs.20.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s king went out and attacked the horses and chariots. He attacked the Arameans with a fierce assault.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.22" osisID="1Kgs.20.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The prophet came to Israel’s king and said to him, <q type="x-complete">Maintain your strength! Know and understand that at the turn of the coming year, Aram’s king will attack you again.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.23" osisID="1Kgs.20.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The officers of Aram’s king said to him, <q type="x-start">Israel’s god is a god of the mountains. That’s why they were stronger than us. But if we fight them on the plains, we will certainly be stronger than they are.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.24" osisID="1Kgs.20.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">This is what you need to do: Remove the kings from their military posts and appoint officials in their place.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.25" osisID="1Kgs.20.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Then raise another army like the one that was destroyed, with horses like those horses and chariots like those chariots. Then we will fight them on the plains, and we will certainly be stronger than they are.</q> The king took their advice and followed it.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.26" osisID="1Kgs.20.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So in the spring of the year, Ben-hadad assembled the Arameans and marched up to Aphek to fight with Israel. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.27" osisID="1Kgs.20.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now the Israelites had already been assembled and provisioned, so they went to engage the Arameans. The Israelites camped before them like two small flocks of goats, but the Arameans filled the land.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.28" osisID="1Kgs.20.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the man of God came forward and said to Israel’s king, <q type="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: Because the Arameans said that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is a god of the mountains but not a god of the valleys, I am handing this whole great army over to you. Then you will know that I am the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.29" osisID="1Kgs.20.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The two armies camped opposite each other for seven days. On the seventh day, the battle began. The Israelites attacked and destroyed one hundred thousand Aramean foot soldiers in a single day. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.30" osisID="1Kgs.20.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who were left fled to Aphek, into the city where a wall fell on twenty-seven thousand more of them. But Ben-hadad escaped and hid in an inner room within the city.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.31" osisID="1Kgs.20.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-hadad’s officers said to him, <q type="x-complete">Listen, we have heard that the kings of Israel are merciful kings. Allow us to put mourning clothes on our bodies and cords around our heads. We will then go to Israel’s king. Perhaps he will let you live.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.32" osisID="1Kgs.20.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So they put mourning clothes on their bodies and cords around their heads. They went to Israel’s king and said, <q type="x-complete">Ben-hadad is your slave. He begs, ‘Please let me live!’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.32" osisID="1Kgs.20.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Israel’s king said, <q type="x-complete">Is he still alive? He is my brother.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.33" osisID="1Kgs.20.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Taking this as a good sign, Ben-hadad’s men quickly accepted this statement.<note osisRef="1Kgs.20.33" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.20.33!note.h">Heb uncertain</note> <q type="x-complete">Yes, Ben-hadad is your brother!</q> they said.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.33" osisID="1Kgs.20.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Go and get him,</q> the king ordered. So Ben-hadad came to him, and the king received him into his chariot.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.34" osisID="1Kgs.20.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Ben-hadad said to the king, <q type="x-complete">I will return the towns that my father took from your father. Furthermore, you can set up markets for yourself in Damascus just as my father did in Samaria.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.34" osisID="1Kgs.20.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king replied,<note osisRef="1Kgs.20.34" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.20.34!note.i">Heb lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">The king replied.</hi></note> <q type="x-complete">On the basis of this covenant, I will let you go.</q> So he made a covenant with Ben-hadad and set him free.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.35" osisID="1Kgs.20.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s command a certain man who belonged to a prophetic group said to his friend: <q type="x-complete">Please strike me.</q> But his friend refused to hit him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.36" osisID="1Kgs.20.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So he said to his friend, <q type="x-complete">Because you didn’t obey the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s voice, a lion will attack you as soon as you leave me.</q> And as the friend left the prophet, a lion found him and attacked him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.37" osisID="1Kgs.20.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the prophet found another man and said, <q type="x-complete">Please strike me.</q> He hit the prophet, and the attack left a wound. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.38" osisID="1Kgs.20.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The prophet went and stood before the king by the road. He disguised himself by putting a bandage over his eyes. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.39" osisID="1Kgs.20.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the king passed by, the prophet called out to the king, <q type="x-start">Your servant was in the middle of the battle when someone brought a prisoner. ‘Guard this man,’ he said. ‘If he escapes it will be your life for his—that, or you will owe me a kikkar of silver.’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.40" osisID="1Kgs.20.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">Your servant got busy doing this and that, and the prisoner disappeared.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.40" osisID="1Kgs.20.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Israel’s king replied, <q type="x-complete">It appears you have decided your own fate.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.41" osisID="1Kgs.20.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The prophet quickly tore the bandage from over his eyes, and Israel’s king recognized him as one of the prophets. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.20.42" osisID="1Kgs.20.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the prophet said to the king, <q type="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: Because you freed a man I condemned to die, it will be your life for his life, and your people for his people.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.20.43" osisID="1Kgs.20.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Israel’s king went to his palace at Samaria, irritated and upset.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.21" osisID="1Kgs.21" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="21"><div scope="1Kgs.21.1-1Kgs.21.29" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Naboth’s vineyard</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.1" osisID="1Kgs.21.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now it happened sometime later that Naboth from Jezreel had a vineyard in Jezreel that was next to the palace of King Ahab of Samaria. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.2" osisID="1Kgs.21.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab ordered Naboth, <q type="x-complete">Give me your vineyard so it can become my vegetable garden, because it is right next to my palace. In exchange for it, I’ll give you an even better vineyard. Or if you prefer, I’ll pay you the price in silver.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.3" osisID="1Kgs.21.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Naboth responded to Ahab, <q type="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> forbid that I give you my family inheritance!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.4" osisID="1Kgs.21.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Ahab went to his palace, irritated and upset at what Naboth<note osisRef="1Kgs.21.4" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.21.4!note.j">Heb adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">from Jezreel</hi>; also in 21:6–7, 15–16.</note> had said to him—because Naboth had said, <q type="x-complete">I won’t give you my family inheritance!</q> Ahab lay down on his bed and turned his face away. He wouldn’t eat anything.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.5" osisID="1Kgs.21.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His wife Jezebel came to him. <q type="x-complete">Why are you upset and not eating any food?</q> she asked.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.6" osisID="1Kgs.21.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He answered her, <q type="x-complete">I was talking to Naboth. I said, ‘Sell me your vineyard. Or if you prefer, I’ll give you another vineyard for it.’ But he said, ‘I won’t give you my vineyard!’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.7" osisID="1Kgs.21.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then his wife Jezebel said to him, <q type="x-complete">Aren’t you the one who rules Israel? Get up! Eat some food and cheer up. I’ll get Naboth’s vineyard for you myself.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.8" osisID="1Kgs.21.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So she wrote letters in Ahab’s name, putting his seal on them. She sent them to the elders and officials who lived in the same town as Naboth. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.9" osisID="1Kgs.21.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what she wrote in the letters: <q type="x-start">Announce a fast and place Naboth at the head of the people.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.10" osisID="1Kgs.21.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Then bring in two liars in front of him and have them testify as follows: ‘You cursed God and king!’ Then take Naboth outside and stone him so he dies.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.11" osisID="1Kgs.21.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The elders and the officials who lived in Naboth’s town did exactly as Jezebel specified in the letters that she had sent. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.12" osisID="1Kgs.21.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They announced a fast and placed Naboth at the head of the people. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.13" osisID="1Kgs.21.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the two liars came and sat in front of him. They testified against Naboth in front of the people, <q type="x-complete">Naboth cursed God and king!</q> So the people took Naboth outside the town and stoned him so that he died.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.14" osisID="1Kgs.21.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It was then reported to Jezebel, <q type="x-complete">Naboth was stoned. He’s dead.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.15" osisID="1Kgs.21.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as Jezebel heard that Naboth had been stoned to death, she said to Ahab, <q type="x-complete">Get up and take ownership of the vineyard of Naboth, which he had refused to sell to you. Naboth is no longer alive; he’s dead.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.16" osisID="1Kgs.21.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Ahab heard that Naboth had died, he got up and went down to Naboth’s vineyard to take ownership of it.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.17" osisID="1Kgs.21.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Elijah from Tishbe: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.18" osisID="1Kgs.21.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Get up and go down to meet Israel’s King Ahab in Samaria. He is in Naboth’s vineyard. He has gone down to take ownership of it.</verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.19" osisID="1Kgs.21.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Say the following to him: This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: So, you’ve murdered and are now taking ownership, are you? Then tell him: This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: In the same place where the dogs licked up Naboth’s blood, they will lick up your own blood.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.20" osisID="1Kgs.21.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Ahab said to Elijah, <q type="x-complete">So you’ve found me, my old enemy!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.20" osisID="1Kgs.21.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">I found you,</q> Elijah said, <q type="x-start">because you’ve enslaved yourself by doing evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.21" osisID="1Kgs.21.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">So I am now bringing evil on you! I will burn until you are consumed, and I will eliminate everyone who urinates on a wall that belongs to Ahab, whether slave or free.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.22" osisID="1Kgs.21.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I will make your household like that of Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, and like the household of Baasha, Ahijah’s son, because of the way you’ve angered me and because you’ve made Israel sin.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.23" osisID="1Kgs.21.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">As for Jezebel, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says this: Dogs will devour Jezebel in the area of Jezreel.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.24" osisID="1Kgs.21.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Dogs will eat anyone of Ahab’s family who dies in town, and birds will eat anyone who dies in the country.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText">(<verse sID="1Kgs.21.25" osisID="1Kgs.21.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Truly there has never been anyone like Ahab who sold out by doing evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes—evil that his wife Jezebel led him to do. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.26" osisID="1Kgs.21.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab’s actions were deplorable. He followed after the worthless idols exactly like the Amorites had done—the very ones the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had removed before the Israelites.)</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.21.27" osisID="1Kgs.21.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Ahab heard these words, he tore his clothes and put mourning clothes on his body. He fasted, even slept in mourning clothes, and walked around depressed. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.28" osisID="1Kgs.21.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word then came to Elijah from Tishbe: </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.21.29" osisID="1Kgs.21.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Have you seen how Ahab has humbled himself before me? Because he has done so, I won’t bring the evil during his lifetime. Instead, I will bring the evil on his household in the days of his son.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Kgs.22" osisID="1Kgs.22" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="22"><div scope="1Kgs.22.1-1Kgs.22.38" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat and Ahab</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.1" osisID="1Kgs.22.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">For three years there was no war between Aram and the Israelites. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.2" osisID="1Kgs.22.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the third year, Judah’s King Jehoshaphat visited Israel’s king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.3" osisID="1Kgs.22.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s king said to his servants, <q type="x-complete">You know, don’t you, that Ramoth-gilead is ours? But we aren’t doing anything to take it back from the king of Aram.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.4" osisID="1Kgs.22.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He said to Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">Will you go with me into battle at Ramoth-gilead?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.4" osisID="1Kgs.22.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Jehoshaphat said to Israel’s king, <q type="x-start">I am with you, and my troops and my horses are united with yours.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.5" osisID="1Kgs.22.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But,</q> Jehoshapat said to Israel’s king, <q type="x-complete">first let’s see what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has to say.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.6" osisID="1Kgs.22.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So Israel’s king gathered about four hundred prophets, and he asked them, <q type="x-complete">Should I go to war with Ramoth-gilead or not?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.6" osisID="1Kgs.22.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Attack!</q> the prophets answered. <q type="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will hand it over to the king.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.7" osisID="1Kgs.22.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Jehoshaphat said, <q type="x-complete">Isn’t there any other prophet of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">Lord</divineName> whom we could ask?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.8" osisID="1Kgs.22.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-complete">There is one other man who could ask the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> for us,</q> Israel’s king told Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">but I hate him because he never prophesies anything good about me, only bad. His name is Micaiah, Imlah’s son.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.8" osisID="1Kgs.22.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">The king shouldn’t speak like that!</q> Jehoshaphat said.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.9" osisID="1Kgs.22.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Israel’s king called an officer and ordered, <q type="x-complete">Bring Micaiah, Imlah’s son, right away.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.10" osisID="1Kgs.22.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Israel’s king and Judah’s King Jehoshaphat were sitting on their thrones, dressed in their royal robes at the threshing floor beside the entrance to the gate of Samaria. All the prophets were prophesying in front of them. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.11" osisID="1Kgs.22.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zedekiah, Chenaanah’s son, made iron horns for himself and said, <q type="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: With these horns you will gore the Arameans until there’s nothing left of them!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.12" osisID="1Kgs.22.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the other prophets agreed: <q type="x-complete">Attack Ramoth-gilead and win! The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will hand it over to the king!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.13" osisID="1Kgs.22.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Meanwhile, the messenger who had gone to summon Micaiah said to him, <q type="x-complete">Listen, the prophets all agree that the king will succeed. You should say the same thing they say and prophesy success.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.14" osisID="1Kgs.22.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Micaiah answered, <q type="x-complete">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> lives, I will say only what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> tells me to say.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.15" osisID="1Kgs.22.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">When Micaiah arrived, the king asked him, <q type="x-complete">Micaiah, should we go to war with Ramoth-gilead or not?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.15" osisID="1Kgs.22.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Attack and win!</q> Micaiah answered. <q type="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will hand it over to the king!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.16" osisID="1Kgs.22.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the king said, <q type="x-complete">How many times must I demand that you tell me the truth when you speak in the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.17" osisID="1Kgs.22.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Micaiah replied, <q type="x-complete">I saw all Israel scattered on the hills like sheep without a shepherd! And then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said: They have no master. Let them return safely to their own homes.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.18" osisID="1Kgs.22.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Israel’s king said to Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">Didn’t I tell you? He never prophesies anything good about me, only bad.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.19" osisID="1Kgs.22.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Micaiah said, <q type="x-start">Listen now to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word: I saw the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> enthroned with all the heavenly forces stationed beside him, at his right and at his left.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.20" osisID="1Kgs.22.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said, ‘Who will persuade Ahab so that he attacks Ramoth-gilead and dies there?’ There were many suggestions</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.21" osisID="1Kgs.22.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">until one particular spirit approached the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and said, ‘I’ll persuade him.’ ‘How?’ the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> asked.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.22" osisID="1Kgs.22.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">‘I will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets,’ he said. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> agreed, ‘You will succeed in persuading him! Go ahead!’</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.23" osisID="1Kgs.22.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">So now, since the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has placed a lying spirit in the mouths of every one of these prophets of yours, it is the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> who has pronounced disaster against you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.24" osisID="1Kgs.22.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zedekiah, Chenaanah’s son, approached Micaiah and slapped him on the cheek. <q type="x-complete">Just how did the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s spirit leave me to speak to you?</q> he asked.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.25" osisID="1Kgs.22.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Micaiah answered, <q type="x-complete">You will find out on the day you try to hide in an inner room.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.26" osisID="1Kgs.22.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Arrest him,</q> ordered Israel’s king, <q type="x-start">and turn him over to Amon the city official and to Joash the king’s son.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.27" osisID="1Kgs.22.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Tell them, ‘The king says: Put this man in prison and feed him minimum rations of bread and water until I return safely.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.28" osisID="1Kgs.22.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">If you ever return safely,</q> Micaiah replied, <q type="x-complete">then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> wasn’t speaking through me.</q> Then he added, <q type="x-complete">Pay attention, every last one of you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.29" osisID="1Kgs.22.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Israel’s king and Judah’s King Jehoshaphat attacked Ramoth-gilead. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.30" osisID="1Kgs.22.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s king said to Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">I will disguise myself when we go into battle,<note osisRef="1Kgs.22.30" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.22.30!note.k">LXX, Tg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Disguise yourself and go</hi></note> but you should wear your royal attire.</q> When Israel’s king had disguised himself, they entered the battle.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.31" osisID="1Kgs.22.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Meanwhile, Aram’s king had commanded his thirty-two chariot officers, <q type="x-complete">Don’t bother with anyone big or small. Fight only with Israel’s king.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.32" osisID="1Kgs.22.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as the chariot officers saw Jehoshaphat, they assumed that he must be Israel’s king, so they turned to attack him. But Jehoshaphat cried out for help. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.33" osisID="1Kgs.22.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the chariot officers realized that he wasn’t Israel’s king, they stopped chasing him. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.34" osisID="1Kgs.22.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">But someone randomly shot an arrow that struck Israel’s king between the joints in his armor.<note osisRef="1Kgs.22.34" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.22.34!note.l">Heb uncertain</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.34" osisID="1Kgs.22.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Turn around and get me out of the battle,</q> the king told his chariot driver. <q type="x-complete">I’ve been hit!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.35" osisID="1Kgs.22.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While the battle raged all that day, the king stood propped up in the chariot facing the Arameans. But that evening he died after his blood had poured from his wound into the chariot. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.36" osisID="1Kgs.22.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the sun set, a shout spread throughout the camp: <q type="x-complete">Retreat to your towns! Retreat to your land!</q> </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.37" osisID="1Kgs.22.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Once the king had died, people came from Samaria and buried the king there. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.38" osisID="1Kgs.22.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They cleaned the chariot at the pool of Samaria. The dogs licked up the king’s blood and the prostitutes bathed in it, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had spoken.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.22.39-1Kgs.22.40" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Ahab’s last days</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.39" osisID="1Kgs.22.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Ahab’s deeds and all that he did—including the ivory palace he built and all the towns he constructed—aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s kings? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.40" osisID="1Kgs.22.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahab lay down with his ancestors. His son Ahaziah succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.22.41-1Kgs.22.50" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.41" osisID="1Kgs.22.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat, Asa’s son, became king over Judah in the fourth year of Israel’s King Ahab. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.42" osisID="1Kgs.22.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat was 35 years old when he became king, and he ruled for twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Azubah; she was Shilhi’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.43" osisID="1Kgs.22.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshapat walked in all the ways of his father Asa, not deviating from it. He did the right things in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, with the exception that he didn’t remove the shrines. The people continued to sacrifice and offer incense at them. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.44" osisID="1Kgs.22.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat made peace with Israel’s king. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.45" osisID="1Kgs.22.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Jehoshaphat’s deeds, the great acts he did, and how he fought in battle, aren’t they written in the official records of Judah’s kings? </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.46" osisID="1Kgs.22.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Additionally, Jehoshaphat purged the land of the consecrated workers<note osisRef="1Kgs.22.46" placement="inline" osisID="1Kgs.22.46!note.m">Traditionally <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">cultic prostitutes</hi></note> who remained from the days of Asa.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.47" osisID="1Kgs.22.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Edom had no king; only a deputy was ruler. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.48" osisID="1Kgs.22.48" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat built Tarshish-styled ships to go to Ophir for gold. But the fleet didn’t go because it was wrecked at Ezion-geber. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.49" osisID="1Kgs.22.49" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Ahaziah, Ahab’s son, said to Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">Let my sailors go with your sailors on the ships.</q> But Jehoshaphat didn’t agree to this. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.50" osisID="1Kgs.22.50" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat died and was buried with his ancestors in his ancestor David’s City. His son Jehoram succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="1Kgs.22.51-1Kgs.22.53" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Ahaziah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Kgs.22.51" osisID="1Kgs.22.51" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the seventeenth year of Judah’s King Jehoshaphat, Ahaziah, Ahab’s son, became king over Israel in Samaria. He ruled over Israel for two years. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.52" osisID="1Kgs.22.52" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes. He walked in his father’s ways and his mother’s ways—that is, in the ways of Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, who had caused Israel to sin. </verse><verse sID="1Kgs.22.53" osisID="1Kgs.22.53" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaziah served Baal and worshipped him. He angered the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, by doing all the same things his father had done.</verse> </p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>