<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">2 Chronicles</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="2Chr"><chapter sID="2Chr.1" osisID="2Chr.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">2 Chronicles</title><div scope="2Chr.1.1-2Chr.1.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon first meets God</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.1.1" osisID="2Chr.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon, David’s son, was securely established over his kingdom because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God was with him and made him very great. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.2" osisID="2Chr.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon summoned all Israel, including the officers of the army,<note osisRef="2Chr.1.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.1.2!note.a">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">officers over thousands and hundreds</hi></note> the judges, and every Israelite leader who was the head of a family. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.3" osisID="2Chr.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon, accompanied by the whole assembly, went to the shrine at Gibeon because that is where God’s meeting tent was, the tent that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s servant Moses had made in the wilderness. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.4" osisID="2Chr.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now David had already brought God’s chest from Kiriath-jearim to the place he had prepared for it because he had pitched a tent for the chest in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.5" osisID="2Chr.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the bronze altar that Bezalel, Uri’s son and Hur’s grandson, had made was there in front of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s dwelling, so that is where Solomon and the assembly worshipped. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.6" osisID="2Chr.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon went there to the bronze altar in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s presence at the meeting tent and offered a thousand entirely burned offerings upon it.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.1.7" osisID="2Chr.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That night God appeared to Solomon and said, <q type="x-complete">Ask whatever you wish, and I will give it to you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.1.8" osisID="2Chr.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">You showed so much kindness to my father David,</q> Solomon replied to God,<q type="x-start">and you have made me king in his place.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.9" osisID="2Chr.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Now, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God, let your promise to my father David be fulfilled because you have made me king over a people as numerous as the earth’s dust.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.10" osisID="2Chr.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Give me wisdom and knowledge so I can lead this people, because no one can govern this great people of yours without your help.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.1.11" osisID="2Chr.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God said to Solomon, <q type="x-start">Since this is what you wish, and because you’ve asked for wisdom and knowledge to govern my people over whom I’ve made you king—rather than asking for wealth, riches, fame, victory over those who hate you, or even a long life—</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.12" osisID="2Chr.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">your request for wisdom and knowledge is granted. But I will also give you wealth, riches, and fame beyond that of any king before you or after you.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.13" osisID="2Chr.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon went from<note osisRef="2Chr.1.13" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.1.13!note.b">LXX, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">to</hi></note> the shrine in Gibeon, from the meeting tent to Jerusalem where he ruled over Israel.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.1.14-2Chr.1.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s wealth</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.1.14" osisID="2Chr.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon acquired more and more chariots and horses until he had fourteen hundred chariots and twelve thousand horses, which he stationed in chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.15" osisID="2Chr.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In Jerusalem, the king made silver and gold as common as stones, and cedar as plentiful as sycamore trees that grow in the foothills. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.16" osisID="2Chr.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon’s horses were imported from Egypt and Kue, purchased from Kue by the king’s agents at the going price. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.1.17" osisID="2Chr.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They would import a chariot from Egypt for six hundred pieces of silver and a horse for one hundred fifty, and then export them to all the Hittite and Aramean kings.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.2" osisID="2Chr.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="2Chr.2.1-2Chr.2.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon prepares to build the temple</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.2.1" osisID="2Chr.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="2Chr.2.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.2.1!note.c">1:18 in Heb</note> Solomon gave orders to build a temple for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s name and to build a royal palace for himself. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.2" osisID="2Chr.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="2Chr.2.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.2.2!note.d">2:1 in Heb</note> To work in the highlands, Solomon drafted 70,000 laborers, 80,000 stonecutters, and 3,600 supervisors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.3" osisID="2Chr.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Solomon sent the following message to King Huram<note osisRef="2Chr.2.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.2.3!note.e">1 Kings spells the king's name as Hiram.</note> of Tyre:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.2.3" osisID="2Chr.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">When my father David was building his palace, you sent him cedar logs. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.4" osisID="2Chr.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now as his son<note osisRef="2Chr.2.4" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.2.4!note.f">LXX; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">his son.</hi></note> I am about to build a temple in the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God. I will dedicate it to him to burn fragrant incense before him, to set out the bread that is regularly displayed, and to offer entirely burned offerings every morning and evening, on the sabbaths, the first of every month, and the festivals of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God, as Israel has been commanded to do forever. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.5" osisID="2Chr.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The temple I am about to build must be magnificent, because our God is greater than all other gods. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.6" osisID="2Chr.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But who is able to build such a temple when even the highest heaven can’t contain God? And who am I that I should build this temple for God, except as a place to burn incense in his presence? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.7" osisID="2Chr.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now send me a craftsman skilled in gold, silver, bronze, and iron, as well as in purple, crimson, and violet yarn—someone also experienced as an engraver. He will work with my craftsmen in Judah and Jerusalem who were provided by my father David. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.8" osisID="2Chr.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Also send me cedar, cypress, and sandalwood logs from Lebanon. I know your servants know how to cut Lebanese timber, so my servants will work with your servants </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.9" osisID="2Chr.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">to prepare plenty of timber for me, because the temple that I am about to build will be magnificent and amazing. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.10" osisID="2Chr.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I will pay the woodcutters twenty thousand kors<note osisRef="2Chr.2.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.2.10!note.g">One kor is equivalent to a homer and is possibly equal to fifty gallons of grain.</note> of crushed wheat, twenty thousand kors of barley, twenty thousand baths<note osisRef="2Chr.2.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.2.10!note.h">One bath is approximately twenty quarts or five gallons.</note> of wine, and twenty thousand baths of olive oil.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.2.11" osisID="2Chr.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Tyre’s King Huram replied in a letter that he sent to Solomon:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.2.11" osisID="2Chr.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> must love his people Israel because he has made you their king! </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.12" osisID="2Chr.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Bless the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, who made heaven and earth. He gave King David a wise son who possesses the knowledge and understanding to build a temple for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and a royal palace for himself. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.13" osisID="2Chr.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m sending you a skilled and experienced craftsman, Huram-abi, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.14" osisID="2Chr.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">whose mother is from the tribe of Dan and whose father is from Tyre. He’s skilled in working with gold, silver, bronze, iron, stone, and wood, as well as purple, violet, and crimson yarn, and fine linen. He can do any kind of engraving and make any design given to him with the assistance of your craftsmen and the craftsmen of my master, your father David. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.15" osisID="2Chr.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So once my master sends the wheat, barley, olive oil, and wine he has promised, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.16" osisID="2Chr.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">we will cut as much timber as you need from Lebanon and bring it by raft on the sea to you at Joppa, where you can take it up to Jerusalem.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.2.17" osisID="2Chr.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon counted all the immigrants in the land of Israel, as his father David had done, and the total was 153,600. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.2.18" osisID="2Chr.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made 70,000 of these immigrants laborers, 80,000 of them stonecutters in the highlands, and 3,600 of them supervisors to keep the people working.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.3" osisID="2Chr.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="2Chr.3.1-2Chr.3.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon builds the temple</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.3.1" osisID="2Chr.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon began to build the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple in Jerusalem on Mount Moriah, where the Lord<note osisRef="2Chr.3.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.1!note.i">LXX; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName></hi>.</note> had appeared to his father David, on the place David had prepared at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.2" osisID="2Chr.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He began building in the second month<note osisRef="2Chr.3.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.2!note.j">LXX; MT adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">on the second (day).</hi></note> of the fourth year of his rule. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.3" osisID="2Chr.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon laid the foundations<note osisRef="2Chr.3.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.3!note.k">Syr <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the measurements</hi></note> for these structures in order to build the temple of God. The length according to the old standard of measurement was ninety feet and the width thirty feet. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.4" osisID="2Chr.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Across the front of the temple<note osisRef="2Chr.3.4" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.4!note.l">LXX; cf 1 Kgs 6:3</note> was a porch as long as the temple was and thirty feet wide, and thirty feet<note osisRef="2Chr.3.4" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.4!note.m">LXX, Syr; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">one hundred eighty feet</hi></note> high. He covered the inside walls with pure gold. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.5" osisID="2Chr.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He paneled the walls of the main room with pine, covered them with fine gold, and decorated them with palm trees and chains. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.6" osisID="2Chr.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He studded the room with precious stones for beauty; the gold was from Parvaim. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.7" osisID="2Chr.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He covered the room, its beams, doorframes, walls, and doors with gold, and carved images of winged creatures on the walls. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.8" osisID="2Chr.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he made the most holy place. It was as long as the temple was wide, thirty feet long and thirty feet wide. He covered it with six hundred kikkars of fine gold. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.9" osisID="2Chr.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The gold nails weighed fifty shekels.<note osisRef="2Chr.3.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.9!note.n">Or approximately thirty ounces</note> He also covered the upper rooms with gold.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.3.10" osisID="2Chr.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the most holy place he formed two statues of winged creatures and covered them with gold. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.11" osisID="2Chr.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Together the wingspan of these creatures was thirty feet. One of the first creature’s wings was seven and a half feet long and touched the temple wall, while the other wing was seven and a half feet long, touching the wing of the other creature. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.12" osisID="2Chr.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Similarly, one wing of the other creature was seven and a half feet long and touched the temple wall, while the other wing was seven and a half feet long and touched the other creature. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.13" osisID="2Chr.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The wings of these creatures extended thirty feet. They stood on their feet facing the main room.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.3.14" osisID="2Chr.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he made the curtain out of fine linen and violet, purple, and crimson yarn, weaving winged creatures into it. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.15" osisID="2Chr.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he made two columns in front of the temple, fifty-two and a half feet high, with a seven and a half foot cap on top of each. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.16" osisID="2Chr.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he made chains like a necklace<note osisRef="2Chr.3.16" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.3.16!note.o">Heb adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the inner room.</hi></note> and placed them on the tops of the columns. He made a hundred pomegranates and placed them into the chains. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.3.17" osisID="2Chr.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he set up the pillars in front of the sanctuary, one on the south, the other on the north. The one on the south he named Jachin, and the one on the north he named Boaz.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.4" osisID="2Chr.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="2Chr.4.1-2Chr.4.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s temple equipment</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.4.1" osisID="2Chr.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He<note osisRef="2Chr.4.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.4.1!note.p"><hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Solomon </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Huram</hi>; this ambiguity with the pronoun continues in the following verses, but compare 2 Chron 3:1, 3; 4:11. If Huram is meant, this is a worker whose name is spelled Hiram in 1 Kgs 7:13-14.</note> also made a bronze altar thirty feet long, thirty feet wide, and fifteen feet high. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.2" osisID="2Chr.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he made a tank of cast metal called the Sea. It was circular in shape, fifteen feet from rim to rim, seven and a half feet high, and forty-five feet in circumference. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.3" osisID="2Chr.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Under the rim were two rows of oxlike figures completely encircling it, ten every eighteen inches, each cast in its mold. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.4" osisID="2Chr.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Sea rested on twelve oxen with their backs toward the center, three facing north, three facing west, three facing south, and three facing east. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.5" osisID="2Chr.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Sea was as thick as the width of a hand. Its rim was shaped like a cup or an open lily blossom. It could hold three thousand baths.<note osisRef="2Chr.4.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.4.5!note.q">One bath is approximately twenty quarts or five gallons.</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.6" osisID="2Chr.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also made ten washbasins and put five on the south and five on the north. The items used for the entirely burned offerings were rinsed in these. The priests washed in the Sea. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.7" osisID="2Chr.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made ten gold lampstands as prescribed and put them in the sanctuary, five on the south and five on the north. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.8" osisID="2Chr.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also made ten tables and put them in the sanctuary, five on the south and five on the north, as well as a hundred gold bowls. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.9" osisID="2Chr.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made the courtyard of the priests and the great courtyard, with doors covered with bronze for the courtyard. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.10" osisID="2Chr.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He placed the Sea at the southeast corner.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.4.11" osisID="2Chr.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Huram made the pots, the shovels, and the bowls. So Huram finished all his work on God’s temple for King Solomon:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.12" osisID="2Chr.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">two columns;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.12" osisID="2Chr.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">two circular capitals on top of the columns;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.12" osisID="2Chr.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">two networks adorning the two circular capitals on top of the columns;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.13" osisID="2Chr.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">four hundred pomegranates for the two networks, with two rows of pomegranates for each network that adorned the two circular capitals on top of the columns;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.14" osisID="2Chr.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">ten<note osisRef="2Chr.4.14" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.4.14!note.r">LXX and 1 Kgs 7:43; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he made</hi></note> stands with ten<note osisRef="2Chr.4.14" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.4.14!note.s">1 Kgs 7:43; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he made</hi></note> basins on them;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.15" osisID="2Chr.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">one Sea;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.15" osisID="2Chr.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">twelve oxen beneath the Sea;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.4.16" osisID="2Chr.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">and the pots, the shovels, and the meat forks.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.4.16" osisID="2Chr.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">All the things that Huram-abi made for King Solomon for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple were made of polished bronze. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.17" osisID="2Chr.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king cast them in clay molds in the Jordan Valley between Succoth and Zarethan.<note osisRef="2Chr.4.17" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.4.17!note.t">With 1 Kgs 7:46; Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Zeredah</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.18" osisID="2Chr.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Due to the very large number of objects, Solomon didn’t even try to weigh the bronze. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.19" osisID="2Chr.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon also made all the equipment for God’s temple: the gold altar; the tables for the bread of the presence; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.20" osisID="2Chr.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the lampstands with their lamps, all of pure gold, to burn before the inner sanctuary as prescribed; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.21" osisID="2Chr.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the flowers, the lamps, and the tongs of pure gold; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.4.22" osisID="2Chr.4.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and the wick trimmers, bowls, ladles, and censers of pure gold. As for the temple entrance, the inner doors to the most holy place as well as the doors to the main hall were made of gold.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.5" osisID="2Chr.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="2Chr.5.1-2Chr.5.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.5.1" osisID="2Chr.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When all of Solomon’s work on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple was finished, he brought the silver, gold, and all the objects his father David had dedicated and put them in the treasuries of God’s temple.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.5.2-2Chr.5.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon dedicates the temple</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.5.2" osisID="2Chr.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon assembled Israel’s elders, all the tribal leaders, and the clan chieftains of Israel at Jerusalem to bring up the chest containing the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s covenant from Zion, David’s City. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.3" osisID="2Chr.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everyone in Israel assembled before the king in the seventh month,<note osisRef="2Chr.5.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.5.3!note.u">September-October, Tishrei</note> during the festival. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.4" osisID="2Chr.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When all Israel’s elders had arrived, the Levites picked up the chest. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.5" osisID="2Chr.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They brought the chest, the meeting tent, and all the holy objects that were in the tent. The priests and<note osisRef="2Chr.5.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.5.5!note.v">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the levitical priests</hi></note> the Levites brought them up, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.6" osisID="2Chr.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">while King Solomon and the entire Israelite assembly that had joined him before the chest sacrificed countless sheep and oxen. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.7" osisID="2Chr.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests brought the chest containing the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s covenant to its designated spot beneath the wings of the winged creatures in the inner sanctuary of the temple, the most holy place. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.8" osisID="2Chr.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The winged creatures spread their wings over the place where the chest rested, covering the chest and its carrying poles. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.9" osisID="2Chr.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The carrying poles were so long that their tips could be seen from the holy place<note osisRef="2Chr.5.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.5.9!note.w">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the chest</hi></note> in front of the inner sanctuary, though they weren’t visible from outside. They are still there today. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.10" osisID="2Chr.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nothing was in the chest except the two stone tablets Moses placed there while at Horeb, where the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made a covenant with the Israelites after they left Egypt.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.5.11" osisID="2Chr.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the priests left the holy place. All the priests who were present had sanctified themselves, regardless of their divisions. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.12" osisID="2Chr.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the levitical musicians—Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, and their families and relatives—were dressed in fine linen and stood east of the altar with cymbals, harps, and zithers, along with one hundred twenty priests blowing trumpets. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.13" osisID="2Chr.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The trumpeters and singers joined together to praise and thank the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> as one. Accompanied by trumpets, cymbals, and other musical instruments, they began to sing, praising the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>: </verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="2Chr.5.13" osisID="2Chr.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Yes, God is good!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="2Chr.5.13" osisID="2Chr.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Yes, God’s faithful love lasts forever!</verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.5.13" osisID="2Chr.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Then a cloud filled the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.<note osisRef="2Chr.5.13" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.5.13!note.x">Cf LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the temple, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.5.14" osisID="2Chr.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests were unable to carry out their duties on account of the cloud because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s glory filled God’s temple.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.6" osisID="2Chr.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="2Chr.6.1-2Chr.6.42" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.6.1" osisID="2Chr.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon said, <q type="x-start">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said that he would live in a dark cloud;</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.2" osisID="2Chr.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">but God, I have built you a lofty temple—a place where you can live forever.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.6.3" osisID="2Chr.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king turned around, and while the entire assembly of Israel was standing there, he blessed them, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.4" osisID="2Chr.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">saying:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.4" osisID="2Chr.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Bless the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of Israel, who spoke directly to my father David and now has kept his promise: </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.5" osisID="2Chr.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">From the day I brought my people out of the land of Egypt, I haven’t selected a city from any Israelite tribe as a site for the building of a temple for my name. Neither have I chosen anyone as prince over my people Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.6" osisID="2Chr.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But now I have chosen Jerusalem as a place for my name, and David as prince over my people Israel.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.7" osisID="2Chr.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My father David wanted to build a temple for the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.8" osisID="2Chr.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said to my father David: <q type="x-start">It is very good that you thought to build a temple for my name. Nevertheless,</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.9" osisID="2Chr.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">you yourself won’t build that temple. Instead, your very own son will build the temple for my name.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.10" osisID="2Chr.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has kept his promise—I have succeeded my father David on Israel’s throne, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said, and I have built the temple for the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.11" osisID="2Chr.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There I’ve placed the chest that contains the covenant that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made with the Israelites.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.6.12" osisID="2Chr.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon stood before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar in front of the entire Israelite assembly and spread out his hands. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.13" osisID="2Chr.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Solomon had made a bronze platform seven and a half feet long, seven and a half feet wide, and four and a half feet high, and he set it in the middle of the enclosure. He stood on it. Then, kneeling before the whole assembly of Israel and spreading his hands toward the sky, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.14" osisID="2Chr.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">he said:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.14" osisID="2Chr.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel, there is no god like you in heaven or on the earth. You keep the covenant and show loyalty to your servants who walk before you with all their heart. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.15" osisID="2Chr.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is the covenant you kept with your servant David my father, which you promised him. Today you have fulfilled what you promised.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.16" osisID="2Chr.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel, keep what you promised my father David your servant when you said to him, <q type="x-complete">You will never fail to have a successor sitting on Israel’s throne as long as your descendants carefully walk according to my Instruction, just as you have walked before me.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.17" osisID="2Chr.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel, may your promise to your servant David come true.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.18" osisID="2Chr.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But how could God possibly live on earth with people? If heaven, even the highest heaven, can’t contain you, how can this temple that I have built contain you? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.19" osisID="2Chr.6.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, my God, listen to your servant’s prayer and request, and hear the cry and prayer that I your servant pray to you. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.20" osisID="2Chr.6.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Constantly watch over this temple, the place where you promised to put your name, and listen to the prayer your servant is praying concerning this place. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.21" osisID="2Chr.6.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen to the request of your servant and your people Israel when they pray concerning this place. Listen from your heavenly dwelling place, and when you hear, forgive!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.22" osisID="2Chr.6.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If someone wrongs another and must take a solemn pledge asserting his innocence before your altar in this temple, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.23" osisID="2Chr.6.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven, act, and decide which of your servants is right. Condemn the guilty party, repaying them for their conduct, but justify the innocent person, repaying them for their righteousness.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.24" osisID="2Chr.6.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If your people Israel are defeated by an enemy because they have sinned against you, but then they change their hearts, give thanks to your name, and ask for mercy in your presence at this temple, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.25" osisID="2Chr.6.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven and forgive the sin of your people Israel. Return them to the land you gave to them and their ancestors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.26" osisID="2Chr.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the sky holds back its rain because Israel has sinned against you, but they then pray concerning this place, give thanks to your name, and turn away from their sin because you have punished them for it,<note osisRef="2Chr.6.26" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.6.26!note.y">LXX, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">you have answered them</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.27" osisID="2Chr.6.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven and forgive the sin of your servants, your people Israel. Teach them the best way for them to follow, and send rain on your land that you gave to your people as an inheritance.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.28" osisID="2Chr.6.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whenever there is a famine or plague in the land, or whenever there is blight, mildew, locusts, or grasshoppers, or whenever someone’s enemies attack them in their cities, or any plague or illness comes, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.29" osisID="2Chr.6.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">whatever prayer or petition is made by any individual or by all of your people Israel—because people will recognize their own pain and suffering and spread out their hands toward this temple—</verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.30" osisID="2Chr.6.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven where you live. Forgive, act, and repay each person according to all their conduct because you know their hearts. You alone know the human heart! </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.31" osisID="2Chr.6.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Do this that they may revere you by following your ways all the days they live on the fertile land that you gave to our ancestors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.32" osisID="2Chr.6.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen also to the foreigner who isn’t from your people Israel, but who comes from a distant country because of your great reputation, your great power, and your outstretched arm. When they come and pray toward this temple, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.33" osisID="2Chr.6.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven where you live, and do everything the foreigner asks. Do this so that all the people of the earth may know your reputation and revere you, as your people Israel do, and recognize that this temple I have built bears your name.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.34" osisID="2Chr.6.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When your people go to war against their enemies, wherever you may send them, and they pray to you toward this city that you have chosen and concerning this temple that I have built for your name, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.35" osisID="2Chr.6.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen from heaven to their prayer and request and do what is right for them.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.36" osisID="2Chr.6.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they sin against you, for there is no one who doesn’t sin, and you become angry with them and hand them over to an enemy who takes them away as prisoners to enemy territory, whether distant or nearby, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.37" osisID="2Chr.6.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">if they change their heart in whatever land they are held captive, turning back and begging for your mercy,<note osisRef="2Chr.6.37" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.6.37!note.z">MT adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the land they are held captive.</hi></note> saying,<q type="x-complete">We have sinned, we have done wrong, and we have acted wickedly!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.38" osisID="2Chr.6.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and if they return to you with all their heart and all their being in the enemy territory where they’ve been taken captive, and pray concerning their land, which you gave to their ancestors, concerning the city you have chosen, and concerning this temple I have built for your name, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.39" osisID="2Chr.6.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then listen to their prayer and request from your heavenly dwelling place. Do what is right for them, and forgive your people who have sinned against you.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.6.40" osisID="2Chr.6.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now, my God, may your eyes be open and your ears attentive to the prayers of this place. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.41" osisID="2Chr.6.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And now go, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God, to your resting place, you and your mighty chest. May your priests, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God, be clothed with salvation; may those loyal to you rejoice in what is good. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.6.42" osisID="2Chr.6.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God, don’t reject your anointed one.<note osisRef="2Chr.6.42" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.6.42!note.a">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">anointed ones</hi></note> Remember your faithful loyalty to your servant David.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.7" osisID="2Chr.7" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="7"><div scope="2Chr.7.1-2Chr.7.11" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.7.1" osisID="2Chr.7.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as Solomon finished praying, fire came down from heaven and consumed the entirely burned offering and the sacrifices, while the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s glory filled the temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.2" osisID="2Chr.7.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests were unable to enter the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s glory had filled the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.3" osisID="2Chr.7.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the Israelites were watching when the fire fell. As the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s glory filled the temple, they knelt down on the pavement with their faces to the ground, worshipping and giving thanks to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, saying, <q type="x-complete">Yes, God is good! Yes, God’s faithful love lasts forever!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.7.4" osisID="2Chr.7.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king and all the people sacrificed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.5" osisID="2Chr.7.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon sacrificed twenty-two thousand oxen and one hundred twenty thousand sheep when the king and all the people dedicated God’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.6" osisID="2Chr.7.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests stood at their posts, as did the Levites with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s musical instruments, which King David had made for giving thanks to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, saying, <q type="x-complete">Yes, God’s faithful love lasts forever!</q> and which David had used when he gave praise. Across from them, the priests were blowing trumpets while all Israel was standing.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.7.7" osisID="2Chr.7.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon also dedicated the middle of the courtyard in front of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. He had to offer the entirely burned offerings and the fat of the well-being sacrifices there because the bronze altar Solomon had made was too small to contain the entirely burned offerings, the grain offerings, and the pieces of fat.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.7.8" osisID="2Chr.7.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time Solomon, together with all Israel, celebrated the festival for seven days. It was a very large assembly that came from Lebo-hamath to the border<note osisRef="2Chr.7.8" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.7.8!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Wadi, </hi>traditionally <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Brook</hi></note> of Egypt. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.9" osisID="2Chr.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the eighth day there was a gathering. They had dedicated the altar for seven days and celebrated the festival for another seven days. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.10" osisID="2Chr.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the twenty-third day of the seventh month,<note osisRef="2Chr.7.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.7.10!note.c">September-October, Tishrei</note> Solomon dismissed the people to their tents, happy and content because of the goodness the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had shown to David, to Solomon, and to his people Israel. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.11" osisID="2Chr.7.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In this way, Solomon finished the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and the royal palace. He successfully accomplished everything he intended for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and his own palace.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.7.12-2Chr.7.22" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon again meets God</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.7.12" osisID="2Chr.7.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> appeared to Solomon at night and said to him: I have heard your prayer and have chosen this place as my house of sacrifice. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.13" osisID="2Chr.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When I close the sky so that there is no rain or I order the locusts to consume the land or I send a plague against my people, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.14" osisID="2Chr.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">if my people who belong to me will humbly pray, seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways, then I will hear from heaven, forgive their sin, and heal their land. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.15" osisID="2Chr.7.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From now on my eyes will be open and my ears will pay attention to the prayers offered in this place, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.16" osisID="2Chr.7.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">because I have chosen this temple and declared it holy so that my name may be there forever. My eyes and my heart will always be there. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.17" osisID="2Chr.7.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for you, if you will walk before me just as your father David did, doing all that I have commanded you and keeping my regulations and case laws, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.18" osisID="2Chr.7.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then I will establish your royal throne, just as I promised your father David: You will never fail to have a successor ruling in Israel. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.19" osisID="2Chr.7.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if any of you ever turn away from and abandon the regulations and commands that I have given you, and go to serve other gods and worship them, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.20" osisID="2Chr.7.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">then I will uproot you<note osisRef="2Chr.7.20" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.7.20!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Israel </hi>(or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">them</hi>)</note> from my land that I gave you, and I will reject this temple that I made holy for my name. I will make it a joke, insulted by everyone. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.21" osisID="2Chr.7.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everyone who passes by this temple—so lofty now—will be shocked and will wonder, Why has the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> done such a thing to this land and temple? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.7.22" osisID="2Chr.7.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The answer will come, Because they abandoned the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors, who brought them out of Egypt. They embraced other gods, worshipping and serving them. This is why God brought all this disaster on them.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.8" osisID="2Chr.8" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="8"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s buildings and prosperity</title><div scope="2Chr.8.1-2Chr.8.18" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.8.1" osisID="2Chr.8.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After twenty years of building the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and his royal palace, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.2" osisID="2Chr.8.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon next rebuilt the cities Huram had given him, and he settled Israelites there.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.8.3" osisID="2Chr.8.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon went to Hamath-zobah and seized it. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.4" osisID="2Chr.8.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He fortified Tadmor in the wilderness, along with all the storage cities he had built in Hamath. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.5" osisID="2Chr.8.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon also built Upper Beth-horon and Lower Beth-horon as fortress cities with walls, gates, and crossbars; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.6" osisID="2Chr.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Baalath; all the cities he used for storage; and all the cities used for chariots and cavalry—along with everything else he wanted to build in Jerusalem, Lebanon, and throughout his kingdom.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.8.7" osisID="2Chr.8.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Any non-Israelite people who remained of the Hittites, Amorites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites—</verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.8" osisID="2Chr.8.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">that is, the descendants of such people who were still in the land because the Israelites weren’t able to destroy them—Solomon forced into the labor gangs that are still in existence today. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.9" osisID="2Chr.8.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, Solomon didn’t force the Israelites to work as slaves; instead, they became warriors, chief officers, and the commanders of his chariots and cavalry. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.10" osisID="2Chr.8.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And Solomon had two hundred fifty chief officers<note osisRef="2Chr.8.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.8.10!note.e">Qere; Kethib <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">officers of the troops</hi></note> who were in charge of the people.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.8.11" osisID="2Chr.8.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon brought Pharaoh’s daughter from David’s City to a palace he had built for her, because he said, <q type="x-complete">My wife mustn’t live in the palace of Israel’s King David, because the places where the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s chest has been are holy.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.8.12" osisID="2Chr.8.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon offered entirely burned offerings to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar that Solomon had built in front of the porch, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.13" osisID="2Chr.8.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">as each day required, according to the commandment of Moses for sabbaths, new moon festivals, and the three annual festivals—Unleavened Bread, Weeks, and Booths. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.14" osisID="2Chr.8.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Just as his father David had ordered, Solomon set up the divisions of the priests for their services and the Levites to their posts for offering praise and ministering in front of the priests, doing what needed to be done each day; as well as the gatekeepers in their divisions at each gate, because this was what David the man of God had commanded. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.15" osisID="2Chr.8.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They didn’t deviate in any way from the king’s commands concerning the priests, the Levites, or the treasuries. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.16" osisID="2Chr.8.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All Solomon’s work was carried out from the day the foundation of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple was laid until its completion. Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple was completely finished.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.8.17" osisID="2Chr.8.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Solomon went to Ezion-geber and Eloth on the coast in the land of Edom. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.8.18" osisID="2Chr.8.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Huram had his servants bring ships to Solomon, along with crews of expert sailors. They went with Solomon’s servants to Ophir and imported four hundred fifty kikkars of gold, which they brought back to King Solomon.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.9" osisID="2Chr.9" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="9"><div scope="2Chr.9.1-2Chr.9.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Queen of Sheba</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Chr.9.1" osisID="2Chr.9.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the queen of Sheba heard reports about Solomon, she came to Jerusalem to test Solomon with riddles. Accompanying her was a huge entourage, with camels carrying spices, large amounts of gold, and precious stones. After she arrived, she told Solomon everything that was on her mind. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.2" osisID="2Chr.9.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon answered all her questions; nothing was too difficult for him to answer. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.3" osisID="2Chr.9.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the queen of Sheba saw how wise Solomon was, the palace he had built, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.4" osisID="2Chr.9.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the food on his table, his servants’ quarters, the function and dress of his attendants, his cupbearers and their dress, and the entirely burned offerings he offered at the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple,<note osisRef="2Chr.9.4" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.9.4!note.f">LXX, Syr, Vulg, 1 Kgs 10:5; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">how he processed </hi>(or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">went up</hi>) <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</hi></note> it took her breath away.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.5" osisID="2Chr.9.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">The report I heard about your deeds and wisdom when I was still at home is true,</q> she said to the king. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.6" osisID="2Chr.9.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">I didn’t believe it until I came and saw it with my own eyes. In fact, the half of it wasn’t told to me! You have far more than I was told.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.7" osisID="2Chr.9.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Your people and these servants who continually serve you and get to listen to your wisdom are truly happy!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.8" osisID="2Chr.9.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Bless the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God because he was pleased to put you on the throne as king for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God. Because your God loved Israel and wanted to establish them forever, he has made you their king to uphold justice and righteousness.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.9" osisID="2Chr.9.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then she gave the king one hundred twenty kikkars of gold, a great quantity of spices, and precious stones. Never again has such a quantity of spice come to Israel as when the queen of Sheba gave this gift to King Solomon.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.10" osisID="2Chr.9.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In addition, Huram’s servants and the servants of Solomon, who had brought gold back from Ophir, also brought algum wood and precious stones. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.11" osisID="2Chr.9.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king made steps<note osisRef="2Chr.9.11" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.9.11!note.g">LXX, Vulg; Heb uncertain</note> for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and for the royal palace with the algum wood, as well as lyres and harps for the musicians. Never before had anything like them been seen in the land of Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.12" osisID="2Chr.9.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon gave the queen of Sheba everything she wanted, even more than she had brought the king. Then she and her servants returned to her homeland.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.9.13-2Chr.9.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s wealth</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.13" osisID="2Chr.9.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon received an annual income of six hundred sixty-six kikkars of gold, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.14" osisID="2Chr.9.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">not including income from the traders and merchants. All the Arabian kings and the governors of the land also brought Solomon gold and silver. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.15" osisID="2Chr.9.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon made two hundred body-sized shields of hammered gold, using fifteen pounds<note osisRef="2Chr.9.15" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.9.15!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">six hundred shekels</hi></note> of hammered gold in each shield; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.16" osisID="2Chr.9.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and three hundred small shields of hammered gold, using seven and a half pounds<note osisRef="2Chr.9.16" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.9.16!note.i">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">three hundred shekels</hi></note> of hammered gold in each shield. The king placed these in the Forest of Lebanon Palace.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.17" osisID="2Chr.9.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king also made a large ivory throne and covered it with pure gold. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.18" osisID="2Chr.9.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Six steps led up to the throne, which had a gold footrest attached. Two lions stood beside the armrests on both sides of the throne. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.19" osisID="2Chr.9.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Another twelve lions stood on both sides of the six steps. No other kingdom had anything like this.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.20" osisID="2Chr.9.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All King Solomon’s drinking cups were made of gold, and all the items in the Forest of Lebanon Palace were made of pure gold, not silver, since even silver wasn’t considered good enough in Solomon’s time! </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.21" osisID="2Chr.9.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The royal fleet sailed to Tarshish with the servants of Huram, returning once every three years with gold, silver, ivory, monkeys, and peacocks.<note osisRef="2Chr.9.21" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.9.21!note.j">Or possibly <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">apes</hi>; Heb uncertain</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.22" osisID="2Chr.9.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Solomon far exceeded all the earth’s kings in wealth and wisdom, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.23" osisID="2Chr.9.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and kings of every nation wanted an audience with Solomon in order to hear his God-given wisdom. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.24" osisID="2Chr.9.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Year after year they came with tribute: objects of silver and gold, clothing, weapons, spices, horses, and mules.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.25" osisID="2Chr.9.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon also had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, together with twelve thousand horsemen that he kept in the chariot cities and with the king in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.26" osisID="2Chr.9.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ruled all the kings from the Euphrates<note osisRef="2Chr.9.26" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.9.26!note.k">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the river</hi></note> to the Philistines’ land and the border of Egypt. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.27" osisID="2Chr.9.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In Jerusalem, the king made silver as common as stones and cedar as common as sycamore trees that grow in the foothills. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.28" osisID="2Chr.9.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon’s horses were imported from Egypt and every land.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.9.29-2Chr.9.31" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Solomon’s remaining days</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.9.29" osisID="2Chr.9.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Solomon’s deeds, from beginning to end, aren’t they written in the records of the prophet Nathan, the prophecies of Ahijah from Shiloh, and the visions of the seer Iddo concerning Jeroboam, Nebat’s son? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.30" osisID="2Chr.9.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon ruled over all Israel in Jerusalem for forty years. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.9.31" osisID="2Chr.9.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Solomon lay down with his ancestors and was buried in David’s City with his father. His son Rehoboam succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.10" osisID="2Chr.10" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="10"><div scope="2Chr.10.1-2Chr.10.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">How Rehoboam lost the kingdom</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.10.1" osisID="2Chr.10.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam went to Shechem, where all Israel had come to make him king. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.2" osisID="2Chr.10.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, heard the news, he returned from Egypt where he had fled from King Solomon. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.3" osisID="2Chr.10.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people sent and called for Jeroboam, who along with all Israel came and said to Rehoboam, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.4" osisID="2Chr.10.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Your father made our workload<note osisRef="2Chr.10.4" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.10.4!note.l">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">our yoke</hi></note> very heavy; if you will lessen the demands your father made of us and lighten the heavy workload he demanded from us, then we will serve you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.5" osisID="2Chr.10.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He answered them, <q type="x-complete">Come back in three days.</q> So the people left.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.6" osisID="2Chr.10.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Rehoboam consulted the elders who had served his father Solomon when he was alive. <q type="x-complete">What do you advise?</q> Rehoboam asked. <q type="x-complete">How should I respond to these people?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.7" osisID="2Chr.10.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">If you are kind to these people and try to please them by speaking gently with them,</q> they replied, <q type="x-complete">they will be your servants forever.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.8" osisID="2Chr.10.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Rehoboam ignored the advice the elders gave him and instead sought the counsel of the young advisors who had grown up with him and now served him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.9" osisID="2Chr.10.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">What do you advise?</q> he asked them. <q type="x-complete">How should we respond to these people who said to me, ‘Lighten the workload your father demanded from us’?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.10" osisID="2Chr.10.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The young people who had grown up with Rehoboam said to him,<q type="x-start">This people said to you, ‘Your father made our workload heavy. Lighten it for us!’ Now this is what you should say to them, ‘My baby<note osisRef="2Chr.10.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.10.10!note.m">Or pinky; perhaps a euphemism</note> finger is thicker than my father’s waist!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.11" osisID="2Chr.10.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">So if my father made your workload heavy, I’ll make it even heavier! If my father disciplined you with whips, I’ll do it with scorpions!’</q></verse></p> <p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.12" osisID="2Chr.10.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam and all the people returned to Rehoboam on the third day, just as the king had specified when he said, <q type="x-complete">Come back in three days.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.13" osisID="2Chr.10.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king then answered the people harshly. He ignored the elders’ advice, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.14" osisID="2Chr.10.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and instead followed the young people’s advice. He said, <q type="x-complete">My father made your workload heavy, but I’ll make it even heavier; my father disciplined you with whips, but I’ll do it with scorpions!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.15" osisID="2Chr.10.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king didn’t listen to the people because this turn of events came from God so that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> might keep his promise concerning Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, which God delivered through Ahijah from Shiloh. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">When all Israel saw<note osisRef="2Chr.10.16" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.10.16!note.n">Syr, OL, Tg; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">saw.</hi></note> that the king wouldn’t listen to them, the people answered the king,</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-start">Why should we care about David?</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">We have no stake in Jesse’s son!</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">Go back to your homes, Israel!</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">You better look after</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-end">your own house now, David!</q></verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.16" osisID="2Chr.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Then all Israel went back to their homes, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.17" osisID="2Chr.10.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and Rehoboam ruled over only the Israelites who lived in the cities of Judah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.10.18" osisID="2Chr.10.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When King Rehoboam sent Hadoram to them (he was the leader of the work gang), the Israelites stoned him to death. King Rehoboam quickly got into his chariot and fled to Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.10.19" osisID="2Chr.10.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And so Israel has been in rebellion against David’s dynasty to this day.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.11" osisID="2Chr.11" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="11"><div scope="2Chr.11.1-2Chr.11.23" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.11.1" osisID="2Chr.11.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Rehoboam arrived at Jerusalem, he assembled the house of Judah and Benjamin, one hundred eighty thousand select warriors, to fight against Israel and to restore the kingdom to Rehoboam. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.2" osisID="2Chr.11.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Shemaiah the man of God: </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.3" osisID="2Chr.11.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tell Judah’s King Rehoboam, Solomon’s son, and all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.4" osisID="2Chr.11.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: Don’t make war against your relatives. Go home, every one of you, because this is my plan. When they heard the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s words, they abandoned their attack against Jeroboam.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.11.5" osisID="2Chr.11.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam lived in Jerusalem, but he built cities for Judah’s defense </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.6" osisID="2Chr.11.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">in Bethlehem, Etam, Tekoa, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.7" osisID="2Chr.11.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Beth-zur, Soco, Adullam, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.8" osisID="2Chr.11.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Gath, Mareshah, Ziph, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.9" osisID="2Chr.11.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Adoraim, Lachish, Azekah, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.10" osisID="2Chr.11.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zorah, Aijalon, and Hebron. These were the fortified cities in Judah and Benjamin. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.11" osisID="2Chr.11.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made the fortifications stronger, placed commanders in them, and supplied them with food, oil, and wine. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.12" osisID="2Chr.11.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also stored shields and spears in each of the cities, making them very strong. This is how Judah and Benjamin remained under his control.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.11.13" osisID="2Chr.11.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests and the Levites from every region throughout all Israel sided with Rehoboam. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.14" osisID="2Chr.11.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Levites left their pastures and property to come to Judah and Jerusalem because Jeroboam and his sons had refused to let them serve as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s priests, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.15" osisID="2Chr.11.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">having appointed his own priests for the shrines and the goat and calf idols he had made. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.16" osisID="2Chr.11.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People from every tribe of Israel who had made up their minds to seek the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, came to Jerusalem to sacrifice to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.17" osisID="2Chr.11.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They strengthened the kingdom of Judah and supported Rehoboam, Solomon’s son, for three years by following the way of David and Solomon those three years.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.11.18" osisID="2Chr.11.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam married Mahalath daughter of Jerimoth, David’s son, and Abihail daughter of Eliab, Jesse’s son. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.19" osisID="2Chr.11.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The sons she bore him were Jeush, Shemariah, and Zaham. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.20" osisID="2Chr.11.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Later he married Maacah, Absalom’s daughter, who bore him Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.21" osisID="2Chr.11.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam loved Absalom’s daughter Maacah more than all his wives and secondary wives. In all, he had eighteen wives and sixty secondary wives, twenty-eight sons, and sixty daughters. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.22" osisID="2Chr.11.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam named Abijah, Maacah’s son, as his successor in order to make him king. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.11.23" osisID="2Chr.11.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He wisely placed some of his sons in every region of Judah and Benjamin, in every fortified city, and gave them plenty of food and sought many wives for them.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.12" osisID="2Chr.12" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="12"><div scope="2Chr.12.1-2Chr.12.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.12.1" osisID="2Chr.12.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But as soon as Rehoboam had secured his royal power, he, along with all Israel, abandoned the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Instruction.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.12.2-2Chr.12.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Rehoboam rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.12.2" osisID="2Chr.12.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Egypt’s King Shishak attacked Jerusalem in the fifth year of King Rehoboam because Israel had been unfaithful to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.3" osisID="2Chr.12.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Accompanying Shishak from Egypt were twelve hundred chariots, sixty thousand horses, and countless Libyan, Sukkite, and Cushite warriors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.4" osisID="2Chr.12.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He captured the fortified cities of Judah and came toward Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.5" osisID="2Chr.12.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the prophet Shemaiah went to Rehoboam and the leaders of Judah who had gathered at Jerusalem because of Shishak, and told them, This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: Since you have abandoned me, now I am abandoning you to Shishak’s power.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.12.6" osisID="2Chr.12.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the leaders of Israel and the king submitted. <q type="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is right,</q> they said.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.12.7" osisID="2Chr.12.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> saw that they had submitted, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word came to Shemaiah: Since they have submitted, I won’t destroy them. I will deliver them in a little while, and I won’t use Shishak to pour out my anger against Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.8" osisID="2Chr.12.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nevertheless, they will be subject to him so that they learn the difference between serving me and serving other nations.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.12.9" osisID="2Chr.12.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Egypt’s King Shishak attacked Jerusalem and seized the treasures of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and the royal palace. He took everything, even the gold shields Solomon had made. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.10" osisID="2Chr.12.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Rehoboam replaced them with bronze shields and assigned them to the officers of the guard who protected the entrance to the royal palace. (</verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.11" osisID="2Chr.12.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whenever the king entered the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, the guards would carry the shields and then return them to the guardroom.) </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.12" osisID="2Chr.12.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Rehoboam submitted, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was no longer angry with him, and total destruction was avoided. There were, after all, some good things still in Judah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.12.13" osisID="2Chr.12.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So King Rehoboam was securely established in Jerusalem. Rehoboam was 41 years old when he became king, and he ruled seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had chosen from all the tribes of Israel to put his name. His mother’s name was Naamah from Ammon. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.14" osisID="2Chr.12.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Rehoboam did what was evil because he didn’t set his heart on seeking the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.15" osisID="2Chr.12.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The deeds of Rehoboam, from beginning to end, aren’t they written in the records of the prophet Shemaiah and the seer Iddo, including the genealogical records? There was continual warfare between Rehoboam and Jeroboam. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.12.16" osisID="2Chr.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rehoboam lay down with his ancestors and was buried in David’s City. His son Abijah<note osisRef="2Chr.12.16" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.12.16!note.o">Spelled Abijam in 1 Kgs 14:31</note> succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.13" osisID="2Chr.13" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="13"><div scope="2Chr.13.1-2Chr.13.22" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Abijah rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.13.1" osisID="2Chr.13.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijah<note osisRef="2Chr.13.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.13.1!note.p">Spelled Abijam in 1 Kgs 15:1, 7-8</note> became king over Judah in the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.2" osisID="2Chr.13.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ruled for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Micaiah; she was Uriel’s daughter from Gibeah. When war broke out between Abijah and Jeroboam, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.3" osisID="2Chr.13.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijah went to fight with an army of four hundred thousand select troops against Jeroboam’s select forces numbering eight hundred thousand, who were arrayed in battle formation.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.13.4" osisID="2Chr.13.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Abijah stood on the heights of Mount Zemaraim in Ephraim’s highlands and said:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.13.4" osisID="2Chr.13.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">“Listen to me, Jeroboam and all Israel! </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.5" osisID="2Chr.13.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Surely you know that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, made an unbreakable covenant<note osisRef="2Chr.13.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.13.5!note.q">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a covenant of salt</hi></note> with David and his descendants that they would rule Israel forever. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.6" osisID="2Chr.13.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It was Jeroboam, Nebat’s son, the servant of Solomon, David’s son, who rebelled against his master. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.7" osisID="2Chr.13.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When some useless, worthless people joined his cause, they overpowered Rehoboam, Solomon’s son, who was too young and timid to resist them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.8" osisID="2Chr.13.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And now do you intend to challenge the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s royal rule, entrusted to David’s descendants? You may have a numerical advantage, as well as the gold calves Jeroboam made for you as gods. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.9" osisID="2Chr.13.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you’ve banished the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s priests, Aaron’s sons, along with the Levites, so that you could appoint your own priests as other countries do. Now anyone who shows up with a young bull and seven rams can become a priest of these phony gods!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.13.10" osisID="2Chr.13.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">But us? The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is our God, and we haven’t abandoned him. Aaron’s descendants serve as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s priests, assisted in the work by the Levites.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.11" osisID="2Chr.13.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Every morning and every evening they offer entirely burned offerings and fragrant incense to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, and set out bread in stacks upon a clean table. At night they light the lamps on the gold lampstand. Yes, while you are abandoning the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God, we are doing what he requires.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.12" osisID="2Chr.13.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Listen! God is on our side, at our head, along with his priests, who are ready to sound the battle trumpets against you. So, Israelites, don’t fight against the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of your ancestors, for you won’t succeed!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.13.13" osisID="2Chr.13.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Meanwhile, Jeroboam had sent troops around behind them for an ambush so that the main force was in front of Judah while the ambush was behind. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.14" osisID="2Chr.13.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Judah looked around and suddenly realized that they were surrounded, they cried out to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> while the priests sounded the trumpets </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.15" osisID="2Chr.13.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and raised the battle cry. When they raised the battle cry, God defeated Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.16" osisID="2Chr.13.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the Israelites fled before Judah, and God gave Judah the victory. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.17" osisID="2Chr.13.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijah and his people struck them severely: five hundred thousand select warriors were killed. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.18" osisID="2Chr.13.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel was subdued on that occasion, and Judah succeeded because they relied on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.19" osisID="2Chr.13.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijah pursued Jeroboam and took these cities away from him: Bethel, Jeshanah, and Ephron,<note osisRef="2Chr.13.19" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.13.19!note.r">Qere, LXX; Kethib <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Ephrain</hi></note> along with their villages. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.20" osisID="2Chr.13.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeroboam failed to regain power during the time of Abijah. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> finally struck him down, and he died. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.21" osisID="2Chr.13.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Abijah, however, grew strong. He married fourteen wives; he had twenty-two sons and sixteen daughters. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.13.22" osisID="2Chr.13.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Abijah’s deeds, what he did and what he said, are written in the account of the prophet Iddo.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.14" osisID="2Chr.14" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="14"><div scope="2Chr.14.1-2Chr.14.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.14.1" osisID="2Chr.14.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Abijah lay down with his ancestors and was buried in David’s City. His son Asa succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.14.2-2Chr.14.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Asa rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.14.1" osisID="2Chr.14.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><note osisRef="2Chr.14.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.14.1!note.s">13:23 in Heb</note> In Asa’s time, the land had peace for ten years. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.2" osisID="2Chr.14.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="2Chr.14.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.14.2!note.t">14:1 in Heb</note> Asa did what was right and good in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God’s eyes. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.3" osisID="2Chr.14.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He removed the foreign altars and shrines, smashed the sacred pillars, cut down the sacred poles,<note osisRef="2Chr.14.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.14.3!note.u">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah; cf 1 Kgs 15:13</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.4" osisID="2Chr.14.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and urged Judah to seek the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors, by doing what the Instruction and the commandments required. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.5" osisID="2Chr.14.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also removed the shrines and incense altars from all the cities of Judah so that the kingdom was at peace under him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.6" osisID="2Chr.14.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the land was at peace, he built fortified cities in Judah; there was no war in those years because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had given him rest.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.14.7" osisID="2Chr.14.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Let’s build up these cities,</q> Asa told Judah. <q type="x-complete">We’ll surround them with walls, towers, gates, and crossbars while the land is still ours, because we sought the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God and he sought us<note osisRef="2Chr.14.7" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.14.7!note.v">LXX; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and </hi>and repeats <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">we sought.</hi></note> and surrounded us with rest.</q> As a result, the people successfully completed their building projects.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.14.8-2Chr.14.15" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Judah defeats Cush</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.14.8" osisID="2Chr.14.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa had an army of three hundred thousand Judeans armed with body-sized shields and spears and another two hundred eighty thousand from Benjamin armed with small shields and bows. All were brave warriors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.9" osisID="2Chr.14.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zerah the Cushite marched against him with an army of one million men and three hundred chariots. When he got as far as Mareshah, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.10" osisID="2Chr.14.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa marched against him, setting up for battle in a valley north<note osisRef="2Chr.13.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.13.10!note.w">LXX; MT an otherwise unknown <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Zephathah Valley</hi></note> of Mareshah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.14.11" osisID="2Chr.14.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Asa cried out to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God, <q type="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, only you can help the weak against the powerful.<note osisRef="2Chr.14.11" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.14.11!note.x">Heb uncertain; or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">it is not with you to help between the many and the powerless.</hi></note> Help us, <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God, because we rely on you and we have marched against this multitude in your name. You are the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God. Don’t let a mere human stand against you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.14.12" osisID="2Chr.14.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> struck the Cushites before Asa and Judah, and the Cushites fled. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.13" osisID="2Chr.14.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa and his troops chased them as far as Gerar. The Cushites fell until there were no survivors. They were completely crushed by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and his army, who carried off a huge amount of loot, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.14" osisID="2Chr.14.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and attacked all the cities surrounding Gerar who were terrified of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. They plundered all these cities as well because there was a great amount of loot in them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.14.15" osisID="2Chr.14.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They also attacked the herdsmen’s camps, taking many sheep and camels before returning to Jerusalem.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.15" osisID="2Chr.15" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="15"><div scope="2Chr.15.1-2Chr.15.7" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.15.1" osisID="2Chr.15.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When God’s spirit came upon Azariah, Oded’s son, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.2" osisID="2Chr.15.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">he confronted Asa: <q type="x-complete">Listen to me, Asa and all Judah and Benjamin,</q> he said. <q type="x-start">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is with you as long as you are with him. If you seek him, he will be found by you; but if you abandon him, he will abandon you.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.3" osisID="2Chr.15.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">For a long time Israel was without the true God, without a priest to teach them, and without the Instruction.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.4" osisID="2Chr.15.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But in their time of trouble they turned to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God. They sought him and found him!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.5" osisID="2Chr.15.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">At that time, it wasn’t safe to travel because great turmoil affected all the inhabitants of the area.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.6" osisID="2Chr.15.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Nation was crushed by nation and city by city, as God troubled them with every kind of problem.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.7" osisID="2Chr.15.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But as for you, be brave and don’t lose heart, because your work will be rewarded!</q></verse></p></div><div scope="2Chr.15.8-2Chr.15.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Asa’s reforms</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.15.8" osisID="2Chr.15.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as Asa heard these words and the prophecy of Azariah, Oded’s son,<note osisRef="2Chr.15.8" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.15.8!note.y">Cf Syr, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and the prophecy of the prophet Oded</hi></note> he felt brave and removed the detestable idols from all of Judah and Benjamin, as well as from the cities he had captured in Ephraim’s highlands, and he repaired the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar that stood before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s entrance hall. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.9" osisID="2Chr.15.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Asa gathered all Judah and Benjamin, along with those who were living among them as immigrants from Ephraim, Manasseh, and Simeon, because many people from Israel had joined up with him when they saw that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God was with him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.10" osisID="2Chr.15.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They gathered in Jerusalem in the third month of the fifteenth year of Asa’s rule. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.11" osisID="2Chr.15.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On that day they sacrificed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> part of the loot they had taken: seven hundred oxen and seven thousand sheep. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.12" osisID="2Chr.15.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They made a covenant to seek the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors, with all their heart and all their being. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.13" osisID="2Chr.15.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They agreed that anyone who refused to seek the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, would be put to death, whether young or old, male or female. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.14" osisID="2Chr.15.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They swore this to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> with a loud voice, shouts of joy, and blasts from trumpets and horns. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.15" osisID="2Chr.15.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All Judah was delighted with the solemn pledge because they had sworn it with all their hearts. When they enthusiastically sought God, he was found by them, and the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> gave them peace on every side. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.16" osisID="2Chr.15.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa the king even removed his grandmother Maacah from the position of queen mother because she had made an image of Asherah. Asa cut down her image, pulverized it, and burned it in the Kidron Valley. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.17" osisID="2Chr.15.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Although the shrines weren’t removed from Israel, Asa nevertheless remained committed with all his heart throughout his life. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.18" osisID="2Chr.15.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He brought into God’s temple the various silver and gold objects that he and his father had dedicated. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.15.19" osisID="2Chr.15.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was no war until the thirty-fifth year of Asa’s rule.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.16" osisID="2Chr.16" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="16"><div scope="2Chr.16.1-2Chr.16.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Aram invades Judah</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.16.1" osisID="2Chr.16.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the thirty-sixth year of Asa’s rule, Israel’s King Baasha attacked Judah and fortified Ramah to prevent Judah’s King Asa from moving into that area. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.2" osisID="2Chr.16.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa took silver and gold from the treasuries of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and the royal palace and sent them to Aram’s King Ben-hadad, who ruled in Damascus, with the following message: </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.3" osisID="2Chr.16.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Let’s make a covenant similar to the one between our fathers. Since I have already sent you silver and gold, break your covenant with Israel’s King Baasha so that he will leave me alone.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.4" osisID="2Chr.16.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ben-hadad agreed with King Asa and sent his army commanders against the cities of Israel, attacking Ijon, Dan, Abel-maim, and all the store-cities of Naphtali. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.5" osisID="2Chr.16.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as Baasha learned of this, he stopped building Ramah and abandoned his work. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.6" osisID="2Chr.16.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then King Asa had all Judah carry away the stone and timber that Baasha was using to build Ramah, and King Asa used it to build Geba and Mizpah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.7" osisID="2Chr.16.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time Hanani the seer came to Judah’s King Asa and said to him, <q type="x-start">Because you relied on Aram’s king and not on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God, the army of Aram’s king has slipped out of your grasp.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.8" osisID="2Chr.16.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Weren’t the Cushites and the Libyans a vast army with chariots and horsemen to spare? Still, when you relied on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, he delivered them into your power,</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.9" osisID="2Chr.16.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes scan the whole world to strengthen those who are committed to him with all their hearts. Your foolishness means that you will have war on your hands from now on.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.10" osisID="2Chr.16.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa was angry with the seer. Asa was so mad he threw Hanani in jail and took his anger out on some of the people.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.16.11-2Chr.16.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Asa’s disease and death</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.16.11" osisID="2Chr.16.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Asa’s deeds, from beginning to end, are written in the official records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.12" osisID="2Chr.16.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the thirty-ninth year of his rule, Asa developed a severe foot disease. But even in his illness he refused to seek the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and consulted doctors instead. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.13" osisID="2Chr.16.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the forty-first year of his rule, Asa lay down with his ancestors </verse><verse sID="2Chr.16.14" osisID="2Chr.16.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He was buried in the tomb he had prepared for himself in David’s City, and was laid on a bed filled with sweet spices and various kinds of perfume, with a huge fire made in his honor.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.17" osisID="2Chr.17" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="17"><div scope="2Chr.17.1-2Chr.17.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.17.1" osisID="2Chr.17.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Asa’s son Jehoshaphat succeeded him as king. Jehoshaphat strengthened his position against Israel </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.2" osisID="2Chr.17.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">by stationing troops in the fortified cities of Judah and placing soldiers throughout the land of Judah and in the cities of Ephraim that his father Asa had captured. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.3" osisID="2Chr.17.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was with Jehoshaphat because he followed the earlier ways of his father<note osisRef="2Chr.17.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.17.3!note.z">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the ways of his father David</hi></note> by not seeking Baal. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.4" osisID="2Chr.17.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, he sought the God of his father, and unlike Israel, he followed God’s commandments. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.5" osisID="2Chr.17.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> gave him firm control over the kingdom, and all Judah brought Jehoshaphat tribute, so that he had abundant riches and honor. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.6" osisID="2Chr.17.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat took pride in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s ways and again removed the shrines and the sacred poles<note osisRef="2Chr.17.6" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.17.6!note.a">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> from Judah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.17.7" osisID="2Chr.17.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the third year of his rule, Jehoshaphat sent his officials Ben-hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Micaiah to teach in the cities of Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.8" osisID="2Chr.17.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They were accompanied by the Levites Shemaiah, Nethaniah, Zebadiah, Asahel, Shemiramoth, Jehonathan, Adonijah, Tobijah, and Tob-adonijah, and by the priests Elishama and Jehoram. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.9" osisID="2Chr.17.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They taught throughout Judah. They brought with them the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Instruction scroll as they made their rounds to all the cities of Judah, teaching the people.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.17.10" osisID="2Chr.17.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the kingdoms surrounding Judah were afraid of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and didn’t wage war against Jehoshaphat. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.11" osisID="2Chr.17.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some of the Philistines brought a load of silver as tribute to Jehoshaphat. The Arabians also brought flocks to Jehoshaphat: seventy-seven hundred rams and seventy-seven hundred goats. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.12" osisID="2Chr.17.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As Jehoshaphat grew increasingly powerful, he built fortresses and storage cities in Judah </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.13" osisID="2Chr.17.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and had many supplies in the cities of Judah. He also had an army of mighty warriors in Jerusalem, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.14" osisID="2Chr.17.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">registered by their clans as follows: Judah’s officers over units of a thousand included Commander Adnah with three hundred thousand soldiers; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.15" osisID="2Chr.17.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">next to him was Commander Jehohanan with two hundred eighty thousand soldiers; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.16" osisID="2Chr.17.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">at his side was Amasiah, Zichri’s son, who volunteered for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> with two hundred thousand soldiers. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.17" osisID="2Chr.17.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From Benjamin came a valiant warrior: Eliada, together with two hundred thousand armed with bow and shield; </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.18" osisID="2Chr.17.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">next to him was Jehozabad, together with one hundred eighty thousand soldiers. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.17.19" osisID="2Chr.17.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These were the individuals who served the king in addition to those the king placed in the fortified cities throughout Judah.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.18" osisID="2Chr.18" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="18"><div scope="2Chr.18.1-2Chr.18.34" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat and Ahab</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.18.1" osisID="2Chr.18.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Even though Jehoshaphat already had great wealth and honor, he allied himself with Ahab through marriage. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.2" osisID="2Chr.18.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A few years later, while Jehoshaphat was visiting Ahab in Samaria, Ahab slaughtered many sheep and oxen for Jehoshaphat and those who were with him in order to persuade him to attack Ramoth-gilead. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.3" osisID="2Chr.18.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-complete">Will you go with me to Ramoth-gilead?</q> Israel’s King Ahab asked Judah’s King Jehoshaphat.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.3" osisID="2Chr.18.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Jehoshaphat replied, <q type="x-start">I and my people will be united with you and your people in battle.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.4" osisID="2Chr.18.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But,</q> Jehoshaphat said to Israel’s king, <q type="x-complete">first, let’s see what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has to say.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.5" osisID="2Chr.18.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So Israel’s king gathered four hundred prophets and asked them, <q type="x-complete">Should we go to war with Ramoth-gilead or not?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.5" osisID="2Chr.18.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Attack!</q> the prophets answered. <q type="x-complete">God will hand it over to the king.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.6" osisID="2Chr.18.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Jehoshaphat said, <q type="x-complete">Isn’t there any other prophet of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> around whom we could ask?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.7" osisID="2Chr.18.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-complete">There’s one other man who could ask the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> for us,</q> Israel’s king told Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">but I hate him because he never prophesies anything good about me, only bad. His name is Micaiah, Imlah’s son.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.7" osisID="2Chr.18.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">The king shouldn’t speak like that!</q> Jehoshaphat said.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.8" osisID="2Chr.18.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Israel’s king called an officer and ordered, <q type="x-complete">Bring Micaiah, Imlah’s son, right away.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.9" osisID="2Chr.18.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Israel’s king and Judah’s King Jehoshaphat were sitting on their thrones dressed in their royal robes at the threshing floor beside the entrance to the gate of Samaria. All the prophets were prophesying in front of them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.10" osisID="2Chr.18.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zedekiah, Chenaanah’s son, made iron horns for himself and said, <q type="x-complete">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: With these horns you will gore the Arameans until there’s nothing left of them!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.11" osisID="2Chr.18.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The other prophets agreed: <q type="x-complete">Attack Ramoth-gilead and win! The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will hand it over to the king!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.12" osisID="2Chr.18.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Meanwhile, the messenger who had gone to summon Micaiah said to him, <q type="x-complete">Listen, the prophets all agree that the king will succeed. You should say the same thing they say and prophesy success.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.13" osisID="2Chr.18.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Micaiah answered, <q type="x-complete">As surely as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> lives, I will say only what God tells me to say.</q><note osisRef="2Chr.18.13" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.18.13!note.b">LXX, 1 Kgs 22:14; MT omits <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">me.</hi></note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.14" osisID="2Chr.18.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">When Micaiah arrived, the king asked him, <q type="x-complete">Micaiah, should we go to war with Ramoth-gilead or not?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.14" osisID="2Chr.18.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Attack and win!</q> Micaiah answered. <q type="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will hand it over to the king.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.15" osisID="2Chr.18.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the king said, <q type="x-complete">How many times must I demand that you tell me the truth when you speak in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s name?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.16" osisID="2Chr.18.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Micaiah replied, <q type="x-complete">I saw all Israel scattered on the hills like sheep without a shepherd! And then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said: ‘They have no master. Let them return safely to their own homes.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.17" osisID="2Chr.18.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Israel’s king said to Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">Didn’t I tell you? He never prophesies anything good about me, only bad.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.18" osisID="2Chr.18.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Micaiah said, <q type="x-start">Listen now to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word: I saw the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> enthroned with all the heavenly forces stationed at his right and at his left.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.19" osisID="2Chr.18.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> said, ‘Who will persuade Israel’s King Ahab so that he attacks Ramoth-gilead and dies there?’ There were several suggestions,</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.20" osisID="2Chr.18.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">until one particular spirit approached the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and said, ‘I will persuade him.’ ‘How?’ the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> asked.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.21" osisID="2Chr.18.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">‘I will be a lying spirit in the mouths of all his prophets,’ he said. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> agreed: ‘You will succeed in persuading him! Go ahead!’</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.22" osisID="2Chr.18.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">So now, since the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> placed a lying spirit in the mouths of these prophets of yours, it is the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> who has pronounced disaster against you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.23" osisID="2Chr.18.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zedekiah, Chenaanah’s son, approached Micaiah and slapped him on the cheek. <q type="x-complete">Just how did the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s spirit leave me to speak to you?</q> he asked.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.24" osisID="2Chr.18.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Micaiah answered, <q type="x-complete">You will find out on the day you try to hide in an inner room.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.25" osisID="2Chr.18.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Arrest him,</q> ordered Israel’s king, <q type="x-start">and turn him over to Amon the city governor and to Joash the king’s son.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.26" osisID="2Chr.18.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Tell them, ‘The king says: Put this man in prison and feed him minimum rations of bread and water until I return safely.’</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.27" osisID="2Chr.18.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">If you ever return safely,</q> Micaiah replied, <q type="x-complete">then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> wasn’t speaking through me.</q> Then he added, <q type="x-complete">Mark my words, every last one of you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.28" osisID="2Chr.18.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Israel’s king and Judah’s King Jehoshaphat attacked Ramoth-gilead. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.29" osisID="2Chr.18.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s king said to Jehoshaphat, <q type="x-complete">I will disguise myself when we go into battle, but you should wear your royal attire.</q> When the king of Israel had disguised himself, they entered the battle.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.30" osisID="2Chr.18.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Meanwhile, Aram’s king had commanded his chariot officers, <q type="x-complete">Don’t bother with anyone big or small. Fight only with Israel’s king.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.31" osisID="2Chr.18.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the chariot officers saw Jehoshaphat, they assumed that he must be Israel’s king, so they turned to attack him. But when Jehoshaphat cried out, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> helped him, and God lured them away from him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.32" osisID="2Chr.18.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the chariot officers realized that he wasn’t Israel’s king, they stopped chasing him.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.18.33" osisID="2Chr.18.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Someone, however, randomly shot an arrow that struck Israel’s king between the joints in his armor. <q type="x-complete">Turn around and get me out of the battle,</q> the king told his chariot driver. <q type="x-complete">I’ve been hit!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.18.34" osisID="2Chr.18.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While the battle raged all that day, Israel’s king stood propped up in his chariot facing the Arameans. But that evening he died, just as the sun was going down.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.19" osisID="2Chr.19" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="19"><div scope="2Chr.19.1-2Chr.19.3" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.19.1" osisID="2Chr.19.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Upon the safe arrival of Judah’s King Jehoshaphat to his palace in Jerusalem, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.2" osisID="2Chr.19.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehu son of Hanani the seer came out to meet him and said, <q type="x-start">Why did you help the wicked? Why have you loved those who hate the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>? This is why the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is angry with you.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.3" osisID="2Chr.19.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Nevertheless, there is some good to be found in you, in that you have removed the sacred poles<note osisRef="2Chr.19.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.19.3!note.c">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherot</hi>, perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> from the land and set your mind to seek God.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="2Chr.19.4-2Chr.19.11" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat’s reforms</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.19.4" osisID="2Chr.19.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Though Jehoshaphat lived in Jerusalem, he regularly went out among the people between Beer-sheba and Ephraim’s highlands, and encouraged them to return to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.5" osisID="2Chr.19.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He appointed judges throughout the land in each of the fortified cities of Judah, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.6" osisID="2Chr.19.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">instructing them, <q type="x-start">Be careful when you pass judgment. You aren’t dispensing justice by merely human standards but for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, who is with you.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.7" osisID="2Chr.19.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Therefore, respect the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and act accordingly, because there can be no injustice, playing favorites, or taking bribes when it comes to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.19.8" osisID="2Chr.19.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat also appointed judges in Jerusalem from among the Levites, the priests, and the family heads of Israel to administer the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Instruction and to settle disputes among those living<note osisRef="2Chr.19.8" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.19.8!note.d">LXX, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">they returned to Jerusalem</hi></note> in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.9" osisID="2Chr.19.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He instructed them, <q type="x-start">You must respect the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> at all times, in truth, and with complete integrity.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.10" osisID="2Chr.19.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">In any case that comes before you from a fellow citizen in an outlying town, whether it involves bloodshed or is an issue of instruction, commandment, regulations, or case laws, you must warn them not to sin against the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, consequently making him angry with both you and your fellow citizen. Do this, and you won’t sin.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.19.11" osisID="2Chr.19.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Amariah the chief priest will be in charge of all religious matters, and Zebadiah, Ishmael’s son, the leader of Judah’s house, will be in charge of all civil matters. The Levites will serve as your officers of the court. Carry out your duties with confidence, and may the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> be with those who do good.</q></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.20" osisID="2Chr.20" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="20"><div scope="2Chr.20.1-2Chr.20.30" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat’s victory</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.20.1" osisID="2Chr.20.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some time later, the Moabites and the Ammonites, along with some of the Meunites,<note osisRef="2Chr.20.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.20.1!note.e">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Ammonites</hi></note> attacked Jehoshaphat. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.2" osisID="2Chr.20.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat was told, <q type="x-complete">A large army from beyond the sea, from Edom,<note osisRef="2Chr.20.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.20.2!note.f">OL; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Aram</hi></note> is coming to attack you. They are already at Hazazon-tamar!</q> (that is, En-gedi). </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.3" osisID="2Chr.20.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Frightened, Jehoshaphat decided to seek the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s help and proclaimed a fast for all Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.4" osisID="2Chr.20.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People from all of Judah’s cities came to ask the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> for help. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.5" osisID="2Chr.20.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Jehoshaphat stood up in the congregation of Judah and Jerusalem in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple in front of the new courtyard. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.6" osisID="2Chr.20.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of our ancestors, you alone are God in heaven. You rule all the kingdoms of the nations. You are so powerful that no one can oppose you.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.7" osisID="2Chr.20.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">You, our God, drove out the inhabitants of this land before your people Israel and gave this land to the descendants of your friend Abraham forever.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.8" osisID="2Chr.20.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They have lived in it and have built a sanctuary in honor of your name in it, saying, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.9" osisID="2Chr.20.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">‘If calamity, sword, flood,<note osisRef="2Chr.20.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.20.9!note.g">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">judgment</hi></note> plague, or famine comes upon us, we will stand before this temple, before you, because your name is in this temple. We will cry out to you in our distress, and you will hear us and save us.’</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.10" osisID="2Chr.20.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">So look here! The Ammonites, the Moabites, and those from Mount Seir—the people you wouldn’t let Israel invade when they came out of Egypt’s land, so Israel avoided them and didn’t destroy them—</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.11" osisID="2Chr.20.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">here they are, returning the favor by coming to drive us out of your possession that you gave to us!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.12" osisID="2Chr.20.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Our God, won’t you punish them? We are powerless against this mighty army that is about to attack us. We don’t know what to do, and so we are looking to you for help.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.13" osisID="2Chr.20.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All Judah was standing before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, even their little ones, wives, and children. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.14" osisID="2Chr.20.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s spirit came upon Jahaziel son of Zechariah son of Benaiah son of Jeiel son of Mattaniah, a Levite of the line of Asaph, as he stood in the middle of the assembly.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.15" osisID="2Chr.20.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Pay attention, all of Judah, every inhabitant of Jerusalem, and King Jehoshaphat,</q> Jahaziel said. <q type="x-start">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says to you: Don’t be afraid or discouraged by this great army because the battle isn’t yours. It belongs to God!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.16" osisID="2Chr.20.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">March out against them tomorrow. Since they will be coming through the Ziz pass, meet them at the end of the valley that opens into the Jeruel wilderness.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.17" osisID="2Chr.20.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">You don’t need to fight this battle. Just take your places, stand ready, and watch how the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, who is with you, will deliver you, Judah and Jerusalem. Don’t be afraid or discouraged! Go out tomorrow and face them. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will be with you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.18" osisID="2Chr.20.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Jehoshaphat bowed down with his face to the ground, and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> in worship. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.19" osisID="2Chr.20.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Levites from the lines of Kohath and Korah stood up to loudly praise the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of Israel.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.20" osisID="2Chr.20.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Early the next morning they went into the Tekoa wilderness. When they were about to go out, Jehoshaphat stood and said, <q type="x-complete">Listen to me, Judah and every inhabitant of Jerusalem! Trust the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God, and you will stand firm; trust his prophets and succeed!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.21" osisID="2Chr.20.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After consulting with the people, Jehoshaphat appointed musicians to play for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, praising his majestic holiness. They were to march out before the warriors, saying, <q type="x-complete">Give thanks to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> because his faithful love lasts forever!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.22" osisID="2Chr.20.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As they broke into joyful song and praise, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> launched a surprise attack against the Ammonites, the Moabites, and those from Mount Seir who were invading Judah, so that they were defeated. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.23" osisID="2Chr.20.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Ammonites and the Moabites turned on those from Mount Seir, completely destroying them. Once they had finished off the inhabitants of Seir, they helped to destroy each other!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.24" osisID="2Chr.20.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Judah arrived at the point overlooking the wilderness, all they could see were corpses lying all over the ground. There were no survivors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.25" osisID="2Chr.20.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Jehoshaphat and his army came to take the loot, they found a great amount of cattle,<note osisRef="2Chr.20.25" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.20.25!note.h">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">among them</hi></note> goods, clothing,<note osisRef="2Chr.20.25" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.20.25!note.i">Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">corpses</hi></note> and other valuables—much more than they could carry. In fact, there was so much it took three days to haul it away. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.26" osisID="2Chr.20.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the fourth day they assembled in Blessing Valley, where they blessed the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. That’s why it is called Blessing Valley to this day. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.27" osisID="2Chr.20.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then everyone from Judah and Jerusalem, with Jehoshaphat at their head, joyfully returned home to Jerusalem because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had given them reason to rejoice over their enemies. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.28" osisID="2Chr.20.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They entered Jerusalem accompanied by harps, lutes, and trumpets, and they went to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.29" osisID="2Chr.20.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The fear of God came on all the surrounding kingdoms when they heard how the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had fought against Israel’s enemies. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.30" osisID="2Chr.20.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As a result, Jehoshaphat’s rule was peaceful because his God gave him rest on all sides.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.20.31-2Chr.20.37" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoshaphat’s last days</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.31" osisID="2Chr.20.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat ruled over Judah. He was 35 years old when he became king, and he ruled for twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Azubah; she was Shilhi’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.32" osisID="2Chr.20.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat walked in the way of his father Asa and didn’t turn aside from it, doing what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.33" osisID="2Chr.20.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">with the exception that he didn’t remove the shrines. The people were still not committed with all their hearts to the God of their ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.34" osisID="2Chr.20.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Jehoshaphat’s deeds, from beginning to end, are written in the records of Jehu, Hanani’s son, which are included in the records of Israel’s kings.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.20.35" osisID="2Chr.20.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Sometime later, Judah’s King Jehoshaphat formed an alliance with Israel’s King Ahaziah, which caused him to sin. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.36" osisID="2Chr.20.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They agreed to build a fleet of Tarshish-styled ships, and they built them in Ezion-geber. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.20.37" osisID="2Chr.20.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Eliezer, Dodavahu’s son from Mareshah, prophesied against Jehoshaphat: <q type="x-complete">Because you have formed an alliance with Ahaziah, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will destroy what you have made.</q> The ships were wrecked and couldn’t sail to Tarshish.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.21" osisID="2Chr.21" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="21"><div scope="2Chr.21.1-2Chr.21.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.21.1" osisID="2Chr.21.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoshaphat died and was buried with his ancestors in David’s City. His son Jehoram succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.21.2-2Chr.21.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoram rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.21.2" osisID="2Chr.21.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoram’s brothers, the other sons of Jehoshaphat, were Azariah, Jehiel, Zechariah, Azariah, Michael, and Shephatiah. All of these were the sons of Israel’s King Jehoshaphat. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.3" osisID="2Chr.21.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Their father had given them many gifts of silver, gold, and other valuables, along with fortified cities in Judah, but he gave the kingdom to Jehoram because he was the oldest son.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.21.4" osisID="2Chr.21.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Jehoram had taken control of his father’s kingdom, he established his rule by killing all his brothers, along with some other leaders of Israel. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.5" osisID="2Chr.21.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoram was 32 years old when he became king, and he ruled for eight years in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.6" osisID="2Chr.21.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He walked in the ways of Israel’s kings, just as Ahab’s dynasty had done, because he married Ahab’s daughter. He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.7" osisID="2Chr.21.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nevertheless, because of the covenant he had made with David, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> wasn’t willing to destroy David’s dynasty. He had promised to preserve a lamp for David and his sons forever. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.8" osisID="2Chr.21.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">During Jehoram’s rule, Edom rebelled against Judah’s power and appointed its own king. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.9" osisID="2Chr.21.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoram, along with all his chariots, crossed over to Zair.<note osisRef="2Chr.21.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.21.9!note.j">Correction with 2 Kgs 8:21; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">with his officers</hi></note> The Edomites, who had surrounded him, attacked at night, defeating him<note osisRef="2Chr.21.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.21.9!note.k">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he defeated Edom</hi></note> and his chariot officers. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.10" osisID="2Chr.21.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Edom has been independent of Judah to this day. Libnah rebelled against Jehoram’s rule at the same time because he had abandoned the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of his ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.11" osisID="2Chr.21.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As if that wasn’t enough, Jehoram constructed shrines throughout Judah’s highlands, encouraged Jerusalem’s citizens to be unfaithful, and led Judah astray.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.21.12" osisID="2Chr.21.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A letter from the prophet Elijah came to Jehoram that read, <q type="x-start">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of your ancestor David, says: Because you haven’t walked in the ways of your father Jehoshaphat or the ways of Judah’s King Asa,</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.13" osisID="2Chr.21.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">but have walked in the ways of Israel’s kings and have encouraged Judah and Jerusalem’s citizens to be unfaithful, just as the house of Ahab did, and because you have even murdered your own brothers, your father’s family, who were better than you,</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.14" osisID="2Chr.21.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> will now strike your family, your children, your wives, and all your possessions with a heavy blow.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.15" osisID="2Chr.21.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">You yourself will become deathly ill with a chronic disease that will cause your intestines to fall out.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.21.16" osisID="2Chr.21.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> made the Philistines and the Arabs, who lived near the Cushites, angry with Jehoram. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.17" osisID="2Chr.21.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They attacked Judah, broke down its defenses, and hauled off all the goods that were found in the royal palace, along with the king’s children and wives. Only Jehoahaz, Jehoram’s youngest son, was spared. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.18" osisID="2Chr.21.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After all this, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> struck Jehoram with an incurable intestinal disease. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.19" osisID="2Chr.21.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">For almost two years he grew steadily worse, until two days before his death, when his intestines fell out, causing him to die in horrible pain. His people didn’t make a fire in his honor as they had done for his ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.21.20" osisID="2Chr.21.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He was 32 years old when he became king, and he ruled for eight years in Jerusalem. No one was sorry he died. He was buried in David’s City but not in the royal cemetery.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.22" osisID="2Chr.22" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="22"><div scope="2Chr.22.1-2Chr.22.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.22.1" osisID="2Chr.22.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The inhabitants of Jerusalem made his youngest son Ahaziah succeed him as king because the raiding party that had invaded the camp with the Arabs had killed all the older sons. So Ahaziah, Jehoram’s son, became king of Judah.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.22.2-2Chr.22.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Ahaziah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.22.2" osisID="2Chr.22.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaziah was 22 years old<note osisRef="2Chr.22.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.22.2!note.l">LXX, Syr, 2 Kgs 8:26; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">42</hi></note> when he became king, and he ruled for one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Athaliah; she was the granddaughter of Omri. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.3" osisID="2Chr.22.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaziah walked in the ways of Ahab’s dynasty, encouraged in this wickedness by his mother. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.4" osisID="2Chr.22.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, just as Ahab’s dynasty had done, because after his father’s death they gave him advice that led to his downfall. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.5" osisID="2Chr.22.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaziah was following their advice when he went with Israel’s King Joram,<note osisRef="2Chr.22.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.22.5!note.m">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Jehoram </hi>(also in 22:6-7); the king's name is variously spelled in either long <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Jehoram </hi>or short <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joram </hi>form.</note> Ahab’s son, to fight against Aram’s King Hazael at Ramoth-gilead, where the Arameans wounded Joram. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.6" osisID="2Chr.22.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Joram returned to Jezreel to recover from the wounds he suffered at Ramah in his battle with Aram’s King Hazael. Then Judah’s King Ahaziah,<note osisRef="2Chr.22.6" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.22.6!note.n">LXX, Syr, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Azariah</hi></note> Jehoram’s son, went down to visit Joram, Ahab’s son, at Jezreel because he had been wounded. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.7" osisID="2Chr.22.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But God used this visit to Joram to bring about Ahaziah’s downfall. After his arrival, Ahaziah went with Joram to meet Jehu, Nimshi’s son, whom the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had anointed to destroy Ahab’s dynasty. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.8" osisID="2Chr.22.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While Jehu was executing judgment on Ahab’s dynasty, he discovered the princes of Judah, Ahaziah’s nephews, serving Ahaziah, and Jehu killed them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.9" osisID="2Chr.22.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Jehu went looking for Ahaziah, who was captured while hiding in Samaria. He was then brought to Jehu and executed. He was given a decent burial, however, because people said, <q type="x-complete">He was the grandson of Jehoshaphat, who sought the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> with all his heart.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.22.9" osisID="2Chr.22.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">There were now no members of Ahaziah’s dynasty strong enough to rule the kingdom.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.22.10-2Chr.22.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Queen Athaliah rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.22.10" osisID="2Chr.22.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Athaliah, Ahaziah’s mother, learned of her son’s death, she immediately destroyed the entire royal family of Judah’s dynasty. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.11" osisID="2Chr.22.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Jehoshabeath the king’s daughter secretly took Ahaziah’s son Jehoash<note osisRef="2Chr.22.11" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.22.11!note.o">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joash</hi>; the king's name is variously spelled in either long <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Jehoash </hi>or short <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joash </hi>form in 2 Kgs.</note> from the rest of the royal children who were about to be murdered, and hid him in a bedroom, along with his nurse. In this way Jehoshabeath, the daughter of King Jehoram, the wife of the priest Jehoiada and the sister of Ahaziah, hid Jehoash from Athaliah so she couldn’t murder him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.22.12" osisID="2Chr.22.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He remained hidden with them in God’s temple for six years while Athaliah ruled the country.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.23" osisID="2Chr.23" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="23"><div scope="2Chr.23.1-2Chr.23.21" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.23.1" osisID="2Chr.23.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But in the seventh year Jehoiada boldly formed a conspiracy with the following unit commanders: Jeroham’s son Azariah, Jehohanan’s son Ishmael, Obed’s son Azariah, Adaiah’s son Maaseiah, and Zichri’s son Elishaphat. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.2" osisID="2Chr.23.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They went throughout Judah recruiting the Levites from all the cities of Judah, as well as the family heads of Israel, who then came to Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.3" osisID="2Chr.23.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The entire assembly made a covenant with the king in God’s temple. Jehoiada said, <q type="x-start">Look! Here is the king’s son. He must be king, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> promised about David’s descendants.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.4" osisID="2Chr.23.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">This is what you must do: A third of you priests and Levites coming on sabbath duty will guard the gates,</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.5" osisID="2Chr.23.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">another third will be at the royal palace, and another third will be at the Foundation Gate. Meanwhile, all the people will be in the courtyards of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.6" osisID="2Chr.23.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Don’t enter the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, because only the priests or Levites on duty can do that. They are allowed to enter because they are holy, but the rest of the people must follow the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s requirements.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.7" osisID="2Chr.23.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">The Levites must surround the king, each with his weapons drawn. Whoever comes near your ranks must be killed; stay near the king wherever he goes.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.23.8" osisID="2Chr.23.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Levites and all Judah did everything that the priest Jehoiada ordered. They each took charge of those men reporting for duty on the Sabbath, as well as those going off duty, since Jehoiada hadn’t released any divisions from duty. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.9" osisID="2Chr.23.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the priest Jehoiada gave the unit commanders King David’s spears and large and small shields that were kept in God’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.10" osisID="2Chr.23.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He positioned all the people, each with their weapons drawn, near the altar and the temple, stretching from the south side of the temple to the north side, so as to protect the king. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.11" osisID="2Chr.23.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then they brought out the king’s son, crowned him, gave him the royal law,<note osisRef="2Chr.23.11" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.23.11!note.p">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">testimony</hi>; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">royal.</hi></note> and made him king. Jehoiada and his sons anointed him as everyone cried out, <q type="x-complete">Long live the king!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.23.12" osisID="2Chr.23.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Athaliah heard the noise made by the people running and cheering the king, she went to the people at the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.13" osisID="2Chr.23.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and saw the king standing by the royal pillar at the entrance, with the commanders and trumpeters beside the king. All the people of the land were rejoicing and blowing trumpets, and singers accompanied by musical instruments were leading the praise. Athaliah ripped her clothes and screamed, <q type="x-complete">Treason! Treason!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.23.14" osisID="2Chr.23.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the priest Jehoiada brought out the unit commanders who were in charge of the army. <q type="x-complete">Take her out under guard,</q><note osisRef="2Chr.23.14" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.23.14!note.q">Heb uncertain</note> he told them, <q type="x-complete">and kill anyone who follows her.</q> This was because the priest had said, <q type="x-complete">She must not be executed in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.15" osisID="2Chr.23.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They arrested her when she reached the entrance of the Horse Gate at the royal palace. She was executed there.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.23.16" osisID="2Chr.23.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoiada then made a covenant between himself, all the people, and the king, that they would be the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s people. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.17" osisID="2Chr.23.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then all the people went to Baal’s temple and tore it down, smashing its altars and images into pieces. They executed Baal’s priest Mattan in front of the altars. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.18" osisID="2Chr.23.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoiada appointed the priests and<note osisRef="2Chr.23.18" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.23.18!note.r">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">levitical priests</hi></note> Levites in charge of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, and then appointed the divisions of the priests and Levites<note osisRef="2Chr.23.18" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.23.18!note.s">LXX; MT lacks <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and then appointed the divisions of the priests and the Levites</hi></note> that David had assigned to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple to offer entirely burned sacrifices to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, as written in the Instruction from Moses, with rejoicing and singing, just as David had ordered. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.19" osisID="2Chr.23.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He posted guards at the gates of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple so that no one who was unclean in any way could enter. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.20" osisID="2Chr.23.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he took the unit commanders, the officials, the rulers of the people, and all the people of the land, and they led the king down from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, processing through the Upper Gate to the palace, where the king sat upon the royal throne. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.23.21" osisID="2Chr.23.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was at peace now that Athaliah had been executed at the palace.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.24" osisID="2Chr.24" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="24"><div scope="2Chr.24.1-2Chr.24.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoash rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.24.1" osisID="2Chr.24.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoash<note osisRef="2Chr.24.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.24.1!note.t">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joash </hi>(see 24:2, 4, 22, 24); the king's name is variously spelled in either long <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Jehoash </hi>or short <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joash </hi>form in 2 Kgs</note> was 7 years old when he became king, and he ruled for forty years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Zibiah; she was from Beer-sheba. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.2" osisID="2Chr.24.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoash did what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes as long as Jehoiada the priest was alive. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.3" osisID="2Chr.24.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoiada had him marry two wives, and Jehoash fathered sons and daughters.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.24.4" osisID="2Chr.24.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Sometime later, Jehoash wanted to renovate the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.5" osisID="2Chr.24.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He gathered the priests and the Levites and said, <q type="x-complete">Go to the cities of Judah and collect the annual tax of silver due from all Israel for the upkeep of God’s temple. Do it right away.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.24.5" osisID="2Chr.24.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">But the Levites procrastinated. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.6" osisID="2Chr.24.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the king summoned the chief priest Jehoiada and asked him, <q type="x-complete">Why haven’t you required the Levites to bring in from Judah and Jerusalem the tax imposed by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s servant Moses and the Israelite assembly for the covenant tent?</q> (</verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.7" osisID="2Chr.24.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now wicked Athaliah and her followers had broken into God’s temple and used all the holy objects of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple in their worship of the Baals.) </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.8" osisID="2Chr.24.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So at the king’s command a box was made and placed outside the gate of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.9" osisID="2Chr.24.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then a proclamation was issued throughout Judah and Jerusalem requiring the people to bring to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> the tax that God’s servant Moses had imposed on Israel in the wilderness. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.10" osisID="2Chr.24.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This so pleased all the leaders and all the people that they gladly dropped their money in the box until it was full. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.11" osisID="2Chr.24.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whenever the box was brought by the Levites to the royal accountants, as soon as they saw that a large amount of money was in the box, the royal scribe and the representative of the high priest would come, empty the box, and return it to its place. This took place day after day, and a large amount of money was collected. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.12" osisID="2Chr.24.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king and Jehoiada would give it to those in charge of the work on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple who in turn hired masons and carpenters to renovate the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, as well as metalworkers for the iron and bronze to repair the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.13" osisID="2Chr.24.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The workers labored hard, and the restoration progressed smoothly under their control until they had brought God’s temple back to its original state and reinforced it. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.14" osisID="2Chr.24.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as they finished, they brought the remaining money to the king and Jehoiada. They used it to make equipment for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, including what was used for the service and the entirely burned offerings, pans, and other objects made of gold and silver. As long as Jehoiada lived, the entirely burned offerings were regularly offered in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.24.15" osisID="2Chr.24.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoiada grew old, and when he reached the age of 130, he died. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.16" osisID="2Chr.24.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He was buried among the kings in David’s City because of his exemplary service to Israel, God, and God’s temple.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.24.17" osisID="2Chr.24.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After Jehoiada’s death, however, the leaders of Judah came and bowed before the king, and the king listened to them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.18" osisID="2Chr.24.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They abandoned the temple of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, their ancestors’ God, and worshipped sacred poles<note osisRef="2Chr.24.18" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.24.18!note.u">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> and idols. Anger came upon Judah and Jerusalem as a consequence of their sin, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.19" osisID="2Chr.24.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and though God sent prophets to them to bring them back to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and to warn them, they refused to listen. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.20" osisID="2Chr.24.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the spirit of God enwrapped Zechariah the son of the priest Jehoiada. Standing before the people, he told them, <q type="x-complete">This is what God says: Why do you defy the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s commands and keep yourselves from prospering? Because you have abandoned the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, he has abandoned you!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.21" osisID="2Chr.24.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the people plotted against Zechariah, and at the king’s command stoned him to death in the courtyard of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.22" osisID="2Chr.24.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Jehoash failed to remember the loyalty that Jehoiada, Zechariah’s father, had shown him and murdered Jehoida’s son, who cried out as he lay dying, <q type="x-complete">May the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> see and seek vengeance!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.24.23" osisID="2Chr.24.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That spring the Aramean army marched against Jehoash. They attacked Judah and Jerusalem, destroyed all the people’s leaders, and sent all the loot to the king of Damascus. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.24" osisID="2Chr.24.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Although the Aramean forces were relatively small, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> handed over to them a very large army, because the people of Judah had abandoned the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, their ancestors’ God. Jehoash was justly punished. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.25" osisID="2Chr.24.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Arameans left him badly wounded, but his own officials plotted against him for murdering the son<note osisRef="2Chr.24.25" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.24.25!note.v">LXX, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">sons</hi></note> of the priest Jehoiada. So they killed him in his bed. He died and was buried in David’s City but not in the royal cemetery. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.26" osisID="2Chr.24.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who plotted against him were the Ammonite Zabad, Shimeath’s son, and the Moabite Jehozabad, Shimrith’s son. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.24.27" osisID="2Chr.24.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The list of Jehoash’s sons, the many prophecies against him, and the account of his restoration of God’s temple are written in the comments on the records of the kings. His son Amaziah succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.25" osisID="2Chr.25" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="25"><div scope="2Chr.25.1-2Chr.25.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Amaziah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.25.1" osisID="2Chr.25.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Amaziah was 25 years old when he became king, and he ruled for twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jehoaddan; she was from Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.2" osisID="2Chr.25.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes but not with all his heart. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.3" osisID="2Chr.25.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Once he had secured control over his kingdom, he executed the officials who had assassinated his father the king. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.4" osisID="2Chr.25.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, he didn’t kill their children because of what is written in the Instruction scroll from Moses, where the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> commanded, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Parents shouldn’t be executed because of what their children have done; neither should children be executed because of what their parents have done. Each person should be executed for their own guilty acts</hi>.<note osisRef="2Chr.25.4" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.25.4!note.w">Deut 24:16</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.5" osisID="2Chr.25.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Amaziah gathered the people of Judah, organizing them into family units under captains of thousands and hundreds for all Judah and Benjamin. He summoned everyone 20 years old and older and found that there were three hundred thousand select troops, ready for service and able to handle spears and body-sized shields. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.6" osisID="2Chr.25.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also hired one hundred thousand warriors from Israel for one hundred kikkars of silver.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.7" osisID="2Chr.25.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But a man of God confronted him. <q type="x-complete">King,</q> he said, <q type="x-start">the troops from Israel must not go with you, because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> isn’t on the side of Israel or any Ephraimite.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.8" osisID="2Chr.25.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Should you go with them anyway, even if you fight fiercely, God will make you stumble before the enemy, because God has the ability to either help or make someone stumble.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.9" osisID="2Chr.25.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Amaziah asked the man of God, <q type="x-complete">What about the hundred kikkars I paid for the Israelite troops?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.9" osisID="2Chr.25.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">God can give you much more than that,</q> the man of God replied.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.10" osisID="2Chr.25.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Amaziah released the Ephraimite troops who had joined him so they could go home, but this only infuriated them against Judah, and they left in a rage. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.11" osisID="2Chr.25.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Amaziah courageously led his people to the Salt Valley, where they killed ten thousand people from Seir. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.12" osisID="2Chr.25.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Judean forces captured another ten thousand alive, brought them to the top of a cliff, and threw them off so that all were dashed to pieces. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.13" osisID="2Chr.25.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Meanwhile, the troops Amaziah had released from fighting alongside him raided cities in Judah from Samaria to Beth-horon, killing three thousand people and carrying off a large amount of loot. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.14" osisID="2Chr.25.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Amaziah returned after defeating the Edomites, he brought the gods of the people of Seir. He set them up as his own gods, bowed down before them, and burned incense to them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.15" osisID="2Chr.25.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">As a result, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was angry with Amaziah and sent a prophet to him.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.15" osisID="2Chr.25.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">Why do you seek the gods of this people?</q> the prophet asked. <q type="x-complete">They couldn’t even deliver their own people from you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.16" osisID="2Chr.25.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-complete">Since when do you give me advice?</q> Amaziah interrupted. <q type="x-complete">You better quit before you end up dead!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.16" osisID="2Chr.25.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">So the prophet stopped, but not until he said, <q type="x-complete">I know God plans to destroy you because you’ve done this and because you’ve refused to listen to my advice.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.17" osisID="2Chr.25.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After Judah’s King Amaziah consulted with his advisors, he sent a challenge to Israel’s King Joash, Jehoahaz’s son and Jehu’s grandson. <q type="x-complete">Come on,</q> he said, <q type="x-complete">let’s go head-to-head!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.18" osisID="2Chr.25.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Israel’s King Joash sent the following reply to Judah’s King Amaziah: <q type="x-start">Once upon a time, a thistle in Lebanon sent a message to a cedar: ‘Give your daughter to my son as a wife.’ But then a wild beast in Lebanon came along and trampled the thistle.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.19" osisID="2Chr.25.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Do you think that because you’ve defeated Edom, you can arrogantly seek even more? Stay home! Why invite disaster when both you and Judah will fall?</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.20" osisID="2Chr.25.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Amaziah wouldn’t listen, because God intended to use this to destroy them since they had sought Edom’s gods. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.21" osisID="2Chr.25.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Israel’s King Joash moved against Judah’s King Amaziah and went head-to-head in battle at Beth-shemesh in Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.22" osisID="2Chr.25.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Judah was defeated by Israel, and everyone ran home. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.23" osisID="2Chr.25.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At Beth-shemesh, Israel’s King Joash captured Judah’s King Amaziah, Jehoash’s<note osisRef="2Chr.25.23" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.25.23!note.x">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joash </hi>(see also 25:25); the king's name is variously spelled in either long <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Jehoash </hi>or short <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Joash </hi>form in 2 Kgs.</note> son and Ahaziah’s<note osisRef="2Chr.25.23" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.25.23!note.y">See 2 Kgs 14:13; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Jehoahaz</hi></note> grandson. Joash brought him to Jerusalem and broke down six hundred feet of the Jerusalem wall from the Ephraim Gate to the Corner Gate. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.24" osisID="2Chr.25.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Joash took<note osisRef="2Chr.25.24" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.25.24!note.z">See 2 Kgs 14:14; Heb omits <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">took.</hi></note> all the gold and silver, and all the objects he could find in God’s temple in the care of Obed-edom, and in the treasuries of the palace, along with some hostages. Then he returned to Samaria.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.25.25" osisID="2Chr.25.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Judah’s King Amaziah, Jehoash’s son, lived fifteen years after the death of Israel’s King Joash, Jehoahaz’s son. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.26" osisID="2Chr.25.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Amaziah’s deeds, from beginning to end, aren’t they written in the official records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.27" osisID="2Chr.25.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From the time Amaziah turned away from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, some people conspired against him in Jerusalem. When Amaziah fled to Lachish, they sent men after him, and they murdered him in Lachish. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.25.28" osisID="2Chr.25.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They carried him back on horses and he was buried with his ancestors in David’s City.<note osisRef="2Chr.25.28" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.25.28!note.a">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Judah</hi></note></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.26" osisID="2Chr.26" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="26"><div scope="2Chr.26.1-2Chr.26.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Uzziah rules Judah</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.26.1" osisID="2Chr.26.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then all the people of Judah took Uzziah,<note osisRef="2Chr.26.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.26.1!note.b">Uzziah is usually named Azariah in 2 Kgs 14:21; 15:1, 6-7.</note> who was 16 years old, and made him king after his father Amaziah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.2" osisID="2Chr.26.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He rebuilt Eloth, restoring it to Judah after King Amaziah had lain down with his ancestors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.26.3" osisID="2Chr.26.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Uzziah was 16 years old when he became king, and he ruled for fifty-two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jecoliah; she was from Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.4" osisID="2Chr.26.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, just as his father Amaziah had done. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.5" osisID="2Chr.26.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He sought God as long as Zechariah, who instructed him in the fear<note osisRef="2Chr.26.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.26.5!note.c">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">visions</hi></note> of God, was alive. And as long as he sought the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, God gave him success. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.6" osisID="2Chr.26.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He marched against the Philistines and broke down the walls of Gath, Jabneh, and Ashdod. Then he rebuilt towns near Ashdod and elsewhere among the Philistines. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.7" osisID="2Chr.26.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God helped him against the Philistines, the Arabs who inhabited Gur,<note osisRef="2Chr.26.7" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.26.7!note.d">Tg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Gur-baal</hi></note> and the Meunites. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.8" osisID="2Chr.26.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Meunites<note osisRef="2Chr.26.8" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.26.8!note.e">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Ammonites</hi></note> paid taxes to Uzziah, whose fame spread even to Egypt because he had grown so powerful. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.9" osisID="2Chr.26.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built towers in Jerusalem, at the Corner Gate, the Valley Gate, and at the Angle, and reinforced them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.10" osisID="2Chr.26.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also built towers in the wilderness and dug many wells for his large herds in the lowlands and the plain. He had many workers who tended his farms and vineyards, because he loved the soil. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.11" osisID="2Chr.26.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Uzziah had a standing army equipped for combat whose units went to war according to the number determined by the scribe Jeiel and Maaseiah, an officer under the authority of Hananiah, one of the king’s officials. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.12" osisID="2Chr.26.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The grand total of family heads in charge of these courageous warriors was twenty-six hundred. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.13" osisID="2Chr.26.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They commanded an army of three hundred seven thousand five hundred. They formed a powerful force that could support the king against the enemy. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.14" osisID="2Chr.26.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Uzziah supplied the entire force with shields, spears, helmets, armor, bows, and sling stones. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.15" osisID="2Chr.26.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He set up clever devices in Jerusalem on the towers and corners of the wall designed to shoot arrows and large stones. And so Uzziah’s fame spread far and wide, because he had received wonderful help until he became powerful.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.26.16" osisID="2Chr.26.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But as soon as he became powerful, he grew so arrogant that he acted corruptly. He was unfaithful to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God by entering the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s sanctuary to burn incense upon the incense altar. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.17" osisID="2Chr.26.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priest Azariah, accompanied by eighty other of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s courageous priests, went in after him </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.18" osisID="2Chr.26.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">and confronted King Uzziah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.26.18" osisID="2Chr.26.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-complete">You have no right, Uzziah,</q> he said, <q type="x-complete">to burn incense to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>! That privilege belongs to the priests, Aaron’s descendants, who have been ordained to burn incense. Get out of this holy place because you have been unfaithful! The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God won’t honor you for this.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.26.19" osisID="2Chr.26.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Uzziah, who already had a censer in his hand ready to burn the incense, became angry. While he was fuming at the priests, skin disease<note osisRef="2Chr.26.19" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.26.19!note.f">The precise meaning is uncertain; traditionally <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">leprosy</hi>—a term used for several different skin diseases. Also in 26:21-20, 23.</note> erupted on his forehead in the presence of the priests before the incense altar in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.20" osisID="2Chr.26.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Azariah the chief priest and all the other priests turned and saw the skin disease on his forehead, they rushed him out of there. Uzziah also was anxious to leave because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had afflicted him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.21" osisID="2Chr.26.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Uzziah had skin disease until the day he died. He lived in a separate house,<note osisRef="2Chr.26.21" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.26.21!note.g">Heb uncertain</note> diseased in his skin, because he was barred from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. His son Jotham supervised the palace administration and governed the people of the land. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.22" osisID="2Chr.26.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Uzziah’s deeds, from beginning to end, were written down by the prophet Isaiah, Amoz’s son. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.26.23" osisID="2Chr.26.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Uzziah died and was buried with his ancestors in a field belonging to the kings, because people said, <q type="x-complete">He had skin disease.</q> His son Jotham succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.27" osisID="2Chr.27" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="27"><div scope="2Chr.27.1-2Chr.27.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jotham rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.27.1" osisID="2Chr.27.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jotham was 25 years old when he became king, and he ruled for sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jerushah; she was Zadok’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.2" osisID="2Chr.27.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jotham did what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, just as his father Uzziah had done. Unlike Uzziah, Jotham didn’t enter the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. But the people continued their crooked practices. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.3" osisID="2Chr.27.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jotham rebuilt the Upper Gate of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and did extensive work on the wall of the elevated fortress.<note osisRef="2Chr.27.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.27.3!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">hillside; </hi>Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.4" osisID="2Chr.27.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He built towns in Judah’s highlands and fortresses and towers in the wooded areas. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.5" osisID="2Chr.27.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He fought against the king of the Ammonites and defeated the Ammonites. They paid him one hundred kikkars of silver, ten thousand kors<note osisRef="2Chr.27.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.27.5!note.i">One kor is equivalent to a homer and is possibly equal to fifty gallons of grain.</note> of wheat, and ten thousand kors of barley that year and for the next two years. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.6" osisID="2Chr.27.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jotham was securely established because he maintained a faithful life before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.7" osisID="2Chr.27.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Jotham’s deeds, including all his wars and accomplishments, are written in the official records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.8" osisID="2Chr.27.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He was 25 years old when he became king, and he ruled for sixteen years in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.27.9" osisID="2Chr.27.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jotham lay down with his ancestors and was buried in David’s City. His son Ahaz succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.28" osisID="2Chr.28" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="28"><div scope="2Chr.28.1-2Chr.28.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Ahaz rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.28.1" osisID="2Chr.28.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaz was 20 years old when he became king, and he ruled for sixteen years in Jerusalem. He didn’t do what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, unlike his ancestor David. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.2" osisID="2Chr.28.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, he walked in the ways of Israel’s kings, making images of the Baals </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.3" osisID="2Chr.28.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and burning incense in the Ben-hinnom Valley. He even burned his own sons alive, imitating the detestable practices of the nations the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had driven out before the Israelites. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.4" osisID="2Chr.28.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He also sacrificed and burned incense at the shrines on every hill and beneath every shady tree. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.5" osisID="2Chr.28.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God handed him over to Aram’s king, who defeated him and carried off many prisoners, bringing them to Damascus. Ahaz was also handed over to Israel’s king, who defeated him with a severe beating. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.6" osisID="2Chr.28.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In Judah, Pekah, Remaliah’s son, killed one hundred twenty thousand warriors in the course of a single day because they had abandoned the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, God of their ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.7" osisID="2Chr.28.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">An Ephraimite warrior named Zichri killed the king’s son Maaseiah, the palace administrator Azrikam, and Elkanah, the king’s second in command. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.8" osisID="2Chr.28.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Israelites took captive two hundred thousand women, boys, and girls from their Judean relatives and seized enormous amounts of plunder, which they took back to Samaria.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.9" osisID="2Chr.28.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">One of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s prophets named Oded lived in Samaria. When the army arrived there, he went to meet them and said, <q type="x-start">Don’t you see that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of your ancestors was angry with Judah and let you defeat them? But look what you’ve done! Your merciless slaughter of them stinks to high heaven!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.10" osisID="2Chr.28.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">And now you think you can enslave the men and women of Judah and Jerusalem? What about your own guilt before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God?</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.11" osisID="2Chr.28.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Listen to me! Send back the captives you took from your relatives, because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> is furious with you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.12" osisID="2Chr.28.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At this, some of the Ephraimite leaders—Johanan’s son Azariah, Meshillemoth’s son Berechiah, Shallum’s son Jehizkiah, and Hadlai’s son Amasa—confronted those returning from battle. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.13" osisID="2Chr.28.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Don’t bring the captives here,</q> they told them. <q type="x-complete">Your plan will only add to our sin and guilt before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. We’re already guilty enough, and great anger is already directed at Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.14" osisID="2Chr.28.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the warriors released the captives and brought the loot before the officers and the whole assembly. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.15" osisID="2Chr.28.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then people named for this task took charge of the captives and dressed everyone who was naked with items taken from the loot. They gave them clothing, sandals, food and drink, and bandaged their wounds. Everyone who couldn’t walk they placed on donkeys, and they brought them to Jericho, Palm City, near their Judean relatives. Then they returned to Samaria.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.16" osisID="2Chr.28.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time King Ahaz sent for help from the king<note osisRef="2Chr.28.16" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.28.16!note.j">LXX, Syr, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">kings</hi></note> of Assyria. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.17" osisID="2Chr.28.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Once again, the Edomites had invaded Judah, defeating Judah and carrying off captives. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.18" osisID="2Chr.28.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Philistines had raided the towns in the lowlands and the arid southern plain of Judah, capturing Beth-shemesh, Aijalon, and Gederoth, along with Soco and its surrounding villages, Timnah and its surrounding villages, and Gimzo and its surrounding villages, and occupying all of these cities. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.19" osisID="2Chr.28.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was humiliating Judah on account of Israel’s King Ahaz, because he had exercised no restraint in Judah and had been utterly unfaithful to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.20" osisID="2Chr.28.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Assyria’s King Tiglath-pileser<note osisRef="2Chr.28.20" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.28.20!note.k">MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Tilgath-pilneser</hi></note> came to Ahaz, but he brought trouble, not support. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.21" osisID="2Chr.28.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Even though Ahaz took items from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, the royal palace, and the officials to buy off the king of Assyria, it was of no help.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.22" osisID="2Chr.28.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It was during this troubled time that King Ahaz became even more unfaithful to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.23" osisID="2Chr.28.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">by sacrificing to the gods of Damascus, who had defeated him.</verse> </p> <p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.23" osisID="2Chr.28.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-complete">Since the gods of Aram’s kings are helping them,</q> he said, <q type="x-complete">I’ll sacrifice to them too, so that they will help me.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.23" osisID="2Chr.28.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">But they became the ruin of both him and all Israel. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.24" osisID="2Chr.28.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaz gathered the objects from God’s temple, cut them up, shut the doors of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, and made himself altars on every corner in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.25" osisID="2Chr.28.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made shrines in all the towns of Judah for burning incense to other gods. This made the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of his ancestors, very angry.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.28.26" osisID="2Chr.28.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Ahaz’s deeds, from beginning to end, are written in the official records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.28.27" osisID="2Chr.28.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Ahaz lay down with his ancestors and was buried in the city, in Jerusalem, but not in the royal cemetery of Israel’s kings. His son Hezekiah succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.29" osisID="2Chr.29" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="29"><div scope="2Chr.29.1-2Chr.29.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Hezekiah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.29.1" osisID="2Chr.29.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah became king when he was 25 years old, and he ruled for twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Abijah; she was Zechariah’s daughter. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.2" osisID="2Chr.29.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, just as his ancestor David had done. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.3" osisID="2Chr.29.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the very first year of his rule, during the first month, Hezekiah reopened the doors of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, having repaired them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.4" osisID="2Chr.29.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he brought in the priests and Levites and assembled them in the eastern square.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.29.5" osisID="2Chr.29.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Listen to me, you Levites!</q> he said. <q type="x-start">Make yourselves holy so you can make holy the temple of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of your ancestors by removing from the sanctuary any impure thing.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.6" osisID="2Chr.29.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Our ancestors were unfaithful and did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God’s eyes. They abandoned him, they ignored the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s dwelling, and they defied him.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.7" osisID="2Chr.29.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">They even closed the doors of the entrance hall, snuffed out the lamps, and stopped burning incense and offering entirely burned offerings in the sanctuary of the God of Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.8" osisID="2Chr.29.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">This angered the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> so much that he made Judah and Jerusalem an object of terror and horror, something people hiss at, as you can see with your own eyes.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.9" osisID="2Chr.29.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">That’s why our ancestors died violent deaths, while our sons, daughters, and wives were taken captive.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.10" osisID="2Chr.29.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But now I intend to make a covenant with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, so God will no longer be angry with us.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.11" osisID="2Chr.29.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Don’t be careless, my sons! The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has chosen you to stand in his presence to serve him, so that you can be his servants and burn incense to him.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.29.12" osisID="2Chr.29.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Then the following Levites got up:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.12" osisID="2Chr.29.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">from the descendants of the Kohathites: Mahath, Amasai’s son, and Joel, Azariah’s son;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.12" osisID="2Chr.29.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">from the descendants of Merari: Kish, Abdi’s son, and Azariah, Jehallelel’s son;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.12" osisID="2Chr.29.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">from the Gershonites: Joah, Zimmah’s son, and Eden, Joah’s son;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.13" osisID="2Chr.29.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">from the descendants of Elizaphan: Shimri and Jeuel;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.13" osisID="2Chr.29.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">from the descendants of Asaph: Zechariah and Mattaniah;</verse></p><p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.14" osisID="2Chr.29.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">from the descendants of Heman: Jehuel and Shimei;</verse></p> <p type="x-CEBListing"><verse sID="2Chr.29.14" osisID="2Chr.29.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and from the descendants of Jeduthun: Shemaiah and Uzziel.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.29.15" osisID="2Chr.29.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These men gathered their relatives, made themselves holy, and went in to purify the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple by obeying the king’s command as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had told him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.16" osisID="2Chr.29.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The priests went in to purify the inner portion of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. They brought out to the courtyard of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple all the impurities they discovered inside. Then the Levites took them out to the Kidron Valley. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.17" osisID="2Chr.29.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They began to make things holy on the first day of the first month.<note osisRef="2Chr.29.17" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.29.17!note.l">March-April, Nisan</note> On the eighth day of the month they reached the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s entrance hall. They made holy the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple for eight days, finishing on the sixteenth day of the first month.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.29.18" osisID="2Chr.29.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then they went before King Hezekiah. <q type="x-complete">We have purified the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s entire temple,</q> they said, <q type="x-start">and the altar for the entirely burned offering together with all its equipment, and the table for the stacks of bread together with all its equipment.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.19" osisID="2Chr.29.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">We have also restored and made holy all the items King Ahaz threw out during his rule in his unfaithfulness. They are now before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="2Chr.29.20-2Chr.29.36" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Hezekiah rededicates the temple</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.29.20" osisID="2Chr.29.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Early the next morning Hezekiah gathered the city leaders and went to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.21" osisID="2Chr.29.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They brought seven bulls, seven rams, and seven lambs, along with seven male goats, for a purification offering on behalf of the kingdom, the sanctuary, and Judah. Hezekiah ordered the priests, Aaron’s sons, to offer them up on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.22" osisID="2Chr.29.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they slaughtered the bulls, the priests took the blood and splashed it against the altar. Next they slaughtered the rams and splashed their blood against the altar, and also slaughtered the lambs, splashing their blood against the altar as well. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.23" osisID="2Chr.29.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Finally, they brought the goats for the purification offering before the king and the assembly. After laying their hands on them, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.24" osisID="2Chr.29.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the priests slaughtered them and smeared the blood on the altar as a purification offering to take away the sin of all Israel, because the king had specifically ordered that the entirely burned sacrifice and the purification offering should be on behalf of all Israel. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.25" osisID="2Chr.29.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah had the Levites stand in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple with cymbals, harps, and zithers, just as the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had ordered through David, the king’s seer Gad, and the prophet Nathan. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.26" osisID="2Chr.29.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While the Levites took their places holding David’s instruments, and the priests their trumpets, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.27" osisID="2Chr.29.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah ordered the entirely burned offering to be offered up on the altar. As they began to offer the entirely burned offering, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s song also began, accompanied by the trumpets and the other instruments of Israel’s King David. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.28" osisID="2Chr.29.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The whole congregation worshipped with singing choirs and blaring trumpets until the end of the entirely burned offering. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.29" osisID="2Chr.29.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After the entirely burned offering was complete, the king and all who were with him bowed down in worship. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.30" osisID="2Chr.29.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then King Hezekiah and the leaders ordered the Levites to praise the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> by using the words of David and the seer Asaph. They did so joyously; then they bowed down in worship too.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.29.31" osisID="2Chr.29.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Now that you have dedicated yourselves to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>,</q> King Hezekiah told them, <q type="x-complete">bring sacrificial thank offerings to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</q> So the assembly brought sacrificial thank offerings, with some people volunteering to provide entirely burned offerings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.32" osisID="2Chr.29.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All in all, the congregation brought seventy bulls, a hundred rams, and two hundred lambs as entirely burned offerings for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.33" osisID="2Chr.29.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">as well as six hundred bulls and three thousand sheep as holy offerings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.34" osisID="2Chr.29.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Unfortunately, there weren’t enough priests to skin all these entirely burned offerings. So their relatives the Levites (who had been more conscientious about preparing themselves than the priests) stepped in and helped them until the work was done or additional priests had made themselves holy. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.35" osisID="2Chr.29.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In addition to the wealth of entirely burned offerings, there was the fat of the well-being sacrifices and drink offerings accompanying the entirely burned offerings. In this way, the service of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple was restored, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.29.36" osisID="2Chr.29.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and Hezekiah and all the people rejoiced at what God had done for them, since it had happened so quickly.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.30" osisID="2Chr.30" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="30"><div scope="2Chr.30.1-2Chr.30.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Hezekiah’s Passover</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.30.1" osisID="2Chr.30.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Hezekiah sent word to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters to Ephraim and Manasseh as well, inviting them to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple in Jerusalem to celebrate the Passover of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.2" osisID="2Chr.30.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king, his officials, and the entire Jerusalem congregation had decided to celebrate Passover in the second month.<note osisRef="2Chr.30.2" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.30.2!note.m">April-May, Iyar</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.3" osisID="2Chr.30.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They had been unable to celebrate it at the usual time because the priests had failed to make themselves holy in sufficient numbers, and the people hadn’t gathered at Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.4" osisID="2Chr.30.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since the plan seemed good to the king and the entire congregation, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.5" osisID="2Chr.30.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">they made arrangements to circulate an announcement throughout all Israel, from Beer-sheba to Dan, to come to Jerusalem to celebrate the Passover of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel, because they hadn’t often kept it as written. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.6" osisID="2Chr.30.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Under the authority of the king, runners took letters from the king and his officials throughout all Israel and Judah, which read:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="2Chr.30.6" osisID="2Chr.30.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">People of Israel! Return to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, so that he may return to those of you who remain, who have escaped capture by the Assyrian kings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.7" osisID="2Chr.30.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t be like your ancestors and relatives, who were unfaithful to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors, so that he made them an object of horror as you can see for yourselves. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.8" osisID="2Chr.30.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So don’t be stubborn like your ancestors. Surrender to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>! Come to God’s sanctuary, which he has made holy forever, and serve the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God so that he won’t be angry with you any longer. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.9" osisID="2Chr.30.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When you return to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, your relatives and your children will receive mercy from their captors and be allowed to return to this land. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God is merciful and compassionate. He won’t withdraw his presence from you if you return to him.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.30.10" osisID="2Chr.30.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the runners went from town to town in Ephraim and Manasseh, all the way to Zebulun. But they were laughed at and made fun of. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.11" osisID="2Chr.30.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Even so, some people from Asher, Manasseh, and Zebulun were submissive and came to Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.12" osisID="2Chr.30.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Moreover, God’s power was at work in Judah, unifying them to do what the king and his officials had ordered by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s command.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.30.13" osisID="2Chr.30.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A huge crowd gathered in Jerusalem to celebrate the Festival of Unleavened Bread in the second month. A very large congregation gathered. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.14" osisID="2Chr.30.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">First, they removed the altars in Jerusalem, and hauled off the incense altars and dumped them in the Kidron Valley. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.15" osisID="2Chr.30.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They slaughtered the Passover lambs on the fourteenth day of the second month. Ashamed of themselves, the priests and the Levites made themselves holy and brought entirely burned offerings to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.16" osisID="2Chr.30.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They now took their places as laid out in the Instruction from Moses the man of God, and the priests splashed the blood they received from the Levites against the altar. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.17" osisID="2Chr.30.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since many in the congregation hadn’t made themselves holy, the Levites slaughtered the Passover lambs, making them holy to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> for all who weren’t ceremonially clean. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.18" osisID="2Chr.30.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This included most of those who had come from Ephraim, Manasseh, Issachar, and Zebulun—people who hadn’t purified themselves and so hadn’t eaten the Passover meal in the prescribed way. But Hezekiah prayed for them: <q type="x-start">May the good <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> forgive</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.19" osisID="2Chr.30.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">everyone who has decided to seek the true God, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors, even though they aren’t ceremonially clean by sanctuary standards.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.20" osisID="2Chr.30.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> heard Hezekiah and healed the people. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.21" osisID="2Chr.30.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the Israelites in Jerusalem joyfully celebrated the Festival of Unleavened Bread for seven days, with the Levites and the priests praising the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> every day, accompanied by the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s mighty instruments. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.22" osisID="2Chr.30.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah congratulated all the Levites who had performed so skillfully for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. They feasted throughout the seven days of the festival, sacrificing well-being offerings and praising the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.30.23" osisID="2Chr.30.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the whole congregation agreed to celebrate another seven days, which they joyfully did. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.24" osisID="2Chr.30.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Judah’s King Hezekiah contributed one thousand bulls and seven thousand sheep for the congregation, while the officials provided another thousand bulls and ten thousand sheep, and great numbers of priests made themselves holy. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.25" osisID="2Chr.30.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the whole congregation of Judah rejoiced, as did the priests and the Levites, the whole congregation from Israel, the immigrants who had come from the land of Israel, and those who lived in Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.26" osisID="2Chr.30.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There was great joy in Jerusalem. Nothing like this had taken place in Jerusalem since the days of Israel’s King Solomon, David’s son. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.30.27" osisID="2Chr.30.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the levitical priests blessed the people, and their voice was heard when their prayer reached God’s holy dwelling in heaven.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.31" osisID="2Chr.31" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="31"><div scope="2Chr.31.1-2Chr.31.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.31.1" osisID="2Chr.31.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When all of these things were finished, all of the Israelites who were present went out to the cities of Judah, smashed the sacred pillars, cut down the sacred poles,<note osisRef="2Chr.31.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.31.1!note.n">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> and completely destroyed the shrines and altars throughout Judah as well as Benjamin, Ephraim, and Manasseh. Then all the Israelites returned to their individual homes in their own cities.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.31.2-2Chr.31.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Hezekiah’s reform</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.31.2" osisID="2Chr.31.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah reappointed the priests and the Levites, each to their divisions and their tasks, to make entirely burned offerings and well-being sacrifices, to serve, to give thanks, and to offer praise in the gates of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s camp. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.3" osisID="2Chr.31.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As his portion, the king personally contributed the entirely burned offerings for the morning and evening sacrifices, as well as the entirely burned offerings for the Sabbaths, new moons, and festivals, as written in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Instruction. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.4" osisID="2Chr.31.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He ordered the people living in Jerusalem to provide the required portion for the priests and the Levites so they could devote themselves to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Instruction. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.5" osisID="2Chr.31.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as the order was issued, the Israelites generously gave the best of their grain, new wine, oil, honey, and all their crops—a tenth of everything, a huge amount. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.6" osisID="2Chr.31.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people of Israel and Judah, living in the cities of Judah, also brought in a tenth of their herds and flocks and a tenth of the items that had been dedicated to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> their God, stacking it up in piles. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.7" osisID="2Chr.31.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They began stacking up the piles in the third month<note osisRef="2Chr.31.7" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.31.7!note.o">May–June, Sivan</note> and finished them in the seventh.<note osisRef="2Chr.31.7" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.31.7!note.p">September–October, Tishrei</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.8" osisID="2Chr.31.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Hezekiah and the officials saw the piles, they blessed the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and his people Israel.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.31.9" osisID="2Chr.31.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Hezekiah asked the priests and Levites about the piles, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.10" osisID="2Chr.31.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the chief priest Azariah, who was from Zadok’s family, answered, <q type="x-complete">Ever since the people started bringing contributions to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple we’ve had enough to eat with plenty to spare. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> has definitely blessed his people! There’s a lot left over.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.31.11" osisID="2Chr.31.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Hezekiah ordered them to prepare storerooms in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. When they finished preparing them, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.12" osisID="2Chr.31.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the priests conscientiously brought in the contributions, the tenth-part gifts, and the dedicated things. Conaniah, a Levite, was put in charge, assisted by his brother Shimei, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.13" osisID="2Chr.31.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">while Jehiel, Azaziah, Nahath, Asahel, Jerimoth, Jozabad, Eliel, Ismachiah, Mahath, and Benaiah served as supervisors under them, as appointed by King Hezekiah and Azariah the official in charge of God’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.14" osisID="2Chr.31.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Levite Kore, Imnah’s son, who was keeper of the East Gate, was in charge of the spontaneous gifts to God. He was responsible for distributing the contribution reserved for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and the dedicated gifts. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.15" osisID="2Chr.31.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah faithfully assisted him regarding<note osisRef="2Chr.31.15" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.31.15!note.q">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">with the assistance of </hi>cf LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the cities of</hi></note> the priests by distributing the portions to their relatives, old and young alike, by divisions. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.16" osisID="2Chr.31.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Additionally, they also distributed daily rations to those males, registered by genealogy, three years old and older, all who entered the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple to carry out their daily duties as their divisions required. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.17" osisID="2Chr.31.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They also distributed to those priests registered by their families, and to Levites 20 years of age and older according to their divisional responsibilities. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.18" osisID="2Chr.31.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The official genealogy included all their small children, their wives, their sons, and their daughters—the entire congregation—for they had faithfully made themselves holy. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.19" osisID="2Chr.31.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for Aaron’s descendants, the priests who lived in the outskirts of the cities, men were assigned to distribute portions to every male among the priests and to every Levite listed in the genealogical records. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.20" osisID="2Chr.31.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what Hezekiah did throughout all Judah, doing what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God considered good, right, and true. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.31.21" osisID="2Chr.31.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everything that Hezekiah began to do for the service of God’s temple, whether by the Instruction or the commands, in order to seek his God, he did successfully and with all his heart.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.32" osisID="2Chr.32" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="32"><div scope="2Chr.32.1-2Chr.32.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Sennacherib’s invasion</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.32.1" osisID="2Chr.32.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After these things and these faithful acts, Assyria’s King Sennacherib invaded Judah and attacked its fortified cities, intending to capture them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.2" osisID="2Chr.32.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Hezekiah realized that Sennacherib also planned on fighting Jerusalem, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.3" osisID="2Chr.32.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">he consulted with his officials and soldiers about stopping up the springs outside the city, and they supported him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.4" osisID="2Chr.32.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A large force gathered to stop up all the springs and the streams that flowed through the land. <q type="x-complete">Why should the kings of Assyria come and find plenty of water?</q> they asked. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.5" osisID="2Chr.32.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah vigorously rebuilt all the broken sections of the wall, erected towers, constructed another wall outside the first, reinforced the terrace of David’s City, and made a large supply of weapons and shields. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.6" osisID="2Chr.32.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He appointed military officers over the troops, assembled them in the square of the city gate, and spoke these words of encouragement: </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.7" osisID="2Chr.32.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">Be brave and be strong! Don’t let the king of Assyria and all those warriors he brings with him scare you or cause you dismay, because our forces are greater than his.<note osisRef="2Chr.32.7" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.32.7!note.r">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">there is greater power with us than with him</hi></note></q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.8" osisID="2Chr.32.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">All he has is human strength, but we have the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God, who will help us fight our battles!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.8" osisID="2Chr.32.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The troops trusted Judah’s King Hezekiah.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.9" osisID="2Chr.32.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After this Assyria’s King Sennacherib, who was attacking Lachish with all his forces, sent his servants to Jerusalem with the following message for Judah’s King Hezekiah and all the people of Judah who were in Jerusalem:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffset"><verse sID="2Chr.32.10" osisID="2Chr.32.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what Assyria’s King Sennacherib says: What makes you so confident that you stay put in Jerusalem while it is being attacked? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.11" osisID="2Chr.32.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Obviously, Hezekiah has fooled you into surrendering yourselves to death by hunger and thirst when he says, <q type="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God will rescue us from Assyria’s king.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.12" osisID="2Chr.32.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Isn’t this the same Hezekiah who got rid of his shrines and altars, and then demanded of Judah and Jerusalem, <q type="x-complete">You must worship and burn incense before only one altar</q>? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.13" osisID="2Chr.32.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know what I and my predecessors have done to the people of other nations? Were any of the gods of these other nations able to rescue their lands from my power? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.14" osisID="2Chr.32.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Which one of any of the gods of these nations that my predecessors destroyed was able to rescue them from my power? So why should your god be able to rescue you from my power? </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.15" osisID="2Chr.32.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t let Hezekiah seduce you like fools. Don’t believe him! No god of any other nation or kingdom has been able to rescue their people from me or from my predecessors. No, your gods won’t rescue you from my power.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.16" osisID="2Chr.32.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Assyrian king’s servants continued to make fun of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God and his servant Hezekiah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.17" osisID="2Chr.32.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He wrote other letters insulting the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of Israel, defying him by saying, <q type="x-complete">Just as the gods of the nations in other countries couldn’t rescue their people from my power, Hezekiah’s god won’t be able to rescue his people from my power.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.18" osisID="2Chr.32.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then they shouted loudly in Hebrew<note osisRef="2Chr.32.18" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.32.18!note.s">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the language of Judah</hi></note> at the people of Jerusalem gathered on the wall, in an attempt to frighten and demoralize them, in order to capture the city. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.19" osisID="2Chr.32.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They spoke about the God of Jerusalem as though he were the work of human hands, like the gods of the other peoples of the earth. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.20" osisID="2Chr.32.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Hezekiah and the prophet Isaiah, Amoz’s son, prayed about this, crying out to heaven. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.21" osisID="2Chr.32.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> sent a messenger who destroyed every warrior, leader, and officer in the camp of the Assyrian king. When Sennacherib went home in disgrace, he entered the temple of his god, and his own sons killed him with a sword. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.22" osisID="2Chr.32.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is how the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> rescued Hezekiah and the citizens of Jerusalem from the power of Assyria’s King Sennacherib, and all others, giving them rest<note osisRef="2Chr.32.22" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.32.22!note.t">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he led them</hi></note> on all sides. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.23" osisID="2Chr.32.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Many people brought offerings to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> in Jerusalem and costly gifts to Judah’s King Hezekiah, who was highly regarded by all the nations from then on.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.32.24-2Chr.32.33" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Hezekiah’s illness</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.24" osisID="2Chr.32.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Around that same time, Hezekiah became deathly ill and prayed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, who answered him with a miraculous sign. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.25" osisID="2Chr.32.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Hezekiah was too proud to respond appropriately to the kindness he had received, and he, along with Judah and Jerusalem, experienced anger. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.26" osisID="2Chr.32.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, Hezekiah and the citizens of Jerusalem humbled themselves in their pride, and so they didn’t experience the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s anger for the rest of Hezekiah’s reign.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.27" osisID="2Chr.32.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah became very wealthy and greatly respected. He made storehouses for his silver, gold, precious stones, spices, shields, and other valuables. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.28" osisID="2Chr.32.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He made barns to store the harvest of grain, wine, and olive oil; stalls for all kinds of cattle; and pens for flocks. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.29" osisID="2Chr.32.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He acquired towns for himself and many flocks and herds because God had given him great wealth. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.30" osisID="2Chr.32.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah was the one who blocked the upper outlet of the waters of the Gihon Spring, channeling them down to the west side of David’s City. Hezekiah succeeded in all that he did, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.32.31" osisID="2Chr.32.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">even in the matter of the ambassadors sent from Babylonian officials to find out about the miraculous sign that occurred in the land, when God had abandoned him in order to test him and to discover what was in his heart.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.32" osisID="2Chr.32.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Hezekiah’s deeds, including his faithfulness, are written in the vision of the prophet Isaiah, Amoz’s son, in the records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings.</verse> </p> <p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.32.33" osisID="2Chr.32.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hezekiah lay down with his ancestors and was buried in the upper area of the tombs of David’s sons. All Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem honored him at his death. His son Manasseh succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.33" osisID="2Chr.33" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="33"><div scope="2Chr.33.1-2Chr.33.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Manasseh rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.33.1" osisID="2Chr.33.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Manasseh was 12 years old when he became king, and he ruled for fifty-five years in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.2" osisID="2Chr.33.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, imitating the detestable practices of the nations that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had driven out before the Israelites. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.3" osisID="2Chr.33.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He rebuilt the shrines that his father Hezekiah had destroyed, set up altars for the Baals, and made sacred poles.<note osisRef="2Chr.33.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.33.3!note.u">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherot, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> He bowed down to all the stars in the sky and worshipped them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.4" osisID="2Chr.33.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He even built altars in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, the very place the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was speaking about when he said, <q type="x-complete">My name will remain in Jerusalem forever.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.5" osisID="2Chr.33.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Manasseh built altars for all the stars in the sky in both courtyards of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.6" osisID="2Chr.33.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He burned his own sons alive in the Ben-hinnom Valley, consulted sign readers, fortune-tellers, and sorcerers, and used mediums and diviners. He did much evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes and made him angry.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.33.7" osisID="2Chr.33.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Manasseh set up the carved image he had made in God’s temple, the very temple God had spoken about to David and his son Solomon, saying: In this temple and in Jerusalem, which I have selected out of all Israel’s tribes, I will put my name forever. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.8" osisID="2Chr.33.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I will never again remove Israel from the fertile land I gave to your ancestors, provided they carefully do everything I have commanded them—keeping all the Instruction, the regulations, and the case laws given through Moses. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.9" osisID="2Chr.33.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In this way Manasseh led Judah and the residents of Jerusalem into doing even more evil than the nations that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had wiped out before the Israelites.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.33.10" osisID="2Chr.33.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> spoke to Manasseh and his people, but they wouldn’t listen. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.11" osisID="2Chr.33.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> brought the army commanders of Assyria’s king against them. They captured Manasseh with hooks, bound him with bronze chains, and carried him off to Babylon. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.12" osisID="2Chr.33.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">During his distress, Manasseh made peace with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God, truly submitting himself to the God of his ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.13" osisID="2Chr.33.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He prayed, and God was moved by his request. God listened to Manasseh’s prayer and restored him to his rule in Jerusalem. Then Manasseh knew that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> was the true God.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.33.14" osisID="2Chr.33.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After this, Manasseh rebuilt the outer wall of David’s City, west of the Gihon Spring in the valley, extending as far as the entrance of the Fish Gate, enclosing the elevated fortress<note osisRef="2Chr.33.14" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.33.14!note.v">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">hillside; </hi>Heb uncertain</note> and greatly increasing its height. He also installed military commanders in all the fortified cities of Judah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.15" osisID="2Chr.33.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He removed the foreign gods and the idol from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, as well as all the altars he had built on the hill of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and in Jerusalem, dumping them outside the city. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.16" osisID="2Chr.33.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He restored the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar, offered well-being sacrifices and thank offerings on it, and ordered the people of Judah to worship the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.17" osisID="2Chr.33.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people, however, still sacrificed at the shrines, but only to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> their God. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.18" osisID="2Chr.33.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Manasseh’s deeds, including his prayer to God and what the seers told him in the name of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, are found in the records of Israel’s kings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.19" osisID="2Chr.33.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Manasseh’s prayer and its answer, all his sin and unfaithfulness, and the locations of the shrines, sacred poles,<note osisRef="2Chr.33.19" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.33.19!note.w">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah</note> and idols he set up before he submitted are written in the records of Hozai.<note osisRef="2Chr.33.19" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.33.19!note.x">LXX <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the seers</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.20" osisID="2Chr.33.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Manasseh lay down with his ancestors and was buried in his palace. His son Amon succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.33.21-2Chr.33.25" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Amon rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.33.21" osisID="2Chr.33.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Amon was 22 years old when he became king, and he ruled for two years in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.22" osisID="2Chr.33.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes, just as his father Manasseh had done. He sacrificed to all the idols his father had made and worshipped them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.23" osisID="2Chr.33.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But unlike his father Manasseh, Amon didn’t submit before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>; instead, Amon increased his guilt. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.24" osisID="2Chr.33.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His own officials plotted against him and killed him in his palace. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.33.25" osisID="2Chr.33.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people of the land then executed all those who had plotted against King Amon and made his son Josiah the next king.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.34" osisID="2Chr.34" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="34"><div scope="2Chr.34.1-2Chr.34.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Josiah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.34.1" osisID="2Chr.34.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Josiah was 8 years old when he became king, and he ruled for thirty-one years in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.2" osisID="2Chr.34.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was right in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes and walked in the ways of his ancestor David, not deviating from it even a bit to the right or left. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.3" osisID="2Chr.34.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the eighth year of his rule, while he was just a boy, he began to seek the God of his ancestor David, and in the twelfth year he began purifying Judah and Jerusalem of the shrines, the sacred poles,<note osisRef="2Chr.34.3" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.34.3!note.y">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">asherim, </hi>perhaps objects devoted to the goddess Asherah; also in 34:4, 7</note> idols, and images. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.4" osisID="2Chr.34.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Under his supervision, the altars for the Baals were torn down, and the incense altars that were above them were smashed. He broke up the sacred poles, idols, and images, grinding them to dust and scattering them over the graves of those who had sacrificed to them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.5" osisID="2Chr.34.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He burned the bones of the priests on their altars, purifying Judah and Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.6" osisID="2Chr.34.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the cities of Mannaseh, Ephraim, and Simeon, all the way up to Naphtali, he removed their temples,<note osisRef="2Chr.34.6" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.34.6!note.z">Heb uncertain</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.7" osisID="2Chr.34.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">tore down the altars and sacred poles, ground the idols to dust, and smashed all the incense altars throughout the land of Israel. Then Josiah returned to Jerusalem.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.34.8-2Chr.34.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Josiah repairs the temple</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.34.8" osisID="2Chr.34.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the eighteenth year of his rule, after he had purified the land and the temple, Josiah sent Azaliah’s son Shaphan, Maaseiah the mayor of the city, and Joahaz’s son Joah the secretary to repair the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.9" osisID="2Chr.34.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they came to the high priest Hilkiah, they delivered the money that had been collected in God’s temple by the levitical gatekeepers from Manasseh, Ephraim, and the rest of Israel, as well as from Judah, Benjamin, and the residents of Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.10" osisID="2Chr.34.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They handed it over to the supervisors<note osisRef="2Chr.34.10" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.34.10!note.a">LXX, Vulg; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">supervisor</hi></note> in charge of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, who in turn paid it to those working on, repairing, and restoring the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.11" osisID="2Chr.34.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They then gave it to the carpenters and the builders to pay for quarried stone and lumber for rafters and beams in the buildings the kings of Judah had neglected. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.12" osisID="2Chr.34.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The men worked conscientiously under the supervision of Jahath and Obadiah, who were Levites descended from Merari, and Zechariah and Meshullam from the Kohathites. The Levites, all of whom were accomplished musicians, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.13" osisID="2Chr.34.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">were also in charge of the laborers and all the workers, no matter what their jobs, while some of the Levites served as scribes, officials, and guards.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.34.14-2Chr.34.33" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The Instruction scroll</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.34.14" osisID="2Chr.34.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While they were bringing out the money that had been brought into the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, Hilkiah the priest found the Instruction scroll that the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> had given through Moses. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.15" osisID="2Chr.34.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Hilkiah told the secretary Shaphan, <q type="x-complete">I have found the Instruction scroll in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.34.15" osisID="2Chr.34.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Then Hilkiah turned the scroll over to Shaphan, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.16" osisID="2Chr.34.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who brought it to the king with this report: <q type="x-start">Your servants are doing everything you’ve asked them to do.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.17" osisID="2Chr.34.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">They have released the money that was found in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and have handed it over to the supervisors and the workers.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.18" osisID="2Chr.34.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the secretary Shaphan told the king, <q type="x-complete">The priest Hilkiah has given me a scroll,</q> and he read it out loud before the king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.34.19" osisID="2Chr.34.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as the king heard what the Instruction scroll said, he ripped his clothes. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.20" osisID="2Chr.34.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king ordered Hilkiah, Shaphan’s son Ahikam, Micah’s son Abdon, the secretary Shaphan, and the royal officer Asaiah as follows: </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.21" osisID="2Chr.34.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Go and ask the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> on my behalf, and on behalf of those who still remain in Israel and Judah, concerning the contents of this scroll that has been found. The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> must be furious with us because our ancestors failed to obey the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word and do everything written in this scroll.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.34.22" osisID="2Chr.34.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Hilkiah and the royal officials went to the prophetess Huldah. She was married to Shallum, Tokhath’s son and Hasrah’s grandson, who was in charge of the wardrobe. She lived in Jerusalem in the second district. When they spoke to her, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.23" osisID="2Chr.34.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">she replied, <q type="x-start">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, says: Tell this to the man who sent you to me:</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.24" osisID="2Chr.34.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> says: I am about to bring disaster on this place and its citizens—all the curses written in the scroll that they have read to Judah’s king.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.25" osisID="2Chr.34.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">My anger burns against this place, never to be quenched, because they’ve deserted me and have burned incense to other gods, angering me by everything they have done.<note osisRef="2Chr.34.25" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.34.25!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">made; </hi>perhaps a reference to idols</note></q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.26" osisID="2Chr.34.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">But also say this to the king of Judah, who sent you to question the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>: This is what the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God, says about the message you’ve just heard:</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.27" osisID="2Chr.34.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Because your heart was broken and you submitted before the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> when you heard what he said against this place and its citizens,<note osisRef="2Chr.34.27" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.34.27!note.c">MT repeats <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and because you humbled yourself before me.</hi></note> and because you ripped your clothes and cried before me, I have listened to you, declares the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.28" osisID="2Chr.34.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">I will gather you to your ancestors, and you will go to your grave in peace. You won’t experience the disaster I am about to bring on this place and its citizens.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.34.28" osisID="2Chr.34.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">When they reported Huldah’s words to the king, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.29" osisID="2Chr.34.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the king sent a message and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.30" osisID="2Chr.34.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king went up to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple, together with all the people of Judah and all the citizens of Jerusalem, the priests and the Levites, and all the people, young and old alike. There the king read out loud all the words of the covenant scroll that had been found in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.31" osisID="2Chr.34.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king stood in his place and made a covenant with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> that he would follow the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> by keeping his commandments, his instructions, and his regulations with all his heart and all his being, in order to fulfill the words of the covenant that were written in this scroll. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.32" osisID="2Chr.34.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he made everyone found in Jerusalem and Benjamin join in a similar promise. The citizens of Jerusalem lived according to the covenant made with God, the God of their ancestors. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.34.33" osisID="2Chr.34.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Josiah got rid of all the detestable idols from all the regions that belonged to the Israelites, and he made everyone who lived in Israel serve the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> their God. As long as Josiah lived, they didn’t turn away from following the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> God of their ancestors.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.35" osisID="2Chr.35" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="35"><div scope="2Chr.35.1-2Chr.35.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Josiah’s Passover</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.35.1" osisID="2Chr.35.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Josiah celebrated the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Passover in Jerusalem. They slaughtered the Passover lambs on the fourteenth day of the first month.<note osisRef="2Chr.35.1" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.35.1!note.d">March-April, Nisan</note> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.2" osisID="2Chr.35.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He assigned the priests to their posts, encouraging them to fulfill their responsibilities in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.35.3" osisID="2Chr.35.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Next Josiah ordered the Levites, who were holy to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> and who instructed all Israel: <q type="x-start">Put the holy chest in the temple built by Israel’s King Solomon, David’s son. You don’t need to carry it around on your shoulders anymore. Now serve the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> your God and his people Israel.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.4" osisID="2Chr.35.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Organize yourselves by families according to your divisions, as directed by Israel’s King David and his son Solomon.</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.5" osisID="2Chr.35.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Stand in the sanctuary, according to the family divisions of your relatives the laypeople, so that there can be Levites for each family division.<note osisRef="2Chr.35.5" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.35.5!note.e">Heb uncertain</note></q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.6" osisID="2Chr.35.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Slaughter the Passover lambs and prepare the holy sacrifices<note osisRef="2Chr.35.6" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.35.6!note.f">Correction; cf 1 Esdr 1:6; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and sanctify yourselves</hi></note> for your relatives in order to celebrate according to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word through Moses.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.35.7" osisID="2Chr.35.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On behalf of the laypeople, Josiah donated from his personal holdings thirty thousand lambs and young goats, and three thousand bulls, all for the Passover offerings. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.8" osisID="2Chr.35.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His officials also provided spontaneous gift offerings for the people, the priests, and the Levites. Hilkiah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, the ones in charge of God’s temple, gave two thousand six hundred Passover lambs and three hundred bulls for the priests. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.9" osisID="2Chr.35.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Conaniah and his brothers Shemaiah and Nethanel, along with Hashabiah, Jeiel, and Jozabad, the leaders of the Levites, provided the Levites with five thousand lambs and five hundred bulls as Passover sacrifices. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.10" osisID="2Chr.35.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When everything was ready, the priests and the Levites took their places as the king had ordered. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.11" osisID="2Chr.35.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then they slaughtered the Passover lambs, and the priests splashed the blood<note osisRef="2Chr.35.11" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.35.11!note.g">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">from their hand</hi></note> while the Levites skinned the animals. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.12" osisID="2Chr.35.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Next they divided the entirely burned offerings among the laypeople by their families to sacrifice to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> as written in the scroll from Moses, and they did the same with the bulls. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.13" osisID="2Chr.35.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They roasted the Passover lambs in the fire as instructed, cooked the holy offerings in pots, kettles, and pans, and brought them quickly to all the laypeople. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.14" osisID="2Chr.35.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Next they prepared food for themselves and for the priests. Since the priests, Aaron’s descendants, were busy offering up the entirely burned offerings and fat pieces until nighttime, the Levites prepared food for themselves and for the priests, Aaron’s descendants. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.15" osisID="2Chr.35.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Asaphite singers also remained at their stations as ordered by David, Asaph, Heman, and the king’s seer Jeduthun, as did the guards at the various gates. They didn’t need to leave their tasks because their fellow Levites prepared food for them. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.16" osisID="2Chr.35.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So on that day all of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s service was prepared for celebrating Passover and offering up entirely burned offerings on the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s altar, just as King Josiah had ordered. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.17" osisID="2Chr.35.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Israelites who were present celebrated the Passover at that time, and observed the Festival of Unleavened Bread for seven days. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.18" osisID="2Chr.35.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Not since the days of the prophet Samuel had such a Passover been celebrated in Israel. And no other king of Israel had celebrated a Passover like the one Josiah celebrated with the priests, the Levites, all the people of Judah and Israel who were present, and the residents of Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.19" osisID="2Chr.35.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This Passover was celebrated in the eighteenth year of Josiah’s rule.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.35.20-2Chr.35.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Josiah’s death</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.35.20" osisID="2Chr.35.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After all of these things, when Josiah had finished restoring the temple, Egypt’s King Neco marched against Carchemish by the Euphrates, and Josiah marched out against him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.21" osisID="2Chr.35.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Neco sent messengers to Josiah. <q type="x-complete">What do you want with me, king of Judah?</q> he asked. <q type="x-complete">I haven’t come to attack you today. I’m after the dynasty that wars with me. God told me to hurry, and he is on my side. Get out of God’s way, or he will destroy you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.35.22" osisID="2Chr.35.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But Josiah wouldn’t turn back. Instead, he camouflaged himself in preparation for battle, refusing to listen to Neco’s words from God’s own mouth, and went to fight Neco on the plain of Megiddo. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.23" osisID="2Chr.35.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When archers shot King Josiah, he said to his servants, <q type="x-complete">Take me away; I’m badly wounded!</q> </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.24" osisID="2Chr.35.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So his servants took him out of his chariot, placed him in another one, and brought him to Jerusalem, where he died and was buried in the tombs of his ancestors. All Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.25" osisID="2Chr.35.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jeremiah composed a funeral song<note osisRef="2Chr.35.25" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.35.25!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">lament, </hi>twice more in this verse</note> for Josiah, and to this day every singer, man or woman, continues to remember Josiah in their funeral songs. They are now traditional in Israel and are written down among the funeral songs.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.35.26" osisID="2Chr.35.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Josiah’s deeds, including his faithfulness in acting according to what is written in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s Instruction, </verse><verse sID="2Chr.35.27" osisID="2Chr.35.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and everything else he did, from beginning to end, are written in the official records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Chr.36" osisID="2Chr.36" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="36"><div scope="2Chr.36.1-2Chr.36.4" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoahaz rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="2Chr.36.1" osisID="2Chr.36.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The people of the land took Jehoahaz, Josiah’s son, and made him the next king in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.2" osisID="2Chr.36.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoahaz was 23 years old when he became king, and he ruled for three months in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.3" osisID="2Chr.36.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king of Egypt removed him from office in Jerusalem. The Egyptian king imposed a fine on the land totaling one hundred kikkars of silver and one kikkar of gold. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.4" osisID="2Chr.36.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king of Egypt made Jehoahaz’s brother Eliakim king of Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. Neco took his brother Jehoahaz prisoner and carried him off to Egypt.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.36.5-2Chr.36.8" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoiakim rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.36.5" osisID="2Chr.36.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoiakim was 25 years old when he became king, and he ruled for eleven years in Jerusalem. He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.6" osisID="2Chr.36.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Babylon’s King Nebuchadnezzar attacked him, bound him with bronze chains, and took him to Babylon. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.7" osisID="2Chr.36.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar also took some equipment from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple to Babylon and placed them in his own temple there. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.8" osisID="2Chr.36.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The rest of Jehoiakim’s deeds, including his detestable practices and all that was charged against him, are written in the official records of Israel’s and Judah’s kings. His son Jehoiachin succeeded him as king.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.36.9-2Chr.36.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jehoiachin rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.36.9" osisID="2Chr.36.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jehoiachin was 18<note osisRef="2Chr.36.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.36.9!note.i">LXX, 2 Kgs 24:8; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">eight</hi></note> years old when he became king, and he ruled for three months<note osisRef="2Chr.36.9" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.36.9!note.j">2 Kgs 24:8; MT adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and ten days.</hi></note> in Jerusalem. He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s eyes. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.10" osisID="2Chr.36.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the springtime, King Nebuchadnezzar sent for him to be brought to Babylon, along with valuable equipment from the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple. Then he made Zedekiah his uncle the next king of Judah and Jerusalem.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.36.11-2Chr.36.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Zedekiah rules Israel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.36.11" osisID="2Chr.36.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Zedekiah was 21 years old when he became king, and he ruled for eleven years in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.12" osisID="2Chr.36.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did what was evil in the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> his God’s eyes and didn’t submit before the prophet Jeremiah, who spoke for the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.13" osisID="2Chr.36.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Moreover, he rebelled against King Nebuchadnezzar, despite the solemn pledge Nebuchadnezzar had forced him to swear in God’s name. He became stubborn and refused to turn back to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, Israel’s God. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.14" osisID="2Chr.36.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the leaders of the priests and the people also grew increasingly unfaithful, following all the detestable practices of the nations. They polluted the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple that God had dedicated in Jerusalem. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.15" osisID="2Chr.36.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Time and time again, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of their ancestors, sent word to them through his messengers because he had compassion on his people and his dwelling. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.16" osisID="2Chr.36.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But they made fun of God’s messengers, treating God’s words with contempt and ridiculing God’s prophets to such an extent that there was no hope of warding off the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s rising anger against his people.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.36.17-2Chr.36.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jerusalem destroyed</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.36.17" osisID="2Chr.36.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So God brought the Babylonian<note osisRef="2Chr.36.17" placement="inline" osisID="2Chr.36.17!note.k">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Chaldean</hi></note> king against them. The king killed their young men with the sword in their temple’s sanctuary, and showed no pity for young men or for virgins, for the old or for the feeble. God handed all of them over to him. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.18" osisID="2Chr.36.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king hauled everything off to Babylon, every item from God’s temple, both large and small, including the treasures of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s temple and those of the king and his officials. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.19" osisID="2Chr.36.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Next the Babylonians burned God’s temple down, demolished the walls of Jerusalem, and set fire to all its palaces, destroying everything of value. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.20" osisID="2Chr.36.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Finally, he exiled to Babylon anyone who survived the killing so that they could be his slaves and the slaves of his children until Persia came to power. </verse><verse sID="2Chr.36.21" osisID="2Chr.36.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is how the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word spoken by Jeremiah was carried out. The land finally enjoyed its sabbath rest. For as long as it lay empty, it rested, until seventy years were completed.</verse> </p></div><div scope="2Chr.36.22-2Chr.36.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Cyrus’ decree</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Chr.36.22" osisID="2Chr.36.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the first year of Persia’s King Cyrus, to carry out the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s promise spoken through Jeremiah, the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> moved Persia’s King Cyrus to issue the following proclamation throughout his kingdom, along with a written decree:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffset"><verse sID="2Chr.36.23" osisID="2Chr.36.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what Persia’s King Cyrus says: The <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, the God of heaven, has given me all the earth’s kingdoms and has instructed me to build a temple for him at Jerusalem in Judah. Whoever among you belong to God’s people, let them go up, and may the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> their God be with them!</verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>