<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Daniel</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="Dan"><chapter sID="Dan.1" osisID="Dan.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Daniel</title><div scope="Dan.1.1-Dan.1.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Jerusalem taken by the Babylonians</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.1.1" osisID="Dan.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the third year of the rule of Judah’s King Jehoiakim, Babylon’s King Nebuchadnezzar came to Jerusalem and attacked it. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.2" osisID="Dan.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Lord handed Judah’s King Jehoiakim over to Nebuchadnezzar, along with some of the equipment from God’s house. Nebuchadnezzar took these to Shinar, to his own god’s temple, putting them in his god’s treasury.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.1.3-Dan.1.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Training for royal service</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.1.3" osisID="Dan.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar instructed his highest official Ashpenaz to choose royal descendants and members of the ruling class from the Israelites—</verse><verse sID="Dan.1.4" osisID="Dan.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">good-looking young men without defects, skilled in all wisdom, possessing knowledge, conversant with learning, and capable of serving in the king’s palace. Ashpenaz was to teach them the Chaldean language and its literature. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.5" osisID="Dan.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king assigned these young men daily allotments from his own food and from the royal wine. Ashpenaz was to teach them for three years so that at the end of that time they could serve before the king. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.6" osisID="Dan.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Among these young men from the Judeans were Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.7" osisID="Dan.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the chief official gave them new names. He named Daniel <q type="x-complete">Belteshazzar,</q> Hananiah <q type="x-complete">Shadrach,</q> Mishael <q type="x-complete">Meshach,</q> and Azariah <q type="x-complete">Abednego.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.1.8-Dan.1.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Test</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.1.8" osisID="Dan.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Daniel decided that he wouldn’t pollute himself with the king’s rations or the royal wine, and he appealed to the chief official in hopes that he wouldn’t have to do so. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.9" osisID="Dan.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now God had established faithful loyalty between Daniel and the chief official; </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.10" osisID="Dan.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but the chief official said to Daniel, <q type="x-complete">I’m afraid of my master, the king, who has mandated what you are to eat and drink. What will happen if he sees your faces looking thinner than the other young men in your group? The king will have my head because of you!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.1.11" osisID="Dan.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Daniel spoke to the guard whom the chief official had appointed over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.12" osisID="Dan.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">Why not test your servants for ten days? You could give us a diet of vegetables to eat and water to drink.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.13" osisID="Dan.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Then compare our appearance to the appearance of the young men who eat the king’s food. Then deal with your servants according to what you see.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.1.14" osisID="Dan.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The guard decided to go along with their plan and tested them for ten days. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.15" osisID="Dan.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the end of ten days they looked better and healthier than all the young men who were eating the king’s food. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.16" osisID="Dan.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the guard kept taking away their rations and the wine they were supposed to drink and gave them vegetables instead. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.17" osisID="Dan.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And God gave knowledge, mastery of all literature, and wisdom to these four men. Daniel himself gained understanding of every type of vision and dream.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.1.18-Dan.1.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Result of the training</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.1.18" osisID="Dan.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the time came to review the young men as the king had ordered, the chief official brought them before Nebuchadnezzar. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.19" osisID="Dan.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the king spoke with them, he found no one as good as Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. So they took their place in the king’s service. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.20" osisID="Dan.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whenever the king consulted them about any aspect of wisdom and understanding, he found them head and shoulders above all the dream interpreters and enchanters in his entire kingdom. </verse><verse sID="Dan.1.21" osisID="Dan.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And Daniel stayed in the king’s service until the first year of King Cyrus.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.2" osisID="Dan.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="Dan.2.1-Dan.2.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">An impossible challenge</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.2.1" osisID="Dan.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the second year of Nebuchadnezzar’s rule, he had many dreams. The dreams made him anxious, but he kept sleeping. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.2" osisID="Dan.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king summoned the dream interpreters, enchanters, diviners, and Chaldeans to explain his dreams to him. They came and stood before the king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.3" osisID="Dan.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king said to them: <q type="x-complete">I had a dream, and I’m anxious to know its meaning.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.4" osisID="Dan.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Chaldeans answered the king in Aramaic:<note osisRef="Dan.2.4" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.2.4!note.a">The book switches into Aramaic at this point, returning to Hebrew in 8:1.</note> <q type="x-complete">Long live the king! Tell your servants the dream, and we will explain its meaning.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.5" osisID="Dan.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king answered the Chaldeans: <q type="x-start">My decision is final: If you can’t tell me the dream and its meaning, you will be torn limb from limb, and your houses will be turned into trash dumps.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.6" osisID="Dan.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But if you do explain the dream and its meaning, you’ll receive generous gifts and glorious honor from me. So explain to me the dream as well as its meaning.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.7" osisID="Dan.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They answered him again: <q type="x-complete">The king must tell his servants the dream. We will then explain the meaning.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.8" osisID="Dan.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king replied: <q type="x-start">Now I definitely know you are stalling for time, because you see that my decision is final</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.9" osisID="Dan.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">and that if you can’t tell me the dream, your fate is certain. You’ve conspired to make false and lying speeches before me until the situation changes. Tell me the dream now! Then I’ll know you can explain its meaning to me.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.10" osisID="Dan.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Chaldeans answered the king: <q type="x-start">No one on earth can do what the king is asking! No king or ruler, no matter how great, has ever asked such a thing of any dream interpreter, enchanter, or Chaldean.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.11" osisID="Dan.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">What the king is asking is impossible! No one could declare the dream to the king but the gods, who don’t live among mere humans.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.12" osisID="Dan.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At this, the king exploded in a furious rage and ordered that all Babylon’s sages be wiped out. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.13" osisID="Dan.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the command went out: The sages were to be killed. Daniel and his friends too were hunted down; they were to be killed as well.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.2.14-Dan.2.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">God reveals the mystery</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.14" osisID="Dan.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Daniel, with wisdom and sound judgment, responded to Arioch the king’s chief executioner, who had gone out to kill Babylon’s sages. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.15" osisID="Dan.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said to Arioch the king’s royal officer, <q type="x-complete">Why is the king’s command so unreasonable?</q> After Arioch explained the situation to Daniel, </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.16" osisID="Dan.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Daniel went and asked the king to give him some time so he could explain the dream’s meaning to him. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.17" osisID="Dan.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Daniel went to his house and explained the situation to his friends Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.18" osisID="Dan.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so that they would ask the God of heaven for help about this mystery, in hopes that Daniel and his friends wouldn’t die with the rest of Babylon’s sages. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.19" osisID="Dan.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then, in a vision by night, the mystery was revealed to Daniel! Daniel praised the God of heaven:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.2.20" osisID="Dan.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">God’s name be praised</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.2.20" osisID="Dan.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">from age to eternal age!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.2.20" osisID="Dan.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Wisdom and might are his!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.2.21" osisID="Dan.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">God is the one who changes times and eras,</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.2.21" osisID="Dan.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">who dethrones one king, only to establish another,</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.2.21" osisID="Dan.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">who grants wisdom to the wise and knowledge to those with insight.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.2.22" osisID="Dan.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">God is the one who uncovers what lies deeply hidden;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.2.22" osisID="Dan.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">he knows what hides in darkness;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.2.22" osisID="Dan.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">light lives with him!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.2.23" osisID="Dan.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">I acknowledge and praise you, my fathers’ God!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.2.23" osisID="Dan.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">You’ve given me wisdom and might,</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.2.23" osisID="Dan.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">and now you’ve made known to me what we asked of you:</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText4"><verse sID="Dan.2.23" osisID="Dan.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">you’ve made known to us the king’s demand.</verse></l></lg></div><div scope="Dan.2.24-Dan.2.35" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel recounts the dream</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.24" osisID="Dan.2.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Daniel went to Arioch, the man the king had appointed to wipe out Babylon’s sages. Daniel said to him, <q type="x-complete">Don’t wipe out the sages of Babylon! Bring me before the king, and I will explain the dream’s meaning to him.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.25" osisID="Dan.2.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Wasting no time, Arioch brought Daniel before the king, telling him, <q type="x-complete">I have found someone from the Judean exiles who will tell the dream’s meaning to the king.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.26" osisID="Dan.2.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In reply the king said to Daniel (whose name was Belteshazzar), <q type="x-complete">Can you really tell me the dream that I saw, as well as its meaning?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.27" osisID="Dan.2.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Daniel answered the king, “Sages, enchanters, dream interpreters, and diviners can’t explain to the king the mystery he seeks. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.28" osisID="Dan.2.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But there is a God in heaven, a revealer of mysteries, who has shown King Nebuchadnezzar what will happen in the days to come! Now this was your dream—this was the vision in your head as you lay in your bed:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.29" osisID="Dan.2.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“As you lay in bed, Your Majesty, your thoughts turned to what will happen in the future. The revealer of mysteries has revealed to you what will happen. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.30" osisID="Dan.2.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now this mystery was revealed to me, not because I have more wisdom than any other living person but so that the dream’s meaning might be made known to the king, and so that you might know the thoughts of your own mind.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.31" osisID="Dan.2.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“Your Majesty, you were looking, and there, rising before you, was a single, massive statue. This statue was huge, shining with dazzling light, and was awesome to see. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.32" osisID="Dan.2.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The statue’s head was made of pure gold; its chest and arms were made from silver; its abdomen and hips were made of bronze. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.33" osisID="Dan.2.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Its legs were of iron, and its feet were a mixture of iron and clay. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.34" osisID="Dan.2.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You observed this until a stone was cut, but not by hands; and it smashed the statue’s feet of iron and clay and shattered them. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.35" osisID="Dan.2.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then all the parts shattered simultaneously—iron, clay, bronze, silver, and gold. They became like chaff, left on summer threshing floors. The wind lifted them away until no trace of them remained. But the stone that smashed the statue became a mighty mountain, and it filled the entire earth.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.2.36-Dan.2.45" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The dream’s meaning: four future rulers</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.36" osisID="Dan.2.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“This was the dream. Now we will tell the king its meaning: </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.37" osisID="Dan.2.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You, Your Majesty, are the king of kings. The God of heaven has given kingship, power, might, and glory to you! </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.38" osisID="Dan.2.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God has delivered into your care human beings, wild creatures, and birds in the sky—wherever they live—and has made you ruler of all of them. You are the gold head. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.39" osisID="Dan.2.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But in your place, another kingdom will arise, one inferior to yours, and then a third, bronze kingdom will rule over all the earth. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.40" osisID="Dan.2.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then will come a fourth kingdom, mighty like iron. Just as iron shatters and crushes everything; so like an iron that smashes, it will shatter and crush all these others. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.41" osisID="Dan.2.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for the feet and toes that you saw, which were a mixture of potter’s clay and iron, that signifies a divided kingdom; but it will possess some of the unyielding strength of iron. Even so, you saw the iron mixed with earthy clay </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.42" osisID="Dan.2.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so that the toes were made from a mixture of iron and clay. Part of the kingdom will be mighty, but part of it will be fragile. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.43" osisID="Dan.2.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Just as you saw the iron mixed with earthy clay, they will join together by intermarrying, but they will not bond to each other, just as iron does not fuse with clay.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.44" osisID="Dan.2.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">But in the days of those kings, the God of heaven will raise up an everlasting kingdom that will be indestructible. Its rule will never pass to another people. It will shatter other kingdoms. It will put an end to all of them. It will stand firm forever,</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.45" osisID="Dan.2.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">just like you saw when the stone, which was cut from the mountain, but not by hands, shattered the iron, bronze, clay, silver, and gold. A great God has revealed to the king what will happen in the future. The dream is certain. Its meaning can be trusted.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.2.46-Dan.2.49" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Nebuchadnezzar honors Daniel</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.2.46" osisID="Dan.2.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then King Nebuchadnezzar bowed low and honored Daniel. The king ordered that grain and incense offerings be made to Daniel. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.47" osisID="Dan.2.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king declared to Daniel, <q type="x-complete">No doubt about it: your God is God of gods, Lord of kings, and a revealer of mysteries because you were able to reveal this mystery!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.48" osisID="Dan.2.48" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king exalted Daniel and lavished gifts on him, making him ruler over all the province of Babylon and chief minister over all Babylon’s sages. </verse><verse sID="Dan.2.49" osisID="Dan.2.49" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At Daniel’s urging, the king appointed Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego to administer the province of Babylon, but Daniel himself remained at the royal court.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.3" osisID="Dan.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="Dan.3.1-Dan.3.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Gold statue</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.3.1" osisID="Dan.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Nebuchadnezzar made a gold statue. It was ninety feet high and nine feet wide. He set it up in the Dura Valley in the province of Babylon. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.2" osisID="Dan.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Nebuchadnezzar then ordered the chief administrators, ministers, governors, counselors, treasurers, judges, magistrates, and all the provincial officials to assemble and come for the dedication of the statue that he had set up. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.3" osisID="Dan.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the chief administrators, ministers, governors, counselors, treasurers, judges, magistrates, and all the provincial officials assembled for the dedication of the statue that King Nebuchadnezzar had set up. They stood in front of the statue the king had set up. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.4" osisID="Dan.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The herald proclaimed loudly: <q type="x-start">Peoples, nations, and languages! This is what you must do:</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.5" osisID="Dan.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">When you hear the sound of the horn, pipe, zither, lyre, harp, flute, and every kind of instrument, you must bow down and worship the gold statue that King Nebuchadnezzar has set up.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.6" osisID="Dan.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Anyone who will not bow down and worship will be immediately thrown into a furnace of flaming fire.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.7" osisID="Dan.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So because of this order as soon as they heard the sound of the horn, pipe, zither, lyre, harp, flute,<note osisRef="Dan.3.7" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.3.7!note.b">Identification of the instruments is not certain; several of the Aramaic terms are Greek loanwords.</note> and every kind of instrument, all the peoples, nations, and languages bowed down and worshipped the gold statue that King Nebuchadnezzar had set up.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.3.8-Dan.3.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Plot against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.8" osisID="Dan.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that moment some Chaldeans came forward, seizing a chance to attack the Jews. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.9" osisID="Dan.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">They said to King Nebuchadnezzar:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.9" osisID="Dan.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-start">Long live the king!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.10" osisID="Dan.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Your Majesty, you gave a command that everyone who hears the sound of the horn, pipe, zither, lyre, harp, flute, and every kind of instrument should bow down and worship the gold statue.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.11" osisID="Dan.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Anyone who wouldn’t bow and worship would be thrown into a furnace of flaming fire.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.12" osisID="Dan.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now there are some Jews, ones you appointed to administer the province of Babylon—specifically, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego—who have ignored your command. They don’t serve your gods, and they don’t worship the gold statue you’ve set up.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.13" osisID="Dan.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In a violent rage Nebuchadnezzar ordered them to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. They were brought before the king.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.14" osisID="Dan.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar said to them: <q type="x-start">Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego: Is it true that you don’t serve my gods or worship the gold statue I’ve set up?</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.15" osisID="Dan.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">If you are now ready to do so, bow down and worship the gold statue I’ve made when you hear the sound of horn, pipe, zither, lyre, harp, flute, and every kind of instrument. But if you won’t worship it, you will be thrown straight into the furnace of flaming fire. Then what god will rescue you from my power?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.16" osisID="Dan.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego answered King Nebuchadnezzar: <q type="x-start">We don’t need to answer your question.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.17" osisID="Dan.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">If our God—the one we serve—is able to rescue us from the furnace of flaming fire and from your power, Your Majesty, then let him rescue us.<note osisRef="Dan.3.17" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.3.17!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he will deliver us</hi></note></q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.18" osisID="Dan.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But if he doesn’t, know this for certain, Your Majesty: we will never serve your gods or worship the gold statue you’ve set up.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.3.19-Dan.3.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Inside the furnace</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.19" osisID="Dan.3.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar was filled with rage, and his face twisted beyond recognition because of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. In response he commanded that the furnace be heated to seven times its normal heat. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.20" osisID="Dan.3.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He told some of the strongest men in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego and throw them into the furnace of flaming fire. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.21" osisID="Dan.3.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego were bound, still dressed in all their clothes, and thrown into the furnace of flaming fire. (</verse><verse sID="Dan.3.22" osisID="Dan.3.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now the king’s command had been rash, and the furnace was heated to such an extreme that the fire’s flame killed the very men who carried Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego to it.) </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.23" osisID="Dan.3.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, fell, bound, into the furnace of flaming fire.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.24" osisID="Dan.3.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Then King Nebuchadnezzar jumped up in shock and said to his associates, <q type="x-complete">Didn’t we throw three men, bound, into the fire?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.24" osisID="Dan.3.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">They answered the king, <q type="x-complete">Certainly, Your Majesty.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.25" osisID="Dan.3.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He replied, <q type="x-complete">Look! I see four men, unbound, walking around inside the fire, and they aren’t hurt! And the fourth one looks like one of the gods.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.26" osisID="Dan.3.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar went near the opening of the furnace of flaming fire and said, <q type="x-complete">Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, servants of the Most High God, come out! Come here!</q> Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego came out of the fire. </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.27" osisID="Dan.3.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The chief administrators, ministers, governors, and the king’s associates crowded around to look at them. The fire hadn’t done anything to them: their hair wasn’t singed; their garments looked the same as before; they didn’t even smell like fire!</verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.3.28-Dan.3.30" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Nebuchadnezzar praises God</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.28" osisID="Dan.3.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar declared: <q type="x-start">May the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego be praised! He sent his messenger<note osisRef="Dan.3.28" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.3.28!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">angel</hi></note> to rescue his servants who trusted him. They ignored the king’s order, sacrificing their bodies, because they wouldn’t serve or worship any god but their God.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.3.29" osisID="Dan.3.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">I now issue a decree to every people, nation, and language: whoever speaks disrespectfully about Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego’s God will be torn limb from limb and their house made a trash heap, because there is no other god who can rescue like this.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.3.30" osisID="Dan.3.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the king made Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego prosperous in the province of Babylon.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.4" osisID="Dan.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="Dan.4.1-Dan.4.8" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Nebuchadnezzar’s testimony</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.4.1" osisID="Dan.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="Dan.4.1" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.4.1!note.e">3:31 in Aram</note> King Nebuchadnezzar’s message to all the peoples, nations, and languages inhabiting the entire earth: “I wish you much peace. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.2" osisID="Dan.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m delighted to share the signs and miracles that the Most High God has worked in my life.</verse> </p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.3" osisID="Dan.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">His signs are superb!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.3" osisID="Dan.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">His miracles so powerful!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.3" osisID="Dan.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">His kingdom is everlasting.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.3" osisID="Dan.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">His rule is for all time.</verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.4" osisID="Dan.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><note osisRef="Dan.4.4" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.4.4!note.f">4:1 in Aram</note> “While I, Nebuchadnezzar, was safe in my house, content in my palace, </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.5" osisID="Dan.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I had a terrifying dream. My thoughts while I was lying in bed and the vision in my mind overwhelmed me. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.6" osisID="Dan.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I ordered all Babylon’s sages to come before me, so they might tell me the dream’s meaning. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.7" osisID="Dan.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the dream interpreters, enchanters, Chaldeans, and diviners came. I told them the dream, but they couldn’t interpret it for me. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.8" osisID="Dan.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Daniel, who is called Belteshazzar after the name of my god, was the last to come before me. In him is the breath<note osisRef="Dan.4.8" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.4.8!note.g">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">spirit</hi>; also in 4:9, 18</note> of the holy gods! I told Daniel the dream:</verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.4.9-Dan.4.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Nebuchadnezzar’s dream</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.9" osisID="Dan.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“Belteshazzar, chief of the dream interpreters, I know the breath of the holy gods is in you, and no mystery is too difficult for you. Tell me the meaning of the visions I had in my dream. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.10" osisID="Dan.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">In my mind, as I lay in bed, I saw a vision:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.10" osisID="Dan.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">At the center of the earth was a towering tree.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.11" osisID="Dan.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The tree grew in size and strength;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.11" osisID="Dan.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">it was as high as the sky;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.11" osisID="Dan.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">it could be seen from every corner of the earth.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.12" osisID="Dan.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Its leaves were beautiful, its fruit abundant;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.12" osisID="Dan.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">it had enough food for everyone.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.12" osisID="Dan.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Wild animals took shade under it;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.12" osisID="Dan.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">birds nested in its branches.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.12" osisID="Dan.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">All living things lived off that tree.</verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.13" osisID="Dan.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“In my mind, as I lay in bed, I saw another vision: A holy watcher came down from heaven. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.14" osisID="Dan.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He proclaimed loudly:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.14" osisID="Dan.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">‘Cut down the tree and shear off its branches!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.14" osisID="Dan.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Strip its leaves and scatter its fruit!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.14" osisID="Dan.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">The creatures should flee from its shelter;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.14" osisID="Dan.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">the birds should take flight from its branches.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.15" osisID="Dan.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">But leave its deepest root in the earth,</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.15" osisID="Dan.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">bound with iron and bronze in the field grass.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.15" osisID="Dan.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Dew from heaven is to wash it,</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.15" osisID="Dan.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and it must live with the animals in the earth’s vegetation.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.16" osisID="Dan.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Its<note osisRef="Dan.4.16" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.4.16!note.h">Throughout 4:15–16 and later in this chap, <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">it </hi>and <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">its </hi>could also be translated <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">he </hi>and <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">his</hi>.</note> human mind is to be changed:</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.16" osisID="Dan.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">it will be given the mind of an animal.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.16" osisID="Dan.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Seven periods of time will pass over it.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.17" osisID="Dan.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">This sentence is by the watchers’ decree;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.17" osisID="Dan.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">this decision is the holy ones’ word</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.17" osisID="Dan.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">so that all who live might know</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.4.17" osisID="Dan.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">that the Most High dominates human kingship.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.4.17" osisID="Dan.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">The Most High gives kingship to anyone he wants</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.4.17" osisID="Dan.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and sets over it the lowest of people.’</verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.18" osisID="Dan.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">This is the dream that I, King Nebuchadnezzar, had. So now Belteshazzar, tell me the meaning because all the sages in my kingdom were unable to interpret it for me. But you are able to do it because the breath of the holy gods is in you.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.4.19-Dan.4.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel interprets the visions</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.19" osisID="Dan.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Daniel, who was called Belteshazzar, was shocked for a bit. What he thought about frightened him.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.19" osisID="Dan.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">The king declared, <q type="x-complete">Don’t let the dream and its meaning scare you, Belteshazzar.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.19" osisID="Dan.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Then Belteshazzar answered, “Sir, I wish the dream to be for those who hate you and its meaning to be for your enemies! </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.20" osisID="Dan.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The tree you saw that grew in size and strength, that was as high as the sky, that could be seen from every corner of the earth, </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.21" osisID="Dan.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">with its beautiful leaves and its abundant fruit, and that had enough food for everyone, with wild animals living under it and birds nesting in its branches—</verse><verse sID="Dan.4.22" osisID="Dan.4.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Your Majesty, that tree is you! You have grown large and become powerful. Your greatness is as high as the sky; your rule extends to the edge of the earth!</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.23" osisID="Dan.4.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">Your Majesty, the holy watcher you saw coming down from heaven, who said, ‘Cut down the tree and destroy it, but leave its deepest root in the earth, bound with iron and bronze in the field grass, dew from heaven is to wash it, and it must live with the wild animals until seven periods of time pass over it’—</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.24" osisID="Dan.4.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Your Majesty, this is the dream’s meaning: It is the sentence of the Most High, delivered to my master the king.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.25" osisID="Dan.4.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">You will be driven away from other humans and will live with the wild animals. You will eat grass like cattle and will be washed by dew from heaven. Seven periods of time will pass over you, until you acknowledge that the Most High dominates human kingship, giving it to anyone he wants.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.26" osisID="Dan.4.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">And when he said to leave the deepest root of the tree—that means your kingship will again be yours, once you acknowledge that heaven rules all.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.27" osisID="Dan.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Therefore, Your Majesty, please accept my advice: remove your sins by doing what is right; remove your wrongdoing by showing mercy to the poor. Then your safety will be long lasting.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.4.28-Dan.4.33" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Visions come true</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.28" osisID="Dan.4.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All this happened to King Nebuchadnezzar. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.29" osisID="Dan.4.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Twelve months later, he was walking on the roof of the royal palace in Babylon. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.30" osisID="Dan.4.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king declared, <q type="x-complete">Isn’t this Babylon, the magnificent city that I built as the royal house by my own mighty strength and for my own majestic glory?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.31" osisID="Dan.4.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These words hadn’t even left the king’s mouth when a voice came from heaven: <q type="x-start">You, King Nebuchadnezzar, are now informed: Kingship is taken away from you.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.32" osisID="Dan.4.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">You will be driven away from other humans and will live with the wild animals. You will eat grass like cattle, and seven periods of time will pass over you until you acknowledge that the Most High dominates human kingship, giving it to anyone he wants.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.33" osisID="Dan.4.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nebuchadnezzar’s sentence was immediately carried out. He was driven away from other humans and ate grass like cattle. Dew from heaven washed his body until he grew hair like eagles’ feathers and claws like a bird.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.4.34-Dan.4.37" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Nebuchadnezzar is restored</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.34" osisID="Dan.4.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“At the end of that time, I, Nebuchadnezzar, raised my eyes to heaven. My reason returned to me, and I praised the Most High. I worshipped and glorified the one who lives forever because his rule is everlasting; his kingdom is for all time. </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.35" osisID="Dan.4.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All of earth’s inhabitants are nothing in comparison. The Most High does whatever he wants with the heaven’s forces and with earth’s inhabitants. No one can contain his power or say to him, ‘What do you think you are doing?’ </verse><verse sID="Dan.4.36" osisID="Dan.4.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So at that moment my reason returned to me. My honor and splendor came back to me for the glory of my kingdom. My associates and my princes wanted to be with me again. Not only was I reinstated over my kingdom, I received more power than ever before.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.4.37" osisID="Dan.4.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, worship, magnify, and glorify the king of heaven. All his works are truth, all his paths are justice, and he is able to humble all who walk in pride.</q></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.5" osisID="Dan.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="Dan.5.1-Dan.5.4" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Belshazzar’s party</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.5.1" osisID="Dan.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">King Belshazzar threw a huge party for a thousand of his princes, and he drank a lot of wine in front of them. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.2" osisID="Dan.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While he was under the wine’s influence, Belshazzar commanded that the gold and silver equipment that his father Nebuchadnezzar had taken from Jerusalem’s temple be brought to the party so that the king, his princes, his consorts, and his secondary wives could drink wine out of them. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.3" osisID="Dan.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the gold<note osisRef="Dan.5.3" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.3!note.i">Vulg, Theodotion add <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">silver</hi>.</note> equipment that had been carried out of the temple, God’s house in Jerusalem, was brought in; and the king, his princes, his consorts, and his secondary wives drank out of it. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.4" osisID="Dan.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They drank a lot of wine; and they praised the gods of gold, silver, bronze, iron, wood, and stone.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.5.5-Dan.5.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Writing on the wall</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.5" osisID="Dan.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Right then the fingers of a human hand appeared and wrote on the plaster of the king’s palace wall in the light of the lamp. The king saw the hand that wrote. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.6" osisID="Dan.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king’s mood changed immediately, and he was deeply disturbed. He felt weak, and his knees were shaking. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.7" osisID="Dan.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The king yelled, calling for the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the diviners.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.7" osisID="Dan.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king told these sages of Babylon: <q type="x-complete">Anyone who can read this writing and tell me its meaning will wear royal robes, will have a gold chain around his neck, and will rule the kingdom as third in command.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.8" osisID="Dan.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then all the king’s sages arrived, but they couldn’t read the writing or interpret it for the king. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.9" osisID="Dan.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that point King Belshazzar was really frightened. All the color drained from his face, and his princes were also very worried.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.10" osisID="Dan.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Upon hearing the commotion coming from the king and his princes, the queen entered the banqueting hall and declared, <q type="x-start">Long live the king! Don’t be so disturbed. Don’t be so frightened.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.11" osisID="Dan.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">There is a man in your kingdom who has the breath<note osisRef="Dan.5.11" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.11!note.j">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">spirit</hi>; also in 5:14</note> of holy gods in him! When your father was alive, this man was shown to possess illumination, insight, and wisdom like the very wisdom of the gods.<note osisRef="Dan.5.11" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.11!note.k">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">wisdom of God</hi></note> Your father King Nebuchadnezzar appointed this man as chief over the dream interpreters, enchanters, Chaldeans, and diviners. Yes, your father did this</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.12" osisID="Dan.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">because this man—Daniel, the one the king named Belteshazzar—possesses an extraordinary spirit, knowledge, and insight into the meaning of dreams. He can explain ambiguities and resolve mysteries. Now in light of all that, summon Daniel! He will explain the meaning of this thing.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.13" osisID="Dan.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So Daniel was brought before the king. The king said to him, <q type="x-start">So you are Daniel, the Daniel from the exiles that my father the king brought from Judah?</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.14" osisID="Dan.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">I have heard that the breath of the gods is in you and that you possess illumination, insight, and extraordinary wisdom.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.15" osisID="Dan.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Now, the sages and the dream interpreters were brought before me to read this writing and interpret it for me, but they couldn’t explain its meaning.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.16" osisID="Dan.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But I’ve heard that you can explain meanings and solve mysteries. So if you can read this writing and interpret it for me, you will wear royal robes, have a gold chain around your neck, and will rule the kingdom as third in command.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.5.17-Dan.5.30" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel interprets the writing</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.17" osisID="Dan.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Daniel answered the king: “Keep your gifts. Give the rewards to someone else. But I will still read the writing to the king and interpret it for him. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.18" osisID="Dan.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen, Your Majesty: The Most High God gave kingship, power, glory, and majesty to your father Nebuchadnezzar. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.19" osisID="Dan.5.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of the power God gave Nebuchadnezzar, all peoples, nations, and languages were terrified of him. He did whatever he wanted, whenever he wanted: killing or sparing, exalting or humbling. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.20" osisID="Dan.5.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when he became arrogant, acting in stubborn pride, he was pulled off his royal throne and the glory was taken from him. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.21" osisID="Dan.5.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He was driven away from other humans, and his mind became like an animal’s. He lived with wild donkeys, he ate grass like cattle, and dew from heaven washed his body until he realized that the Most High God dominates human kingship and sets over it anyone he wants.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.22" osisID="Dan.5.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“But you who are his son, Belshazzar, you haven’t submitted, even though you’ve known all this. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.23" osisID="Dan.5.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, you’ve set yourself up against the Lord of heaven! The equipment of God’s house was brought to you; and you, your princes, your consorts, and your secondary wives drank wine out of it, all the while praising the gods of silver, gold, bronze, iron, wood, and stone—gods who can’t see, hear, or know anything. But you didn’t glorify the true God who holds your very breath in his hand and who owns every road you take.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.24" osisID="Dan.5.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“That’s why this hand was sent from God and why this message was written down. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.25" osisID="Dan.5.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">This is what was written down:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.25" osisID="Dan.5.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><hi type="x-CEBInscription">mene, mene, tekel, </hi>and <hi type="x-CEBInscription">parsin</hi>.<note osisRef="Dan.5.25" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.25!note.l">Aram <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Upharsin</hi></note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.26" osisID="Dan.5.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">This is the meaning of the word <hi type="x-CEBInscription">mene</hi>: God has numbered<note osisRef="Dan.5.26" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.26!note.m">Aram <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">menah</hi>, which is a wordplay with <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Mene</hi></note> the days of your rule. It’s over!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.27" osisID="Dan.5.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation"><hi type="x-CEBInscription">tekel </hi>means that you’ve been weighed<note osisRef="Dan.5.27" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.27!note.n">Aram <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">teqal</hi>, which is a wordplay with <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Tekel</hi></note> on the scales, and you don’t measure up.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.28" osisID="Dan.5.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end"><hi type="x-CEBInscription">peres</hi><note osisRef="Dan.5.28" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.28!note.o">The singular form of the plural <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Parsin </hi>in 5:25</note> means your kingship is divided<note osisRef="Dan.5.28" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.28!note.p">Aram <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">peras</hi>, which is a wordplay with <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Parsin</hi></note> and given to the Medes and the Persians.</q><note osisRef="Dan.5.28" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.5.28!note.q">Aram <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Paras</hi>, another wordplay with <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Parsin</hi></note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.29" osisID="Dan.5.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Belshazzar commanded that Daniel be dressed in a purple robe, have a gold chain around his neck, and be officially appointed as third in command in the kingdom.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.5.30" osisID="Dan.5.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That very same night, Belshazzar the Chaldean king was killed. </verse><verse sID="Dan.5.31" osisID="Dan.5.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Darius the Mede received the kingdom at the age of 62.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.6" osisID="Dan.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="Dan.6.1-Dan.6.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Plot against Daniel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.6.1" osisID="Dan.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Darius decided to appoint one hundred twenty chief administrators throughout the kingdom, </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.2" osisID="Dan.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and to set over them three main officers to whom they would report so that the king wouldn’t have to be bothered with too much.<note osisRef="Dan.6.2" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.6.2!note.r">Aram uncertain</note> One of these main officers was Daniel. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.3" osisID="Dan.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of his extraordinary spirit, Daniel soon surpassed the other officers and the chief administrators—so much so that the king had plans to set him over the entire kingdom. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.4" osisID="Dan.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As a result, the other officers and the chief administrators tried to find some problem with Daniel’s work for the kingdom. But they couldn’t find any problem or corruption at all because Daniel was trustworthy. He wasn’t guilty of any negligence or corruption.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.5" osisID="Dan.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So these men said, <q type="x-complete">We won’t find any fault in Daniel, unless we can find something to use against him from his religious practice.</q><note osisRef="Dan.6.5" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.6.5!note.s">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">in the Instruction of his God</hi></note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.6" osisID="Dan.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So these officers and chief administrators ganged together and went to the king. They said to him, <q type="x-start">Long live King Darius!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.7" osisID="Dan.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">All the officers of the kingdom, the ministers, the chief administrators, the royal associates, and the governors advise the king to issue an edict and enforce a law, that for thirty days anyone who says prayers to any god or human being except you, Your Majesty, will be thrown into a pit of lions.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.8" osisID="Dan.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now, Your Majesty, issue the law and sign the document so that it cannot be changed, as per the law of Media and Persia, which cannot be annulled.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.9" osisID="Dan.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, King Darius signed the document containing the law.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.6.10-Dan.6.15" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel prays</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.10" osisID="Dan.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Daniel learned that the document had been signed, he went to his house. Now his upper room had open windows that faced Jerusalem. Daniel knelt down, prayed, and praised his God three times that day, just like he always did. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.11" osisID="Dan.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Just then these men, all ganged together, came upon Daniel praying and seeking mercy from his God. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.12" osisID="Dan.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">They then went and talked to the king about the law: <q type="x-complete">Your Majesty! Didn’t you sign a law, that for thirty days any person who prays to any god or human being besides you, Your Majesty, would be thrown into a pit of lions?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.12" osisID="Dan.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king replied, <q type="x-complete">The decision is absolutely firm in accordance with the law of Media and Persia, which cannot be annulled.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.13" osisID="Dan.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So they said to the king, <q type="x-complete">One of the Judean exiles, Daniel, has ignored you, Your Majesty, as well as the law you signed. He says his prayers three times a day!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.14" osisID="Dan.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the king heard this report, he was very unhappy. He decided to rescue Daniel and did everything he could do to save Daniel before the sun went down. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.15" osisID="Dan.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But these men, all ganged together, came and said to the king, <q type="x-complete">You must realize, Your Majesty, that the law of Media and Persia, including every law and edict the king has issued, cannot be changed.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.6.16-Dan.6.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel in the lions’ pit</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.16" osisID="Dan.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So the king gave the order, and they brought Daniel and hurled him into the pit of lions.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.16" osisID="Dan.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The king said to Daniel: <q type="x-complete">Your God—the one you serve so consistently—will rescue you.</q><note osisRef="Dan.6.16" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.6.16!note.t">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">May your God—the one you serve so consistently—rescue you.</hi></note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.17" osisID="Dan.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A single stone was brought and placed over the entrance to the pit. The king sealed it with his own ring and with those of his princes so that Daniel’s situation couldn’t be changed. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.18" osisID="Dan.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king then went home to his palace and fasted through the night. No pleasures<note osisRef="Dan.6.18" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.6.18!note.u">Aram uncertain</note> were brought to him, and he couldn’t sleep. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.19" osisID="Dan.6.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At dawn, at the first sign of light, the king rose and rushed to the lions’ pit.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.20" osisID="Dan.6.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As he approached it, he called out to Daniel, worried: <q type="x-complete">Daniel, servant of the living God! Was your God—the one you serve so consistently—able to rescue you from the lions?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.21" osisID="Dan.6.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then Daniel answered the king: <q type="x-start">Long live the king!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.22" osisID="Dan.6.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">My God sent his messenger, who shut the lions’ mouths. They haven’t touched me because I was judged innocent before my God. I haven’t done anything wrong to you either, Your Majesty.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.23" osisID="Dan.6.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king was thrilled. He commanded that Daniel be brought up out of the pit, and Daniel was lifted out. Not a scratch was found on him, because he trusted in his God. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.24" osisID="Dan.6.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The king then ordered that the men who had accused Daniel be brought and thrown into the lions’ pit—including their wives and children. They hadn’t even reached the bottom of the pit before the lions overpowered them, crushing all their bones.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.6.25-Dan.6.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">New decree</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.25" osisID="Dan.6.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Then King Darius wrote the following decree:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffset"><verse sID="Dan.6.25" osisID="Dan.6.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">To all the peoples, nations, and languages inhabiting the entire earth: I wish you much peace. </verse><verse sID="Dan.6.26" osisID="Dan.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">I now issue this command: In every region of my kingdom, all people must fear and revere Daniel’s God because:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.6.26" osisID="Dan.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">He is the living God.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.6.26" osisID="Dan.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">God stands firm forever.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.6.26" osisID="Dan.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">His kingship is indestructible.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.6.26" osisID="Dan.6.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">God’s rule will last until the end of time.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.6.27" osisID="Dan.6.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He is rescuer and savior;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.6.27" osisID="Dan.6.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">God performs signs and miracles in heaven and on earth.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.6.27" osisID="Dan.6.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Here’s the proof:</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.6.27" osisID="Dan.6.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">He rescued Daniel from the lions’ power.</verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.6.28" osisID="Dan.6.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And so Daniel was made prosperous during the rule of Darius and during the rule of Cyrus the Persian.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.7" osisID="Dan.7" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="7"><div scope="Dan.7.1-Dan.7.8" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel’s vision: four beasts</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.7.1" osisID="Dan.7.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the first year of Babylon’s King Belshazzar, Daniel had a dream—a vision in his head as he lay on his bed. He wrote the dream down. Here is the beginning of the account:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.2" osisID="Dan.7.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I am Daniel. In the vision I had during the night I saw the four winds of heaven churning the great sea. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.3" osisID="Dan.7.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Four giant beasts emerged from the sea, each different from the others. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.4" osisID="Dan.7.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The first was like a lion with eagle’s wings. I observed it until its wings were pulled off, and it was lifted up from the ground. It was then set on two feet, like a human being, and it received a human mind. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.5" osisID="Dan.7.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then I saw another beast, a second one, like a bear. It was raised on one side. It had three ribs in its mouth between its teeth. It was told: <q type="x-complete">Get up! Devour much flesh!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.6" osisID="Dan.7.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I kept watching, and suddenly there was another beast, this one like a leopard. On its back it had four wings like bird wings. This beast had four heads. Authority was given to it.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.7" osisID="Dan.7.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After this, as I continued to watch this night vision, I saw a fourth beast, terrifying and hideous, with extraordinary power and with massive iron teeth. As it ate and crushed, its feet smashed whatever was left over. It was different from all the other beasts before it, and it had ten horns. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.8" osisID="Dan.7.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I was staring at the horns when, suddenly, another small horn came up between them. Three of the earlier horns were ripped out to make room for it. On this new horn were eyes like human eyes and a mouth that bragged and bragged.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.7.9-Dan.7.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Throne of fire and the human figure</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">As I was watching,</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">thrones were raised up.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">The ancient one took his seat.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">His clothes were white like snow;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">his hair was like a lamb’s wool.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">His throne was made of flame;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.9" osisID="Dan.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">its wheels were blazing fire.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.10" osisID="Dan.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">A river of fire flowed out from his presence;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.10" osisID="Dan.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">thousands upon thousands served him;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.10" osisID="Dan.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">ten thousand times ten thousand stood ready to serve him!</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.10" osisID="Dan.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">The court sat in session; the scrolls were opened.</verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.11" osisID="Dan.7.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I kept watching. I watched from the moment the horn started bragging until the beast was killed and its body was destroyed, handed over to be burned with fire. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.12" osisID="Dan.7.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the authority of the remaining beasts was brought to an end, but they were given an extension among the living for a set time and season.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.13" osisID="Dan.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">As I continued to watch this night vision of mine, I suddenly saw</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.13" osisID="Dan.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">one like a human being<note osisRef="Dan.7.13" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.7.13!note.v">Aram <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">kebar enash </hi>(<hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">like a son of man</hi>) is an idiom that means <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">like a human being; </hi>cf also 8:17; 10:16, 18 for Heb approximations.</note></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.13" osisID="Dan.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">coming with the heavenly clouds.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.13" osisID="Dan.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">He came to the ancient one</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.13" osisID="Dan.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and was presented before him.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.14" osisID="Dan.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Rule, glory, and kingship were given to him;</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.14" osisID="Dan.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">all peoples, nations, and languages will serve him.</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.14" osisID="Dan.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">His rule is an everlasting one—</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.14" osisID="Dan.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">it will never pass away!—</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.14" osisID="Dan.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">his kingship is indestructible.</verse></l></lg></div><div scope="Dan.7.15-Dan.7.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Beasts interpreted</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.15" osisID="Dan.7.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now this caused me, Daniel, to worry.<note osisRef="Dan.7.15" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.7.15!note.w">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">my spirit was distressed in its sheath</hi>; Aram uncertain</note> My visions disturbed me greatly. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.16" osisID="Dan.7.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">So I went to one of the servants who was standing ready nearby. I asked him for the truth about all this.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.16" osisID="Dan.7.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">He spoke to me and explained to me the meaning of these things. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.17" osisID="Dan.7.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">These four giant beasts are four kings that will rise up from the earth,</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.18" osisID="Dan.7.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">but the holy ones of the Most High will receive the kingship. They will hold the kingship securely forever and always.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.19" osisID="Dan.7.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Next I wanted greater clarity about the fourth beast, the one that was different from all the others and utterly terrifying with its iron teeth and bronze claws. As it ate and crushed, its feet smashed whatever was left over. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.20" osisID="Dan.7.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I wanted greater clarity about the ten horns on its head, and the other horn that came up, along with the three that fell out to make room for it—but especially about the horn that had eyes and a mouth that bragged, and that seemed more important than the others. </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.21" osisID="Dan.7.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As I watched, this same horn waged war against the holy ones and defeated them, </verse><verse sID="Dan.7.22" osisID="Dan.7.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">until the Ancient One came. Then judgment was given in favor of the holy ones of the Most High. The set time arrived, and the holy ones held the kingship securely.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.23" osisID="Dan.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">This is what he said:</verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.23" osisID="Dan.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-start">The fourth beast means</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.23" osisID="Dan.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">that there will be a fourth kingship on the earth.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.23" osisID="Dan.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">It will be different from all the other kingships.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.23" osisID="Dan.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">It will devour the entire earth, trample it, crush it.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.24" osisID="Dan.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">The ten horns mean</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.24" osisID="Dan.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">that from this kingship will rise ten kings,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.24" osisID="Dan.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">and after them will rise yet another.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.24" osisID="Dan.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">He will be different from the previous ones.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.24" osisID="Dan.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">He will defeat three kings.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">He will say things against the Most High</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">and will exhaust the holy ones of the Most High.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">He will try to change times set by law.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">And for a period of time,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">periods of time,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">and half a period of time,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.25" osisID="Dan.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">they will be delivered into his power.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.26" osisID="Dan.7.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">Then the court will sit in session.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.26" osisID="Dan.7.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">His rule will be taken away—</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.26" osisID="Dan.7.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">ruined and wiped out for all time.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.27" osisID="Dan.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">The kingship, authority, and power</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.7.27" osisID="Dan.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">of all kingdoms under heaven</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.27" osisID="Dan.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">will be given to the people,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.7.27" osisID="Dan.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">the holy ones of the Most High.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.7.27" osisID="Dan.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-end">Their kingship is an everlasting one; every authority will serve them and obey.</q></verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.28" osisID="Dan.7.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The account ends here.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.7.28" osisID="Dan.7.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Now as for how I, Daniel, felt about this: My thoughts disturbed me greatly. My mood darkened considerably, and I kept thinking about this matter.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.8" osisID="Dan.8" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="8"><div scope="Dan.8.1-Dan.8.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Vision of a ram and a goat</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.8.1" osisID="Dan.8.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the third year of King Belshazzar’s rule, a vision came to me, Daniel, some time after the earlier vision I had. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.2" osisID="Dan.8.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I saw this vision, and as I experienced it I was in the walled city of Susa in the province of Elam,<note osisRef="Dan.8.2" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.8.2!note.x">Some LXX sources; MT repeats <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">I had this vision before I was by the Ulai canal.</hi></note> by the Ulai canal. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.3" osisID="Dan.8.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When I lifted my eyes, I suddenly saw a ram with two horns standing in front of the canal. Both horns were high, but one was higher than the other. The higher one came up after the other one. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.4" osisID="Dan.8.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I saw the ram goring west, north, and south. No animal could resist the ram, and no one could stop it, rescuing others from its power. The ram did whatever it pleased. It became powerful.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.5" osisID="Dan.8.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I was trying to understand this when suddenly a he-goat came from the west, crossing the entire earth but not touching the ground. Between this goat’s eyes was a horn that was a sight to see. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.6" osisID="Dan.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The he-goat came to the ram that had two horns, the one I’d seen standing in front of the canal. The he-goat charged the ram in powerful anger. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.7" osisID="Dan.8.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I saw the he-goat approach the ram. It was enraged at the ram and attacked it, shattering the ram’s two horns. The ram couldn’t resist the he-goat. The he-goat threw the ram on the ground and trampled on it. No one could rescue the ram from the he-goat’s power.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.8" osisID="Dan.8.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The he-goat became even greater, but at the height of its power, its large horn snapped. In its place, four horns, each a sight to see, came up toward the four winds of heaven. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.9" osisID="Dan.8.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A single, very small horn came out of one of the four horns. It grew bigger and bigger, stretching toward the south, the east, and the beautiful country. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.10" osisID="Dan.8.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It grew as high as the heavenly forces, until it finally threw some of them and some of the stars down to the earth. Then it trampled on them. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.11" osisID="Dan.8.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It grew as high as the very leader of those forces, taking the daily sacrifice away from him<note osisRef="Dan.8.11" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.8.11!note.y">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the daily sacrifice was taken away from him.</hi></note> and overturning his holy place. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.12" osisID="Dan.8.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In an act of rebellion, another force will take control of the daily sacrifice. It will throw truth to the ground and will succeed in everything it does.<note osisRef="Dan.8.12" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.8.12!note.z">Heb uncertain</note></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.8.13-Dan.8.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">How long?</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.13" osisID="Dan.8.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I then heard a certain holy one speaking. A second holy one said to the first one: <q type="x-complete">How long will this vision last—the one concerning the daily sacrifice, the desolating rebellion, and the handing over of the sanctuary and its forces to be trampled?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.14" osisID="Dan.8.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said to me, <q type="x-complete">For two thousand three hundred evenings and mornings. Then the sanctuary will be restored.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.8.15-Dan.8.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Vision interpreted</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.15" osisID="Dan.8.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now I, Daniel, needed help understanding the vision I saw. Suddenly standing in front of me was someone who looked like a man. </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.16" osisID="Dan.8.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I then heard a human voice coming out of the center of the Ulai canal. It called out: <q type="x-complete">Gabriel, help this person understand what he has seen.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.17" osisID="Dan.8.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Gabriel approached me, and I was terrified when he came. I fell with my face to the ground. Gabriel said to me, <q type="x-complete">Know this, human one: the vision is for the end time.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.18" osisID="Dan.8.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As soon as he said this to me, I fell into a trance. My face was still on the ground. Then Gabriel touched me and set me up on my feet.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.19" osisID="Dan.8.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said, <q type="x-start">Now, I am going to tell you what will happen during the time of doom that is coming, because at the appointed time there will be an end.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.20" osisID="Dan.8.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The two-horned ram you saw represents the kings of Media and Persia.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.21" osisID="Dan.8.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The long-haired he-goat is the king of Greece, and the big horn between its eyes is the first king.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.8.22" osisID="Dan.8.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">The horn that snapped so that four came up in its place means that four kingdoms will come from one nation, but these four won’t have the strength of the first one.</q></verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.8.23" osisID="Dan.8.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">When their kingship nears its end</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.8.23" osisID="Dan.8.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">and their sins<note osisRef="Dan.8.23" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.8.23!note.a">LXX; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">rebels</hi></note> are almost complete,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.8.23" osisID="Dan.8.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">a king will step forward.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.8.23" osisID="Dan.8.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">He will be stern and a master of deception.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.8.24" osisID="Dan.8.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">At the height of his power,<note osisRef="Dan.8.24" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.8.24!note.b">LXX sources; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">His power will grow strong, but not by his own power, </hi>perhaps influenced by 8:22.</note></q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.8.24" osisID="Dan.8.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">he will wreak unbelievable destructions.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.8.24" osisID="Dan.8.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">He will succeed in all he does.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.8.24" osisID="Dan.8.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">He will destroy both the mighty</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.8.24" osisID="Dan.8.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">and the people of the holy ones.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">Along with his cunning,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">he will succeed by using deceit.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">In his own mind, he will be great.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">In a time of peace,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">he will bring destruction on many,</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">opposing even the supreme leader.</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><q type="x-continuation">But he will be broken—</q></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="Dan.8.25" osisID="Dan.8.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">and not by a human hand.</q></verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBNoIndent"><verse sID="Dan.8.26" osisID="Dan.8.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now this vision of evening and morning, which has been announced, is true. But you must seal it up, because it is for days far in the future.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.8.27" osisID="Dan.8.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then I, Daniel, was overwhelmed and felt sick for days. When I finally got up and went about the king’s business, I remained troubled by the vision and couldn’t understand it.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.9" osisID="Dan.9" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="9"><div scope="Dan.9.1-Dan.9.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Daniel’s prayer</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Dan.9.1" osisID="Dan.9.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the first year of Darius’ rule—Darius, who was Ahasuerus’ son, a Median by birth and who ruled the Chaldean kingdom—</verse><verse sID="Dan.9.2" osisID="Dan.9.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I, Daniel, pondered the scrolls, specifically the number of years that it would take to complete Jerusalem’s desolation according to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>’s word to the prophet Jeremiah. It was seventy years. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.3" osisID="Dan.9.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I then turned my face to my Lord God, asking for an answer with prayer and pleading, and with fasting, mourning clothes, and ashes. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.4" osisID="Dan.9.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">As I prayed to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God, I made this confession:</verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="Dan.9.4" osisID="Dan.9.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Please, my Lord—you are the great and awesome God, the one who keeps the covenant, and truly faithful to all who love him and keep his commands: </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.5" osisID="Dan.9.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We have sinned and done wrong. We have brought guilt on ourselves and rebelled, ignoring your commands and your laws. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.6" osisID="Dan.9.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We haven’t listened to your servants, the prophets, who spoke in your name to our kings, our leaders, our parents, and to all the land’s people. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.7" osisID="Dan.9.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Righteousness belongs to you, my Lord! But we are ashamed this day—we, the people of Judah, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, all Israel whether near or far, in whatever country where you’ve driven them because of their unfaithfulness when they broke faith with you. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.8" osisID="Dan.9.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName>, we are ashamed—we, our kings, our leaders, and our parents who sinned against you. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.9" osisID="Dan.9.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Compassion and deep forgiveness belong to my Lord, our God, because we rebelled against him. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.10" osisID="Dan.9.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We didn’t listen to the voice of the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God by following the teachings he gave us through his servants, the prophets. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.11" osisID="Dan.9.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All Israel broke your Instruction and turned away, ignoring your voice. Then the curse that was sworn long ago—the one written in the Instruction from Moses, God’s servant—swept over us because we sinned against God. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.12" osisID="Dan.9.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God confirmed the words he spoke against us and against our rulers, bringing great trouble on us. What happened in Jerusalem hasn’t happened anywhere else in the entire world! </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.13" osisID="Dan.9.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All this trouble came upon us, exactly as it was written in the Instruction of Moses, but we didn’t try to reconcile with the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God by turning from our wrongdoing or by finding wisdom in your faithfulness. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.14" osisID="Dan.9.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> oversaw the great trouble and brought it on us, because the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> our God has been right in every move he’s made, but we haven’t listened to his voice.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffset"><verse sID="Dan.9.15" osisID="Dan.9.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">But now, my Lord, our God—you who brought your people out of Egypt with a strong hand, making a name for yourself even to this day: We have sinned and done the wrong thing.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.16" osisID="Dan.9.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My Lord, please! In line with your many righteous acts, please turn your raging anger from Jerusalem, which is your city, your own holy mountain. Because of our sins and the wrongdoing of our parents, both Jerusalem and your people have become a disgrace to all our neighbors.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBOffset"><verse sID="Dan.9.17" osisID="Dan.9.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">But now, our God, listen to your servant’s prayer and pleas for help. Shine your face on your ruined sanctuary, for your own sake, my Lord.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.18" osisID="Dan.9.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Open your ears, my God, and listen! Open your eyes and look at our devastation. Look at the city called by your name! We pray our prayers for help to you, not because of any righteous acts of ours but because of your great compassion. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.19" osisID="Dan.9.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My Lord, listen! My Lord, forgive! My Lord, pay attention and act! Don’t delay! My God, do all this for your own sake, because your city and your people are called by your name.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.9.20-Dan.9.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Seventy weeks</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.9.20" osisID="Dan.9.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While I was still speaking, praying, and confessing my sin and the sins of my people Israel—while I was still praying my prayer for help to the <divineName type="x-CEBLord">LORD</divineName> my God about my God’s holy mountain—</verse><verse sID="Dan.9.21" osisID="Dan.9.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">while I was still speaking this prayer, the man Gabriel approached me at the time of the evening offering. This was the same Gabriel I had seen in my earlier vision. He was weary with exhaustion.<note osisRef="Dan.9.21" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.9.21!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">approached me in swift flight at the time of the evening offering; </hi>Heb uncertain</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.9.22" osisID="Dan.9.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He explained as he spoke with me: “Daniel, here’s why I’ve come: to give you insight and understanding. </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.23" osisID="Dan.9.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When you began making your requests, a word went out, and I’ve come to tell it to you because you are greatly treasured. So now understand this word and grasp the meaning of this vision! </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.24" osisID="Dan.9.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Seventy weeks are appointed for your people and for your holy city to complete the rebellion, to end sins, to cover over wrongdoing, to bring eternal righteousness, to seal up prophetic vision, and to anoint the most holy place.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.9.25" osisID="Dan.9.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">So you must know and gain wisdom about this: There will be seven weeks from the moment the word went out to restore and rebuild Jerusalem until a leader is anointed. And for sixty-two weeks the city will be rebuilt with a courtyard and a moat. But in difficult times,</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.26" osisID="Dan.9.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">after the sixty-two weeks, an anointed one will be eliminated. No one will support him.<note osisRef="Dan.9.26" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.9.26!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and will have nothing </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">and will disappear; </hi>Heb uncertain</note> The army of a future leader will destroy the city and the sanctuary. His<note osisRef="Dan.9.26" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.9.26!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Its </hi>(the army’s)</note> end will come in a flood, but devastations will be decreed until the end of the war.<note osisRef="Dan.9.26" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.9.26!note.f">Heb uncertain</note></q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.9.27" osisID="Dan.9.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">For one week, he will make a strong covenant with many people. For a half-week, he will stop both sacrifices and offerings. In their place<note osisRef="Dan.9.27" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.9.27!note.g">Correction <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">on the wing; </hi>Heb uncertain</note> will be the desolating monstrosities until the decreed destruction sweeps over the devastator.</q></verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.10" osisID="Dan.10" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="10"><div scope="Dan.10.1-Dan.10.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Vision of a man</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="Dan.10.1" osisID="Dan.10.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the third year of Persia’s King Cyrus, a message was revealed to Daniel, who was called Belteshazzar. The message was true: there would be a great conflict. Daniel understood the message, having discerned the meaning of the vision.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.2" osisID="Dan.10.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">During that time, I, Daniel, had been mourning for three weeks. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.3" osisID="Dan.10.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I didn’t eat any rich foods. Neither meat nor wine passed my lips, and I didn’t clean up at all until the three weeks were up. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.4" osisID="Dan.10.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then, on the twenty-fourth day of the first month, as I was on the bank of the great Tigris River, </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.5" osisID="Dan.10.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I looked up and suddenly saw a man clothed in linen in front of me. He had a brilliant gold belt around his waist, </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.6" osisID="Dan.10.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and his body was like topaz. His face was like a flash of lightning, and his eyes were like burning torches. His arms and feet looked like polished bronze. When he spoke, it sounded like the roar of a crowd. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.7" osisID="Dan.10.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Only I, Daniel, saw this vision. The other people who were with me didn’t see it. Despite that, they were terrified and ran away to hide.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.8" osisID="Dan.10.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So I was left alone to see this great vision all by myself. All my strength left me. My energy was sapped, and I couldn’t stay strong. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.9" osisID="Dan.10.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then I heard the sound of the man’s words. When I heard it, I fell into a trance with my face on the ground. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.10" osisID="Dan.10.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But then a hand touched me, lifting me up to my hands and knees.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.11" osisID="Dan.10.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The man said to me, <q type="x-complete">Daniel, you are greatly treasured. Now grasp the meaning of what I’m saying to you. And stand up, because I’ve been sent to you.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.11" osisID="Dan.10.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">As he said this to me, I stood up, shaking.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.12" osisID="Dan.10.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the man said to me, <q type="x-start">Don’t be afraid, Daniel, because from the day you first set your mind to understand things and to humble yourself before your God, your words were heard. I’ve come because of your words!</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.13" osisID="Dan.10.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">For twenty-one days the leader of the Persian kingdom blocked my way. But then Michael, one of the highest leaders, came to help me. I left Michael there with the leader of the Persian kingdom.<note osisRef="Dan.10.13" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.10.13!note.h">LXX; Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">after I was detained there with the kings of Persia</hi></note></q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.14" osisID="Dan.10.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But I’ve come to help you understand what will happen to your people in the future, because there is another vision concerning that time.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.15" osisID="Dan.10.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While he said this to me, I turned my face to the ground and kept quiet. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.16" osisID="Dan.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But then someone who looked like a human being<note osisRef="Dan.10.16" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.10.16!note.i">Heb <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">bene adam </hi>(<hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a son of a man</hi>) is an idiom that means <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">human being; </hi>cf 7:13.</note> touched my lips. Then I opened my mouth and spoke, saying to the person standing in front of me: <q type="x-start">My lord, the vision bothered me deeply, and I couldn’t stay strong during it.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.17" osisID="Dan.10.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">So how can I, my lord’s servant, speak with you, my lord? Even now there’s no strength in me, and I can barely breathe.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.18" osisID="Dan.10.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who looked like a human being touched me again and gave me strength. </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.19" osisID="Dan.10.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He said, <q type="x-complete">Don’t be afraid. You are greatly treasured. All will be well with you. Be strong!</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.19" osisID="Dan.10.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">As he spoke to me, I suddenly felt strong. Then I said: <q type="x-complete">My lord can go on, because you’ve made me strong.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.10.20" osisID="Dan.10.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he said: “Do you know why I have come to you? Now I must go back to fight the leader of Persia. As I leave, the leader of Greece will come! </verse><verse sID="Dan.10.21" osisID="Dan.10.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But I will tell you what is written in the Scroll of Truth. No one stands strong with me against these leaders except your leader Michael.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.11" osisID="Dan.11" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="11"><div scope="Dan.11.1-Dan.11.4" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">A vast empire divided</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="Dan.11.1" osisID="Dan.11.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">In the first year of Darius the Mede’s rule, I took my stand to strengthen and protect him.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.2" osisID="Dan.11.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I will now tell you the truth. Persia will have three more kings, but the fourth will be richer than all of them. Once he has become strong through his great riches, he will disturb everyone, including the Greek kingdom. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.3" osisID="Dan.11.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then a warrior-king will come forward, ruling over a vast empire and doing whatever he wants. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.4" osisID="Dan.11.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But even as he takes control, his kingdom will be broken, divided to the four winds of heaven. It won’t pass to his descendants. No one will rule like he did because his kingdom will be uprooted. It will belong to others, not to these.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.11.5-Dan.11.35" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">South and north</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.5" osisID="Dan.11.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“Then the southern king will gain power, but one of his princes will overpower him, ruling in his place. His empire will be vast. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.6" osisID="Dan.11.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After some years, they will make an agreement together. The southern king’s daughter will go to the northern king to finalize the agreement, but she won’t retain her great power. Neither will his power remain in place. In those times she will be handed over, along with her escort, the one who fathered her, and the one who strengthened her.<note osisRef="Dan.11.6" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.11.6!note.j">Heb uncertain</note></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.7" osisID="Dan.11.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“A branch from her roots will rise up in his place. Attacking the army, he will enter the walled fortress of the northern king. He will fight with them, and he will conquer. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.8" osisID="Dan.11.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will even carry off their gods to Egypt, along with their statues and their silver and gold equipment. For years he will avoid the northern king. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.9" osisID="Dan.11.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then the northern king will attack the kingdom of the southern king, but will return to his own land. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.10" osisID="Dan.11.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His sons will get ready for war, gathering massive forces. Their attack will be like an overwhelming flood. And they will attack again, taking the battle as far as his walled fortress.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.11" osisID="Dan.11.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“The southern king, in a bitter rage, will come out to battle the northern king. He will muster a huge army, but the army will be handed over to his enemy. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.12" osisID="Dan.11.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When the army is carried off, he will become confident. He will kill tens of thousands, but he will not stand strong. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.13" osisID="Dan.11.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The northern king will then muster another army—this one bigger than the first. After some years have passed, he will attack with a large and well-equipped army. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.14" osisID="Dan.11.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In those times, many will oppose the southern king. Violent persons from among your people also will rise up to support the vision, but they will fail.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.15" osisID="Dan.11.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“When the northern king attacks, he will throw up a siege ramp and occupy a walled city. The southern forces will not be able to resist—not even its elite forces. No one will be strong enough to resist. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.16" osisID="Dan.11.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who comes to attack will do whatever he wants; no one will be able to oppose him. He will take his place in the beautiful country, and he will hand out destruction. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.17" osisID="Dan.11.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will decide to occupy his entire kingdom by force. He will make an agreement with him and will give him a wife, intending to destroy him,<note osisRef="Dan.11.7" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.11.7!note.k">DSS; MT <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">her </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">it </hi>(the kingdom)</note> but it won’t succeed and it won’t happen.<note osisRef="Dan.11.7" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.11.7!note.l">Heb adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">for him</hi>.</note> </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.18" osisID="Dan.11.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will turn his face to the coastlands, capturing many people. A commander will put an end to his disgrace,<note osisRef="Dan.11.18" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.11.18!note.m">Heb adds <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">for him</hi>.</note> even though he won’t repay that disgrace. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.19" osisID="Dan.11.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he will turn his attention to the walled fortresses of his own country but will stumble, fall, and disappear.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.20" osisID="Dan.11.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“In his place one will arise who will send his agent to exact a kingdom’s glory, but in a few days he will be broken, though not by anger and not by war. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.21" osisID="Dan.11.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A worthless person will arise in his place. Royal majesty will not have been given to him, but he will come in a time of security and seize the kingdom by deceitful means. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.22" osisID="Dan.11.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Forces will be completely swept away and broken before him. The same is true for the leader of the covenant. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.23" osisID="Dan.11.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From the moment they make an agreement with him, he will act deceitfully. He will gain power at the expense of a small nation. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.24" osisID="Dan.11.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will come into a province’s richest places untroubled and will do what his fathers and grandfathers never could. He will hand out plunder, spoil, and wealth to them. He will make plans against fortresses, but only for a time.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.25" osisID="Dan.11.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“Then with a large army he will gather his strength and courage against the southern king. The southern king, with a large and super powerful army, will prepare for war, but he won’t endure because they will make plans against him. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.26" osisID="Dan.11.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who eat the king’s provisions will destroy him. His army will be overrun. Many will die.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.27" osisID="Dan.11.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“These two kings, with their minds set on evil, will sit at one table, telling lies, but with no success because the end will come at the set time. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.28" osisID="Dan.11.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will return to his country with great wealth and set his mind against a holy covenant. He will do what he wants and then return to his country. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.29" osisID="Dan.11.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the set time he will again battle against the south, but the second time will be different from the first. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.30" osisID="Dan.11.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Kittim ships will fight against him, and he will retreat in fear. He will rage against a holy covenant and will do what he wants. Then he will pay special attention to those who violate a holy covenant. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.31" osisID="Dan.11.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His forces will come and make the sanctuary fortress impure. They will stop the daily sacrifice and set up a desolating monstrosity. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.32" osisID="Dan.11.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">By deceitful means he will corrupt those who violate a covenant, but the people who acknowledge their God will stand strong and will act.</verse> </p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.33" osisID="Dan.11.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“The people’s teachers will help many understand, but for a time they will fall by sword and by flame, by captivity and by plunder. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.34" osisID="Dan.11.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they fall, they will receive a little help, but many will join them with deceitful plans. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.35" osisID="Dan.11.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some of the teachers too will fall in order that they might be refined, purified, and cleansed—until an end time, because it is still not yet the set time.</verse> </p></div><div scope="Dan.11.36-Dan.11.45" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">An end to the arrogant king</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.11.36" osisID="Dan.11.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">“The king will do whatever he wants. He will exalt himself, making himself greater than any god. He will say unbelievable things against the God of gods. He will succeed until the doom is completed, because what is decreed must take place. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.37" osisID="Dan.11.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will give no thought to the gods of his fathers, nor to the god cherished by women. He will give no thought to any god, because he will make himself greater than all of them. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.38" osisID="Dan.11.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In their place, he will worship a god of walled fortresses. With gold and silver, rare stones and precious things, he will worship a god his fathers did not acknowledge. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.39" osisID="Dan.11.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will deal with walled fortresses with the help of a foreign god. He will heap rewards on those who support him, making them rule over many and dividing up the land for a price. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.40" osisID="Dan.11.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the end time, the southern king will attack him. The northern king will storm against him with chariots and horses and many ships. He will invade countries, sweeping over them like a flood. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.41" osisID="Dan.11.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will invade the beautiful country, and tens of thousands will die. But Edom, Moab, and the best of the Ammonites will escape from his hand. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.42" osisID="Dan.11.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will extend his power into other countries. Even Egypt won’t escape. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.43" osisID="Dan.11.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will take control of Egypt’s hidden treasures of gold, silver, and all its precious things. Libyans and Cushites will follow at his feet. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.44" osisID="Dan.11.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But reports from the east and north will alarm him, and in a great rage he will set off to devastate and destroy many. </verse><verse sID="Dan.11.45" osisID="Dan.11.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will pitch his royal tents between the sea and the beautiful holy mountain. But he will come to his end, and no one will help him.</verse> </p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Dan.12" osisID="Dan.12" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="12"><div scope="Dan.12.1-Dan.12.4" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Eternal life or eternal disgrace</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="Dan.12.1" osisID="Dan.12.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-start">At that time, Michael the great leader who guards your people will take his stand. It will be a difficult time—nothing like it has ever happened since nations first appeared. But at that time every one of your people who is found written in the scroll will be rescued.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.2" osisID="Dan.12.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Many of those who sleep in the dusty land<note osisRef="Dan.12.2" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.12.2!note.n">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">earthy soil </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">dust of the earth</hi></note> will wake up—some to eternal life, others to shame and eternal disgrace.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.3" osisID="Dan.12.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Those skilled in wisdom<note osisRef="Dan.12.3" placement="inline" osisID="Dan.12.3!note.o">See 1:4; or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">The teachers; </hi>see 11:33, 35; also in 12:10.</note> will shine like the sky. Those who lead many to righteousness will shine like the stars forever and always.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.4" osisID="Dan.12.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">But you, Daniel, must keep these words secret! Seal the scroll until the end time! Many will stray far, but knowledge will increase.</q></verse></p></div><div scope="Dan.12.5-Dan.12.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Waiting for the end time</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.12.5" osisID="Dan.12.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I, Daniel, looked and suddenly saw two other figures—one standing on each side of the stream. </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.6" osisID="Dan.12.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">One said to the man clothed in white linen, who was farther upstream: <q type="x-complete">When will these astonishing things be over?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.12.7" osisID="Dan.12.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I heard the man clothed in white linen, who was farther upstream, swear by the one who lives forever as he raised both hands to heaven: <q type="x-complete">For one set time, two set times, and half a set time. When the breaking of the holy people’s power is over, all these things will be over.</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.12.8" osisID="Dan.12.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I heard it, but I didn’t understand it. <q type="x-complete">My lord,</q> I said, <q type="x-complete">what will happen after all this?</q></verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Dan.12.9" osisID="Dan.12.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He said, <q type="x-start">Get going now, Daniel, because these words must remain secret and sealed up until the end time.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.10" osisID="Dan.12.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Many will purify, cleanse, and refine themselves, but the wicked will act wickedly. None of the wicked will understand, but those skilled in wisdom will understand.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.11" osisID="Dan.12.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">There will be one thousand two hundred ninety days from the time the daily sacrifice is stopped to the setting up of the desolating monstrosity.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.12" osisID="Dan.12.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-continuation">Happy is the one who waits and reaches one thousand three hundred thirty-five days.</q> </verse><verse sID="Dan.12.13" osisID="Dan.12.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">Now as for you, go on to the end. You will rest and will stand to receive your reward at the end of days.</q></verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>