<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Corinthians</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="1Cor"><chapter sID="1Cor.1" osisID="1Cor.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Corinthians</title><div scope="1Cor.1.1-1Cor.1.3" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Cor.1.1" osisID="1Cor.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From Paul, called by God’s will to be an apostle of Jesus Christ, and from Sosthenes our brother. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Cor.1.2" osisID="1Cor.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">To God’s church that is in Corinth: </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Cor.1.2" osisID="1Cor.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">To those who have been made holy to God in Christ Jesus, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.2" osisID="1Cor.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">who are called to be God’s people. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Cor.1.2" osisID="1Cor.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Together with all those who call upon the name of our Lord Jesus Christ in every place—</verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.2" osisID="1Cor.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">he’s their Lord and ours! </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Cor.1.3" osisID="1Cor.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.1.4-1Cor.1.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Thanksgiving for the Corinthians</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.1.4" osisID="1Cor.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I thank my God always for you, because of God’s grace that was given to you in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.5" osisID="1Cor.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That is, you were made rich through him in everything: in all your communication and every kind of knowledge, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.6" osisID="1Cor.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">in the same way that the testimony about Christ was confirmed with you. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.7" osisID="1Cor.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The result is that you aren’t missing any spiritual gift while you wait for our Lord Jesus Christ to be revealed. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.8" osisID="1Cor.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He will also confirm your testimony about Christ until the end so that you will be blameless on the day of our Lord Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.9" osisID="1Cor.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God is faithful, and you were called by him to partnership with his Son, Jesus Christ our Lord. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.1.10-1Cor.1.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Rival groups in Corinth</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.1.10" osisID="1Cor.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now I encourage you, brothers and sisters, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ: Agree with each other and don’t be divided into rival groups. Instead, be restored with the same mind and the same purpose. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.11" osisID="1Cor.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, Chloe’s people gave me some information about you, that you’re fighting with each other. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.12" osisID="1Cor.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What I mean is this: that each one of you says, <q type="x-complete">I belong to Paul,</q> <q type="x-complete">I belong to Apollos,</q> <q type="x-complete">I belong to Cephas,</q> <q type="x-complete">I belong to Christ.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.13" osisID="1Cor.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Has Christ been divided? Was Paul crucified for you, or were you baptized in Paul’s name? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.14" osisID="1Cor.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Thank God that I didn’t baptize any of you, except Crispus and Gaius, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.15" osisID="1Cor.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so that nobody can say that you were baptized in my name! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.16" osisID="1Cor.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Oh, I baptized the house of Stephanas too. Otherwise, I don’t know if I baptized anyone else. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.17" osisID="1Cor.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Christ didn’t send me to baptize but to preach the good news. And Christ didn’t send me to preach the good news with clever words so that Christ’s cross won’t be emptied of its meaning. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.1.18-1Cor.1.31" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Human wisdom versus the cross</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.1.18" osisID="1Cor.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The message of the cross is foolishness to those who are being destroyed. But it is the power of God for those of us who are being saved. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.19" osisID="1Cor.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It is written in scripture: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and I will reject the intelligence of the intelligent</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.1.19" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.1.19!note.a">Isa 29:14</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.20" osisID="1Cor.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Where are the wise? Where are the legal experts? Where are today’s debaters? Hasn’t God made the wisdom of the world foolish? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.21" osisID="1Cor.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In God’s wisdom, he determined that the world wouldn’t come to know him through its wisdom. Instead, God was pleased to save those who believe through the foolishness of preaching. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.22" osisID="1Cor.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jews ask for signs, and Greeks look for wisdom, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.23" osisID="1Cor.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but we preach Christ crucified, which is a scandal to Jews and foolishness to Gentiles. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.24" osisID="1Cor.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But to those who are called—both Jews and Greeks—Christ is God’s power and God’s wisdom. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.25" osisID="1Cor.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is because the foolishness of God is wiser than human wisdom, and the weakness of God is stronger than human strength. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.1.26" osisID="1Cor.1.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Look at your situation when you were called, brothers and sisters! By ordinary human standards not many were wise, not many were powerful, not many were from the upper class. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.27" osisID="1Cor.1.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But God chose what the world considers foolish to shame the wise. God chose what the world considers weak to shame the strong. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.28" osisID="1Cor.1.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And God chose what the world considers low-class and low-life—what is considered to be nothing—to reduce what is considered to be something to nothing. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.29" osisID="1Cor.1.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So no human being can brag in God’s presence. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.30" osisID="1Cor.1.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It is because of God that you are in Christ Jesus. He became wisdom from God for us. This means that he made us righteous and holy, and he delivered us. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.1.31" osisID="1Cor.1.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is consistent with what was written: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The one who brags should brag in the Lord!</hi><note osisRef="1Cor.1.31" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.1.31!note.b">Jer 9:24</note> </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.2" osisID="1Cor.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="1Cor.2.1-1Cor.2.5" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.2.1" osisID="1Cor.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When I came to you, brothers and sisters, I didn’t come preaching God’s secrets to you like I was an expert in speech or wisdom. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.2" osisID="1Cor.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I had made up my mind not to think about anything while I was with you except Jesus Christ, and to preach him as crucified. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.3" osisID="1Cor.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I stood in front of you with weakness, fear, and a lot of shaking. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.4" osisID="1Cor.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My message and my preaching weren’t presented with convincing wise words but with a demonstration of the Spirit and of power. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.5" osisID="1Cor.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I did this so that your faith might not depend on the wisdom of people but on the power of God. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.2.6-1Cor.2.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Definition of wisdom</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.2.6" osisID="1Cor.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What we say is wisdom to people who are mature. It isn’t a wisdom that comes from the present day or from today’s leaders who are being reduced to nothing. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.7" osisID="1Cor.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We talk about God’s wisdom, which has been hidden as a secret. God determined this wisdom in advance, before time began, for our glory. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.8" osisID="1Cor.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It is a wisdom that none of the present-day rulers have understood, because if they did understand it, they would never have crucified the Lord of glory! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.9" osisID="1Cor.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But this is precisely what is written: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">God has prepared things for those who love him that no eye has seen, or ear has heard, or that haven’t crossed the mind of any human being</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.2.9" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.2.9!note.c">Isa 64:4</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.10" osisID="1Cor.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God has revealed these things to us through the Spirit. The Spirit searches everything, including the depths of God. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.11" osisID="1Cor.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Who knows a person’s depths except their own spirit that lives in them? In the same way, no one has known the depths of God except God’s Spirit. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.12" osisID="1Cor.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We haven’t received the world’s spirit but God’s Spirit so that we can know the things given to us by God. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.13" osisID="1Cor.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These are the things we are talking about—not with words taught by human wisdom but with words taught by the Spirit—we are interpreting spiritual things to spiritual people. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.14" osisID="1Cor.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But people who are unspiritual don’t accept the things from God’s Spirit. They are foolishness to them and can’t be understood, because they can only be comprehended in a spiritual way. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.15" osisID="1Cor.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Spiritual people comprehend everything, but they themselves aren’t understood by anyone. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.2.16" osisID="1Cor.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Who has known the mind of the Lord, who will advise him?</hi><note osisRef="1Cor.2.16" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.2.16!note.d">Isa 40:13</note> But we have the mind of Christ. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.3" osisID="1Cor.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="1Cor.3.1-1Cor.3.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Wisdom applied to divisions in the church</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.3.1" osisID="1Cor.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I couldn’t talk to you like spiritual people but like unspiritual people, like babies in Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.2" osisID="1Cor.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I gave you milk to drink instead of solid food, because you weren’t up to it yet. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.3" osisID="1Cor.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now you are still not up to it because you are still unspiritual. When jealousy and fighting exist between you, aren’t you unspiritual and living by human standards? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.4" osisID="1Cor.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When someone says, <q type="x-complete">I belong to Paul,</q> and someone else says, <q type="x-complete">I belong to Apollos,</q> aren’t you acting like people without the Spirit? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.5" osisID="1Cor.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After all, what is Apollos? What is Paul? They are servants who helped you to believe. Each one had a role given to them by the Lord: </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.6" osisID="1Cor.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I planted, Apollos watered, but God made it grow. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.7" osisID="1Cor.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, neither the one who plants nor the one who waters is anything, but the only one who is anything is God who makes it grow. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.8" osisID="1Cor.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who plants and the one who waters work together, but each one will receive their own reward for their own labor. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.9" osisID="1Cor.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We are God’s coworkers, and you are God’s field, God’s building. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.3.10" osisID="1Cor.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I laid a foundation like a wise master builder according to God’s grace that was given to me, but someone else is building on top of it. Each person needs to pay attention to the way they build on it. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.11" osisID="1Cor.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one can lay any other foundation besides the one that is already laid, which is Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.12" osisID="1Cor.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So, whether someone builds on top of the foundation with gold, silver, precious stones, wood, grass, or hay, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.13" osisID="1Cor.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">each one’s work will be clearly shown. The day will make it clear, because it will be revealed with fire—the fire will test the quality of each one’s work. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.14" osisID="1Cor.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If anyone’s work survives, they’ll get a reward. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.15" osisID="1Cor.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if anyone’s work goes up in flames, they’ll lose it. However, they themselves will be saved as if they had gone through a fire. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.16" osisID="1Cor.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that you are God’s temple and God’s Spirit lives in you? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.17" osisID="1Cor.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If someone destroys God’s temple, God will destroy that person, because God’s temple is holy, which is what you are. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.3.18" osisID="1Cor.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t fool yourself. If some of you think they are worldly-wise, then they should become foolish so that they can become wise. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.19" osisID="1Cor.3.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This world’s wisdom is foolishness to God. As it’s written, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">He catches the wise in their cleverness.</hi><note osisRef="1Cor.3.19" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.3.19!note.e">Job 5:13</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.20" osisID="1Cor.3.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And also, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The Lord knows that the thoughts of the wise are silly</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.3.20" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.3.20!note.f">Ps 94:11</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.21" osisID="1Cor.3.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, no one should brag about human beings. Everything belongs to you—</verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.22" osisID="1Cor.3.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Paul, Apollos, Cephas, the world, life, death, things in the present, things in the future—everything belongs to you, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.3.23" osisID="1Cor.3.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but you belong to Christ, and Christ belongs to God. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.4" osisID="1Cor.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="1Cor.4.1-1Cor.4.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s role as an apostle</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.4.1" osisID="1Cor.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So a person should think about us this way—as servants of Christ and managers of God’s secrets. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.2" osisID="1Cor.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In this kind of situation, what is expected of a manager is that they prove to be faithful. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.3" osisID="1Cor.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I couldn’t care less if I’m judged by you or by any human court; I don’t even judge myself. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.4" osisID="1Cor.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m not aware of anything against me, but that doesn’t make me innocent, because the Lord is the one who judges me. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.5" osisID="1Cor.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So don’t judge anything before the right time—wait until the Lord comes. He will bring things that are hidden in the dark to light, and he will make people’s motivations public. Then there will be recognition for each person from God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.4.6" osisID="1Cor.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I have applied these things to myself and Apollos for your benefit. I’ve done this so that you can learn what it means not to go beyond what has been written and so none of you will become arrogant by supporting one of us against the other. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.7" osisID="1Cor.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Who says that you are better than anyone else? What do you have that you didn’t receive? And if you received it, then why are you bragging as if you didn’t receive it? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.8" osisID="1Cor.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You’ve been filled already! You’ve become rich already! You rule like kings without us! I wish you did rule so that we could be kings with you! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.9" osisID="1Cor.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I suppose that God has shown that we apostles are at the end of the line. We are like prisoners sentenced to death, because we have become a spectacle in the world, both to angels and to humans. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.10" osisID="1Cor.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We are fools for Christ, but you are wise through Christ! We are weak, but you are strong! You are honored, but we are dishonored! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.11" osisID="1Cor.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Up to this very moment we are hungry, thirsty, wearing rags, abused, and homeless. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.12" osisID="1Cor.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We work hard with our own hands. When we are insulted, we respond with a blessing; when we are harassed, we put up with it; </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.13" osisID="1Cor.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">when our reputation is attacked, we are encouraging. We have become the scum of the earth, the waste that runs off everything, up to the present time. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.4.14" osisID="1Cor.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m not writing these things to make you ashamed but to warn you, since you are my loved children. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.15" osisID="1Cor.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You may have ten thousand mentors in Christ, but you don’t have many fathers. I gave birth to you in Christ Jesus through the gospel, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.16" osisID="1Cor.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so I encourage you to follow my example. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.17" osisID="1Cor.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why I’ve sent Timothy to you; he’s my loved and trusted child in the Lord; he’ll remind you about my way of life in Christ Jesus. He’ll teach the same way as I teach everywhere in every church. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.18" osisID="1Cor.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some have become arrogant as if I’m not coming to see you. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.19" osisID="1Cor.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But, if the Lord is willing, I’ll come to you soon. Then I won’t focus on what these arrogant people say, but I’ll find out what power they possess. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.20" osisID="1Cor.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God’s kingdom isn’t about words but about power. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.4.21" osisID="1Cor.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Which do you want? Should I come to you with a big stick to punish you, or with love and a gentle spirit? </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.5" osisID="1Cor.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="1Cor.5.1-1Cor.5.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Confronting sexual immorality in the church</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.5.1" osisID="1Cor.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everyone has heard that there is sexual immorality among you. This is a type of immorality that isn’t even heard of among the Gentiles—a man is having sex with his father’s wife! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.2" osisID="1Cor.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And you’re proud of yourselves instead of being so upset that the one who did this thing is expelled from your community. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.3" osisID="1Cor.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Though I’m absent physically, I’m present in the spirit and I’ve already judged the man who did this as if I were present. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.4" osisID="1Cor.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When you meet together in the name of our Lord Jesus, I’ll be present in spirit with the power of our Lord Jesus. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.5" osisID="1Cor.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time we need to hand this man over to Satan to destroy his human weakness so that his spirit might be saved on the day of the Lord. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.5.6" osisID="1Cor.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Your bragging isn’t good! Don’t you know that a tiny grain of yeast makes a whole batch of dough rise? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.7" osisID="1Cor.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Clean out the old yeast so you can be a new batch of dough, given that you’re supposed to be unleavened bread. Christ our Passover lamb has been sacrificed, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.8" osisID="1Cor.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so let’s celebrate the feast with the unleavened bread of honesty and truth, not with old yeast or with the yeast of evil and wickedness. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.5.9" osisID="1Cor.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I wrote to you in my earlier letter not to associate with sexually immoral people. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.10" osisID="1Cor.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But I wasn’t talking about the sexually immoral people in the outside world by any means—or the greedy, or the swindlers, or people who worship false gods—otherwise, you would have to leave the world entirely! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.11" osisID="1Cor.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now I’m writing to you not to associate with anyone who calls themselves <q type="x-complete">brother</q> or <q type="x-complete">sister</q> who is sexually immoral, greedy, someone who worships false gods, an abusive person, a drunk, or a swindler. Don’t even eat with anyone like this. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.12" osisID="1Cor.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What do I care about judging outsiders? Isn’t it your job to judge insiders? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.5.13" osisID="1Cor.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God will judge outsiders. <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Expel the evil one from among you!</hi><note osisRef="1Cor.5.13" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.5.13!note.g">Deut 17:7; 19:19; 22:21, 24; 24:7</note> </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.6" osisID="1Cor.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="1Cor.6.1-1Cor.6.11" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Confronting lawsuits in the church</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.6.1" osisID="1Cor.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When someone in your assembly has a legal case against another member, do they dare to take it to court to be judged by people who aren’t just, instead of by God’s people? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.2" osisID="1Cor.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Or don’t you know that God’s people will judge the world? If the world is to be judged by you, are you incompetent to judge trivial cases? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.3" osisID="1Cor.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that we will judge angels? Why not ordinary things? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.4" osisID="1Cor.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then if you have ordinary lawsuits, do you appoint people as judges who aren’t respected by the church? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.5" osisID="1Cor.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m saying this because you should be ashamed of yourselves! Isn’t there one person among you who is wise enough to pass judgment between believers? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.6" osisID="1Cor.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But instead, does a brother or sister have a lawsuit against another brother or sister, and do they do this in front of unbelievers? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.7" osisID="1Cor.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The fact that you have lawsuits against each other means that you’ve already lost your case. Why not be wronged instead? Why not be cheated? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.8" osisID="1Cor.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But instead you are doing wrong and cheating—and you’re doing it to your own brothers and sisters. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.6.9" osisID="1Cor.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that people who are unjust won’t inherit God’s kingdom? Don’t be deceived. Those who are sexually immoral, those who worship false gods, adulterers, both participants in same-sex intercourse,<note osisRef="1Cor.6.9" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.6.9!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">submissive and dominant male sexual partners</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.10" osisID="1Cor.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">thieves, the greedy, drunks, abusive people, and swindlers won’t inherit God’s kingdom. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.11" osisID="1Cor.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That is what some of you used to be! But you were washed clean, you were made holy to God, and you were made right with God in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ and in the Spirit of our God. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.6.12-1Cor.6.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Avoid sexual immorality</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.6.12" osisID="1Cor.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I have the freedom to do anything, but not everything is helpful. I have the freedom to do anything, but I won’t be controlled by anything. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.13" osisID="1Cor.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Food is for the stomach and the stomach is for food, and yet God will do away with both. The body isn’t for sexual immorality but for the Lord, and the Lord is for the body. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.14" osisID="1Cor.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God has raised the Lord and will raise us through his power. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.15" osisID="1Cor.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that your bodies are parts of Christ? So then, should I take parts of Christ and make them a part of someone who is sleeping around?<note osisRef="1Cor.6.15" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.6.15!note.i">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a prostitute; </hi>commonly, women who sell their bodies to multiple sex partners but includes those who are sexually immoral</note> No way! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.16" osisID="1Cor.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that anyone who is joined to someone who is sleeping around is one body with that person? The scripture says, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The two will become one flesh</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.6.16" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.6.16!note.j">Gen 2:2</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.17" osisID="1Cor.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who is joined to the Lord is one spirit with him. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.18" osisID="1Cor.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Avoid sexual immorality! Every sin that a person can do is committed outside the body, except those who engage in sexual immorality commit sin against their own bodies. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.19" osisID="1Cor.6.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Or don’t you know that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit who is in you? Don’t you know that you have the Holy Spirit from God, and you don’t belong to yourselves? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.6.20" osisID="1Cor.6.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You have been bought and paid for, so honor God with your body. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.7" osisID="1Cor.7" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="7"><div scope="1Cor.7.1-1Cor.7.40" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Marriage and celibacy</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.7.1" osisID="1Cor.7.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now, about what you wrote: <q type="x-complete">It’s good for a man not to have sex with a woman.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.2" osisID="1Cor.7.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each man should have his own wife, and each woman should have her own husband because of sexual immorality. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.3" osisID="1Cor.7.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The husband should meet his wife’s sexual needs, and the wife should do the same for her husband. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.4" osisID="1Cor.7.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The wife doesn’t have authority over her own body, but the husband does. Likewise, the husband doesn’t have authority over his own body, but the wife does. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.5" osisID="1Cor.7.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t refuse to meet each other’s needs unless you both agree for a short period of time to devote yourselves to prayer. Then come back together again so that Satan might not tempt you because of your lack of self-control. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.6" osisID="1Cor.7.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m saying this to give you permission; it’s not a command. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.7" osisID="1Cor.7.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I wish all people were like me, but each has a particular gift from God: one has this gift, and another has that one. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.7.8" osisID="1Cor.7.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m telling those who are single and widows that it’s good for them to stay single like me. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.9" osisID="1Cor.7.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if they can’t control themselves, they should get married, because it’s better to marry than to burn with passion. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.10" osisID="1Cor.7.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m passing on the Lord’s command to those who are married: A wife shouldn’t leave her husband, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.11" osisID="1Cor.7.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but if she does leave him, then she should stay single or be reconciled to her husband. And a man shouldn’t divorce his wife. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.7.12" osisID="1Cor.7.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m telling everyone else (the Lord didn’t say this specifically): If a believer has a wife who doesn’t believe, and she agrees to live with him, then he shouldn’t divorce her. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.13" osisID="1Cor.7.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If a woman has a husband who doesn’t believe and he agrees to live with her, then she shouldn’t divorce him. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.14" osisID="1Cor.7.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The husband who doesn’t believe belongs to God because of his wife, and the wife who doesn’t believe belongs to God because of her husband. Otherwise, your children would be contaminated by the world, but now they are spiritually set apart. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.15" osisID="1Cor.7.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if a spouse who doesn’t believe chooses to leave, then let them leave. The brother or sister isn’t tied down in these circumstances. God has called you to peace. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.16" osisID="1Cor.7.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">How do you know as a wife if you will save your husband? Or how do you know as a husband if you will save your wife? </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.7.17" osisID="1Cor.7.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nevertheless, each person should live the kind of life that the Lord assigned when he called each one. This is what I teach in all the churches. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.18" osisID="1Cor.7.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If someone was circumcised when called, he shouldn’t try to reverse it. If someone wasn’t circumcised when he was called, he shouldn’t be circumcised. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.19" osisID="1Cor.7.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Circumcision is nothing; not being circumcised is nothing. What matters is keeping God’s commandments. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.20" osisID="1Cor.7.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each person should stay in the situation they were in when they were called. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.21" osisID="1Cor.7.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If you were a slave when you were called, don’t let it bother you. But if you are actually able to be free, take advantage of the opportunity. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.22" osisID="1Cor.7.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Anyone who was a slave when they were called by the Lord has the status of being the Lord’s free person. In the same way, anyone who was a free person when they were called is Christ’s slave. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.23" osisID="1Cor.7.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You were bought and paid for. Don’t become slaves of people. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.24" osisID="1Cor.7.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, brothers and sisters, each of you should stay with God in the situation you were in when you were called. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.7.25" osisID="1Cor.7.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I don’t have a command from the Lord about people who have never been married,<note osisRef="1Cor.7.25" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.7.25!note.k">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">virgins</hi></note> but I’ll give you my opinion as someone you can trust because of the Lord’s mercy. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.26" osisID="1Cor.7.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So I think this advice is good because of the present crisis: Stay as you are. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.27" osisID="1Cor.7.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If you are married, don’t get a divorce. If you are divorced, don’t try to find a spouse. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.28" osisID="1Cor.7.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if you do marry, you haven’t sinned; and if someone who hasn’t been married gets married, they haven’t sinned. But married people will have a hard time, and I’m trying to spare you that. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.29" osisID="1Cor.7.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what I’m saying, brothers and sisters: The time has drawn short. From now on, those who have wives should be like people who don’t have them. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.30" osisID="1Cor.7.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who are sad should be like people who aren’t crying. Those who are happy should be like people who aren’t happy. Those who buy something should be like people who don’t have possessions. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.31" osisID="1Cor.7.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who use the world should be like people who aren’t preoccupied with it, because this world in its present form is passing away. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.7.32" osisID="1Cor.7.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I want you to be free from concerns. A man who isn’t married is concerned about the Lord’s concerns—how he can please the Lord. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.33" osisID="1Cor.7.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But a married man is concerned about the world’s concerns—how he can please his wife. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.34" osisID="1Cor.7.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His attention is divided. A woman who isn’t married or who is a virgin is concerned about the Lord’s concerns so that she can be dedicated to God in both body and spirit. But a married woman is concerned about the world’s concerns—how she can please her husband. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.35" osisID="1Cor.7.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m saying this for your own advantage. It’s not to restrict you but rather to promote effective and consistent service to the Lord without distraction. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.7.36" osisID="1Cor.7.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If someone thinks he is acting inappropriately toward an unmarried woman whom he knows, and if he has strong feelings and it seems like the right thing to do, he should do what he wants—he’s not sinning—they should get married. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.37" osisID="1Cor.7.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if a man stands firm in his decision, and doesn’t feel the pressure, but has his own will under control, he does right if he decides in his own heart not to marry the woman. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.38" osisID="1Cor.7.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, the one who marries the unmarried woman does right, and the one who doesn’t get married will do even better. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.39" osisID="1Cor.7.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A woman is obligated to stay in her marriage as long as her husband is alive. But if her husband dies, she is free to marry whomever she wants, only it should be a believer in the Lord. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.7.40" osisID="1Cor.7.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But in my opinion, she will be happier if she stays the way she is. And I think that I have God’s Spirit too. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.8" osisID="1Cor.8" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="8"><div scope="1Cor.8.1-1Cor.8.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Meat sacrificed to false gods</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.8.1" osisID="1Cor.8.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now concerning meat that has been sacrificed to a false god: We know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge makes people arrogant, but love builds people up. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.2" osisID="1Cor.8.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If anyone thinks they know something, they don’t yet know as much as they should know. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.3" osisID="1Cor.8.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if someone loves God, then they are known by God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.8.4" osisID="1Cor.8.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So concerning the actual food involved in these sacrifices to false gods, we know that a false god isn’t anything in this world, and that there is no God except for the one God. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.5" osisID="1Cor.8.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Granted, there are so-called <q type="x-complete">gods,</q> in heaven and on the earth, as there are many gods and many lords. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.6" osisID="1Cor.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">However, for us believers, </verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Cor.8.6" osisID="1Cor.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">There is one God the Father. </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="1Cor.8.6" osisID="1Cor.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">All things come from him, and we belong to him. </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Cor.8.6" osisID="1Cor.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">And there is one Lord Jesus Christ. </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="1Cor.8.6" osisID="1Cor.8.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">All things exist through him, and we live through him. </verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.8.7" osisID="1Cor.8.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But not everybody knows this. Some are eating this food as though it really is food sacrificed to a real idol, because they were used to idol worship until now. Their conscience is weak because it has been damaged. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.8" osisID="1Cor.8.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Food won’t bring us close to God. We’re not missing out if we don’t eat, and we don’t have any advantage if we do eat. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.9" osisID="1Cor.8.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But watch out or else this freedom of yours might be a problem for those who are weak. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.10" osisID="1Cor.8.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Suppose someone sees you (the person who has knowledge) eating in an idol’s temple. Won’t the person with a weak conscience be encouraged to eat the meat sacrificed to false gods? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.11" osisID="1Cor.8.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The weak brother or sister for whom Christ died is destroyed by your knowledge. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.12" osisID="1Cor.8.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You sin against Christ if you sin against your brothers and sisters and hurt their weak consciences this way. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.8.13" osisID="1Cor.8.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why, if food causes the downfall of my brother or sister, I won’t eat meat ever again, or else I may cause my brother or sister to fall. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.9" osisID="1Cor.9" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="9"><div scope="1Cor.9.1-1Cor.9.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Waiving rights for the gospel</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Cor.9.1" osisID="1Cor.9.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Haven’t I seen Jesus our Lord? Aren’t you my work in the Lord? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.2" osisID="1Cor.9.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I’m not an apostle to others, at least I am to you! You are the seal that shows I’m an apostle. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.3" osisID="1Cor.9.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is my defense against those who criticize me. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.4" osisID="1Cor.9.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t we have the right to eat and drink? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.5" osisID="1Cor.9.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t we have the right to travel with a wife who believes like the rest of the apostles, the Lord’s brothers, and Cephas? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.6" osisID="1Cor.9.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Or is it only I and Barnabas who don’t have the right to not work for our living? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.7" osisID="1Cor.9.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Who joins the army and pays their own way? Who plants a vineyard and doesn’t eat its fruit? Who shepherds a flock and doesn’t drink its milk? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.8" osisID="1Cor.9.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m not saying these things just based on common sense, am I? Doesn’t the Law itself say these things? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.9" osisID="1Cor.9.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In Moses’ Law it’s written: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">You will not muzzle the ox when it is threshing</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.9.9" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.9.9!note.l">Deut 25:4</note> Is God worried about oxen, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.10" osisID="1Cor.9.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">or did he say this entirely for our sake? It was written for our sake because the one who plows and the one who threshes should each do so with the hope of sharing the produce. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.11" osisID="1Cor.9.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If we sowed spiritual things in you, is it so much to ask to harvest some material things from you? </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.9.12" osisID="1Cor.9.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If others have these rights over you, don’t we deserve them all the more? However, we haven’t made use of this right, but we put up with everything so we don’t put any obstacle in the way of the gospel of Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.13" osisID="1Cor.9.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that those who serve in the temple get to eat food from the temple, and those who serve at the altar share part of what is sacrificed on the altar? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.14" osisID="1Cor.9.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, the Lord commanded that those who preach the gospel should get their living from the gospel. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.15" osisID="1Cor.9.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But I haven’t taken advantage of this. And I’m not writing this so that it will be done for me. It’s better for me to die than to lose my right to brag about this! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.16" osisID="1Cor.9.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I preach the gospel, I have no reason to brag, since I’m obligated to do it. I’m in trouble if I don’t preach the gospel. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.17" osisID="1Cor.9.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I do this voluntarily, I get rewarded for it. But if I’m forced to do it, then I’ve been charged with a responsibility. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.18" osisID="1Cor.9.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What reward do I get? That when I preach, I offer the good news free of charge. That’s why I don’t use the rights to which I’m entitled through the gospel. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.9.19" osisID="1Cor.9.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Although I’m free from all people, I make myself a slave to all people, to recruit more of them. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.20" osisID="1Cor.9.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I act like a Jew to the Jews, so I can recruit Jews. I act like I’m under the Law to those under the Law, so I can recruit those who are under the Law (though I myself am not under the Law). </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.21" osisID="1Cor.9.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I act like I’m outside the Law to those who are outside the Law, so I can recruit those outside the Law (though I’m not outside the law of God but rather under the law of Christ). </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.22" osisID="1Cor.9.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I act weak to the weak, so I can recruit the weak. I have become all things to all people, so I could save some by all possible means. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.23" osisID="1Cor.9.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the things I do are for the sake of the gospel, so I can be a partner with it. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.9.24" osisID="1Cor.9.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you know that all the runners in the stadium run, but only one gets the prize? So run to win. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.25" osisID="1Cor.9.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everyone who competes practices self-discipline in everything. The runners do this to get a crown of leaves that shrivel up and die, but we do it to receive a crown that never dies. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.26" osisID="1Cor.9.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now this is how I run—not without a clear goal in sight. I fight like a boxer in the ring, not like someone who is shadowboxing. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.9.27" osisID="1Cor.9.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rather, I’m landing punches on my own body and subduing it like a slave. I do this to be sure that I myself won’t be disqualified after preaching to others. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.10" osisID="1Cor.10" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="10"><div scope="1Cor.10.1-1Cor.10.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Warning from the wilderness generation</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Cor.10.1" osisID="1Cor.10.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I want you to be sure of the fact that our ancestors were all under the cloud and they all went through the sea. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.2" osisID="1Cor.10.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All were baptized into Moses in the cloud and in the sea. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.3" osisID="1Cor.10.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All ate the same spiritual food, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.4" osisID="1Cor.10.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and all drank the same spiritual drink. They drank from a spiritual rock that followed them, and the rock was Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.5" osisID="1Cor.10.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, God was unhappy with most of them, and they were struck down in the wilderness. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.6" osisID="1Cor.10.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These things were examples for us, so we won’t crave evil things like they did. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.7" osisID="1Cor.10.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t worship false gods like some of them did, as it is written, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The people sat down to eat and drink and they got up to play</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.10.7" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.10.7!note.m">Exod 32:6</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.8" osisID="1Cor.10.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Let’s not practice sexual immorality, like some of them did, and twenty-three thousand died in one day. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.9" osisID="1Cor.10.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Let’s not test Christ, like some of them did, and were killed by the snakes. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.10" osisID="1Cor.10.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Let’s not grumble, like some of them did, and were killed by the destroyer. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.11" osisID="1Cor.10.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These things happened to them as an example and were written as a warning for us to whom the end of time has come. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.12" osisID="1Cor.10.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So those who think they are standing need to watch out or else they may fall. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.13" osisID="1Cor.10.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No temptation has seized you that isn’t common for people. But God is faithful. He won’t allow you to be tempted beyond your abilities. Instead, with the temptation, God will also supply a way out so that you will be able to endure it. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.10.14-1Cor.10.33" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Avoid false gods to glorify God</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.10.14" osisID="1Cor.10.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, my dear friends, run away from the worship of false gods! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.15" osisID="1Cor.10.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m talking to you like you are sensible people. Think about what I’m saying. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.16" osisID="1Cor.10.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Isn’t the cup of blessing that we bless a sharing in the blood of Christ? Isn’t the loaf of bread that we break a sharing in the body of Christ? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.17" osisID="1Cor.10.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since there is one loaf of bread, we who are many are one body, because we all share the one loaf of bread. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.18" osisID="1Cor.10.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Look at the people of Israel. Don’t those who eat the sacrifices share from the altar? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.19" osisID="1Cor.10.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What am I saying then? That food sacrificed to a false god is anything, or that a false god is anything? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.20" osisID="1Cor.10.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No, but this kind of sacrifice is sacrificed to demons and not to God. I don’t want you to be sharing in demons. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.21" osisID="1Cor.10.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You can’t drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons; you can’t participate in the table of the Lord and the table of demons. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.22" osisID="1Cor.10.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Or should we make the Lord jealous? We aren’t stronger than he is, are we? </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.10.23" osisID="1Cor.10.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everything is permitted, but everything isn’t beneficial. Everything is permitted, but everything doesn’t build others up. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.24" osisID="1Cor.10.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one should look out for their own advantage, but they should look out for each other. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.25" osisID="1Cor.10.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Eat everything that is sold in the marketplace, without asking questions about it because of your conscience. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.26" osisID="1Cor.10.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The earth and all that is in it belong to the Lord</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.10.26" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.10.26!note.n">Ps 24:1</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.27" osisID="1Cor.10.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If an unbeliever invites you to eat with them and you want to go, eat whatever is served, without asking questions because of your conscience. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.28" osisID="1Cor.10.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if someone says to you, <q type="x-complete">This meat was sacrificed in a temple,</q> then don’t eat it for the sake of the one who told you and for the sake of conscience. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.29" osisID="1Cor.10.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now when I say <q type="x-complete">conscience</q> I don’t mean yours but the other person’s. Why should my freedom be judged by someone else’s conscience? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.30" osisID="1Cor.10.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I participate with gratitude, why should I be blamed for food I thank God for? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.31" osisID="1Cor.10.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So, whether you eat or drink or whatever you do, you should do it all for God’s glory. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.32" osisID="1Cor.10.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t offend either Jews or Greeks, or God’s church. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.10.33" osisID="1Cor.10.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is the same thing that I do. I please everyone in everything I do. I don’t look out for my own advantage, but I look out for many people so that they can be saved. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.11" osisID="1Cor.11" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="11"><div scope="1Cor.11.1-1Cor.11.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.11.1" osisID="1Cor.11.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Follow my example, just like I follow Christ’s. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.11.2-1Cor.11.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Appropriate dress in worship</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.11.2" osisID="1Cor.11.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I praise you because you remember all my instructions, and you hold on to the traditions exactly as I handed them on to you. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.3" osisID="1Cor.11.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now I want you to know that the head of every man is Christ, and the head of the woman is the man, and the head of Christ is God. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.4" osisID="1Cor.11.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Every man who prays or prophesies with his head covered shames his head. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.11.5" osisID="1Cor.11.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Every woman who prays or prophesies with her head uncovered disgraces her head. It is the same thing as having her head shaved. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.6" osisID="1Cor.11.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If a woman doesn’t cover her head, then she should have her hair cut off. If it is disgraceful for a woman to have short hair or to be shaved, then she should keep her head covered. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.7" osisID="1Cor.11.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A man shouldn’t have his head covered, because he is the image and glory of God; but the woman is man’s glory. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.8" osisID="1Cor.11.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Man didn’t have his origin from woman, but woman from man; </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.9" osisID="1Cor.11.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and man wasn’t created for the sake of the woman, but the woman for the sake of the man. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.10" osisID="1Cor.11.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this a woman should have authority over her head, because of the angels. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.11" osisID="1Cor.11.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, woman isn’t independent from man, and man isn’t independent from woman in the Lord. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.12" osisID="1Cor.11.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As woman came from man so also man comes from woman. But everything comes from God. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.13" osisID="1Cor.11.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Judge for yourselves: Is it appropriate for a woman to pray to God with her head uncovered? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.14" osisID="1Cor.11.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Doesn’t nature itself teach you that if a man has long hair, it is a disgrace to him; </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.15" osisID="1Cor.11.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but if a woman has long hair, it is her glory? This is because her long hair is given to her for a covering. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.16" osisID="1Cor.11.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if someone wants to argue about this, we don’t have such a custom, nor do God’s churches. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.11.17-1Cor.11.34" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The community meal</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.11.17" osisID="1Cor.11.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now I don’t praise you as I give the following instruction because when you meet together, it does more harm than good. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.18" osisID="1Cor.11.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">First of all, when you meet together as a church, I hear that there are divisions among you, and I partly believe it. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.19" osisID="1Cor.11.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s necessary that there are groups among you, to make it clear who is genuine. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.20" osisID="1Cor.11.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So when you get together in one place, it isn’t to eat the Lord’s meal. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.21" osisID="1Cor.11.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each of you goes ahead and eats a private meal. One person goes hungry while another is drunk. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.22" osisID="1Cor.11.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t you have houses to eat and drink in? Or do you look down on God’s churches and humiliate those who have nothing? What can I say to you? Will I praise you? No, I don’t praise you in this. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.11.23" osisID="1Cor.11.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I received a tradition from the Lord, which I also handed on to you: on the night on which he was betrayed, the Lord Jesus took bread. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.24" osisID="1Cor.11.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After giving thanks, he broke it and said, <q type="x-complete">This is my body, which is for you; do this to remember me.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.25" osisID="1Cor.11.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did the same thing with the cup, after they had eaten, saying, <q type="x-complete">This cup is the new covenant in my blood. Every time you drink it, do this to remember me.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.26" osisID="1Cor.11.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Every time you eat this bread and drink this cup, you broadcast the death of the Lord until he comes. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.11.27" osisID="1Cor.11.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why those who eat the bread or drink the cup of the Lord inappropriately will be guilty of the Lord’s body and blood. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.28" osisID="1Cor.11.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each individual should test himself or herself, and eat from the bread and drink from the cup in that way. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.29" osisID="1Cor.11.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who eat and drink without correctly understanding the body are eating and drinking their own judgment. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.30" osisID="1Cor.11.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, many of you are weak and sick, and quite a few have died. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.31" osisID="1Cor.11.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if we had judged ourselves, we wouldn’t be judged. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.32" osisID="1Cor.11.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, we are disciplined by the Lord when we are judged so that we won’t be judged and condemned along with the whole world. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.33" osisID="1Cor.11.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">For these reasons, my brothers and sisters, when you get together to eat, wait for each other. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.11.34" osisID="1Cor.11.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If some of you are hungry, they should eat at home so that getting together doesn’t lead to judgment. I will give directions about the other things when I come. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.12" osisID="1Cor.12" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="12"><div scope="1Cor.12.1-1Cor.12.31" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Spiritual gifts</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Cor.12.1" osisID="1Cor.12.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I don’t want you to be ignorant about spiritual gifts. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.2" osisID="1Cor.12.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know that when you were Gentiles you were often misled by false gods that can’t even speak. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.3" osisID="1Cor.12.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So I want to make it clear to you that no one says, <q type="x-complete">Jesus is cursed!</q> when speaking by God’s Spirit, and no one can say, <q type="x-complete">Jesus is Lord,</q> except by the Holy Spirit. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.4" osisID="1Cor.12.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There are different spiritual gifts but the same Spirit; </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.5" osisID="1Cor.12.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and there are different ministries and the same Lord; </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.6" osisID="1Cor.12.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and there are different activities but the same God who produces all of them in everyone. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.7" osisID="1Cor.12.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A demonstration of the Spirit is given to each person for the common good. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.8" osisID="1Cor.12.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A word of wisdom is given by the Spirit to one person, a word of knowledge to another according to the same Spirit, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.9" osisID="1Cor.12.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">faith to still another by the same Spirit, gifts of healing to another in the one Spirit, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.10" osisID="1Cor.12.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">performance of miracles to another, prophecy to another, the ability to tell spirits apart to another, different kinds of tongues<note osisRef="1Cor.12.10" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.12.10!note.o">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">ecstatic speech </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">languages </hi>could be used for <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">tongues </hi>or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">tongue </hi>throughout chaps 12–14.</note> to another, and the interpretation of the tongues to another. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.11" osisID="1Cor.12.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All these things are produced by the one and same Spirit who gives what he wants to each person. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.12.12" osisID="1Cor.12.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Christ is just like the human body—a body is a unit and has many parts; and all the parts of the body are one body, even though there are many. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.13" osisID="1Cor.12.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We were all baptized by one Spirit into one body, whether Jew or Greek, or slave or free, and we all were given one Spirit to drink. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.14" osisID="1Cor.12.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Certainly the body isn’t one part but many. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.15" osisID="1Cor.12.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If the foot says, <q type="x-complete">I’m not part of the body because I’m not a hand,</q> does that mean it’s not part of the body? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.16" osisID="1Cor.12.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If the ear says, <q type="x-complete">I’m not part of the body because I’m not an eye,</q> does that mean it’s not part of the body? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.17" osisID="1Cor.12.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If the whole body were an eye, what would happen to the hearing? And if the whole body were an ear, what would happen to the sense of smell? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.18" osisID="1Cor.12.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But as it is, God has placed each one of the parts in the body just like he wanted. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.19" osisID="1Cor.12.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If all were one and the same body part, what would happen to the body? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.20" osisID="1Cor.12.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But as it is, there are many parts but one body. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.21" osisID="1Cor.12.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the eye can’t say to the hand, <q type="x-complete">I don’t need you,</q> or in turn, the head can’t say to the feet, <q type="x-complete">I don’t need you.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.22" osisID="1Cor.12.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, the parts of the body that people think are the weakest are the most necessary. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.23" osisID="1Cor.12.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The parts of the body that we think are less honorable are the ones we honor the most. The private parts of our body that aren’t presentable are the ones that are given the most dignity. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.24" osisID="1Cor.12.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The parts of our body that are presentable don’t need this. But God has put the body together, giving greater honor to the part with less honor </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.25" osisID="1Cor.12.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so that there won’t be division in the body and so the parts might have mutual concern for each other. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.26" osisID="1Cor.12.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If one part suffers, all the parts suffer with it; if one part gets the glory, all the parts celebrate with it. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.27" osisID="1Cor.12.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You are the body of Christ and parts of each other. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.28" osisID="1Cor.12.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the church, God has appointed first apostles, second prophets, third teachers, then miracles, then gifts of healing, the ability to help others, leadership skills, different kinds of tongues. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.29" osisID="1Cor.12.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All aren’t apostles, are they? All aren’t prophets, are they? All aren’t teachers, are they? All don’t perform miracles, do they? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.30" osisID="1Cor.12.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All don’t have gifts of healing, do they? All don’t speak in different tongues, do they? All don’t interpret, do they? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.12.31" osisID="1Cor.12.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Use your ambition to try to get the greater gifts. And I’m going to show you an even better way. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.13" osisID="1Cor.13" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="13"><div scope="1Cor.13.1-1Cor.13.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Love: the universal spiritual gift</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Cor.13.1" osisID="1Cor.13.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I speak in tongues of human beings and of angels but I don’t have love, I’m a clanging gong or a clashing cymbal. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.2" osisID="1Cor.13.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I have the gift of prophecy and I know all the mysteries and everything else, and if I have such complete faith that I can move mountains but I don’t have love, I’m nothing. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.3" osisID="1Cor.13.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I give away everything that I have and hand over my own body to feel good about what I’ve done but I don’t have love, I receive no benefit whatsoever. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.13.4" osisID="1Cor.13.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Love is patient, love is kind, it isn’t jealous, it doesn’t brag, it isn’t arrogant, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.5" osisID="1Cor.13.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">it isn’t rude, it doesn’t seek its own advantage, it isn’t irritable, it doesn’t keep a record of complaints, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.6" osisID="1Cor.13.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">it isn’t happy with injustice, but it is happy with the truth. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.7" osisID="1Cor.13.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Love puts up with all things, trusts in all things, hopes for all things, endures all things. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.13.8" osisID="1Cor.13.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Love never fails. As for prophecies, they will be brought to an end. As for tongues, they will stop. As for knowledge, it will be brought to an end. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.9" osisID="1Cor.13.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We know in part and we prophesy in part; </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.10" osisID="1Cor.13.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but when the perfect comes, what is partial will be brought to an end. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.11" osisID="1Cor.13.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When I was a child, I used to speak like a child, reason like a child, think like a child. But now that I have become a man, I’ve put an end to childish things. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.12" osisID="1Cor.13.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now we see a reflection in a mirror; then we will see face-to-face. Now I know partially, but then I will know completely in the same way that I have been completely known. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.13.13" osisID="1Cor.13.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now faith, hope, and love remain—these three things—and the greatest of these is love. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.14" osisID="1Cor.14" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="14"><div scope="1Cor.14.1-1Cor.14.40" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Spiritual gifts and church order</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Cor.14.1" osisID="1Cor.14.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pursue love, and use your ambition to try to get spiritual gifts but especially so that you might prophesy. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.2" osisID="1Cor.14.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is because those who speak in a tongue don’t speak to people but to God; no one understands it—they speak mysteries by the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.3" osisID="1Cor.14.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who prophesy speak to people, building them up, and giving them encouragement and comfort. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.4" osisID="1Cor.14.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People who speak in a tongue build up themselves; those who prophesy build up the church. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.5" osisID="1Cor.14.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I wish that all of you spoke in tongues, but I’d rather you could prophesy. Those who prophesy are more important than those who speak in tongues, unless they are able to interpret them so that the church might be built up. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.6" osisID="1Cor.14.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After all, brothers and sisters, if I come to you speaking in tongues, how will I help you unless I speak to you with a revelation, some knowledge, a prophecy, or a teaching? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.7" osisID="1Cor.14.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Likewise, things that aren’t alive like a harp or a lyre can make a sound, but if there aren’t different notes in the sounds they make, how will the tune from the harp or the lyre be recognized? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.8" osisID="1Cor.14.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And if a trumpet call is unrecognizable, then who will prepare for battle? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.9" osisID="1Cor.14.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s the same way with you: If you don’t use language that is easy to understand when you speak in a tongue, then how will anyone understand what is said? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.10" osisID="1Cor.14.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It will be as if you are speaking into the air! There are probably many language families in the world, and none of them are without meaning. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.11" osisID="1Cor.14.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So if I don’t know the meaning of the language, then I will be like a foreigner to those who speak it, and they will be like foreigners to me. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.12" osisID="1Cor.14.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The same holds true for you: since you are ambitious for spiritual gifts, use your ambition to try to work toward being the best at building up the church. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.14.13" osisID="1Cor.14.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, those who speak in a tongue should pray to be able to interpret. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.14" osisID="1Cor.14.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I pray in a tongue, my spirit prays but my mind isn’t productive. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.15" osisID="1Cor.14.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What should I do? I’ll pray in the Spirit, but I’ll pray with my mind too; I’ll sing a psalm in the Spirit, but I’ll sing the psalm with my mind too. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.16" osisID="1Cor.14.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After all, if you praise God in the Spirit, how will the people who aren’t trained in that language say <q type="x-complete">Amen!</q> to your thanksgiving, when they don’t know what you are saying? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.17" osisID="1Cor.14.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You may offer a beautiful prayer of thanksgiving, but the other person is not being built up. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.18" osisID="1Cor.14.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I thank God that I speak in tongues more than all of you. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.19" osisID="1Cor.14.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But in the church I’d rather speak five words in my right mind than speak thousands of words in a tongue so that I can teach others. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.14.20" osisID="1Cor.14.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, don’t be like children in the way you think. Well, be babies when it comes to evil, but be adults in your thinking. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.21" osisID="1Cor.14.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the Law it is written: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">I will speak to this people with foreign languages and foreigners’ lips, but they will not even listen to me this way</hi>,<note osisRef="1Cor.14.21" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.14.21!note.p">Isa 28:11-12</note> says the Lord. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.22" osisID="1Cor.14.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, tongues are a sign for those who don’t believe, not for those who believe. But prophecy is a sign for believers, not for those who don’t believe. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.23" osisID="1Cor.14.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So suppose that the whole church is meeting and everyone is speaking in tongues. If people come in who are outsiders or unbelievers, won’t they say that you are out of your minds? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.24" osisID="1Cor.14.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if everyone is prophesying when an unbeliever or outsider comes in, they are tested by all and called to account by all. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.25" osisID="1Cor.14.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The secrets of their hearts are brought to light. When that happens, they will fall on their faces and worship God, proclaiming out loud that truly God is among you! </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.14.26" osisID="1Cor.14.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What is the outcome of this, brothers and sisters? When you meet together, each one has a psalm, a teaching, a revelation, a tongue, or an interpretation. All these things must be done to build up the church. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.27" osisID="1Cor.14.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If some speak in a tongue, then let two or at most three speak, one at a time, and someone must interpret. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.28" osisID="1Cor.14.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, if there is no interpreter, then they should keep quiet in the meeting. They should speak privately to themselves and to God. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.29" osisID="1Cor.14.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the case of prophets, let two or three speak and have the rest evaluate what is said. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.30" osisID="1Cor.14.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And if some revelation comes to someone else who is sitting down, the first one should be quiet. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.31" osisID="1Cor.14.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You can all prophesy one at a time so that everyone can learn and be encouraged. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.32" osisID="1Cor.14.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The spirits of prophets are under the control of the prophets. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.33" osisID="1Cor.14.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God isn’t a God of disorder but of peace. Like in all the churches of God’s people, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.34" osisID="1Cor.14.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">the women should be quiet during the meeting. They are not allowed to talk. Instead, they need to get under control, just as the Law says. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.35" osisID="1Cor.14.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If they want to learn something, they should ask their husbands at home. It is disgraceful for a woman to talk during the meeting. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.14.36" osisID="1Cor.14.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Did the word of God originate with you? Has it come only to you? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.37" osisID="1Cor.14.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If anyone thinks that they are prophets or <q type="x-complete">spiritual people,</q> then let them recognize that what I’m writing to you is the Lord’s command. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.38" osisID="1Cor.14.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If someone doesn’t recognize this, they aren’t recognized. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.39" osisID="1Cor.14.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, brothers and sisters, use your ambition to try to get the gift of prophecy, but don’t prevent speaking in tongues. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.14.40" osisID="1Cor.14.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everything should be done with dignity and in proper order. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.15" osisID="1Cor.15" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="15"><div scope="1Cor.15.1-1Cor.15.58" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The resurrection</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Cor.15.1" osisID="1Cor.15.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I want to call your attention to the good news that I preached to you, which you also received and in which you stand. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.2" osisID="1Cor.15.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You are being saved through it if you hold on to the message I preached to you, unless somehow you believed it for nothing. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.3" osisID="1Cor.15.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I passed on to you as most important what I also received: Christ died for our sins in line with the scriptures, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.4" osisID="1Cor.15.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">he was buried, and he rose on the third day in line with the scriptures. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.5" osisID="1Cor.15.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He appeared to Cephas, then to the Twelve, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.6" osisID="1Cor.15.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and then he appeared to more than five hundred brothers and sisters at once—most of them are still alive to this day, though some have died. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.7" osisID="1Cor.15.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then he appeared to James, then to all the apostles, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.8" osisID="1Cor.15.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and last of all he appeared to me, as if I were born at the wrong time. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.9" osisID="1Cor.15.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m the least important of the apostles. I don’t deserve to be called an apostle, because I harassed God’s church. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.10" osisID="1Cor.15.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I am what I am by God’s grace, and God’s grace hasn’t been for nothing. In fact, I have worked harder than all the others—that is, it wasn’t me but the grace of God that is with me. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.11" osisID="1Cor.15.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, whether you heard the message from me or them, this is what we preach and this is what you have believed. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.15.12" osisID="1Cor.15.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So if the message that is preached says that Christ has been raised from the dead, then how can some of you say, <q type="x-complete">There’s no resurrection of the dead</q>? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.13" osisID="1Cor.15.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If there’s no resurrection of the dead, then Christ hasn’t been raised either. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.14" osisID="1Cor.15.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If Christ hasn’t been raised, then our preaching is useless and your faith is useless. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.15" osisID="1Cor.15.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We are found to be false witnesses about God, because we testified against God that he raised Christ, when he didn’t raise him if it’s the case that the dead aren’t raised. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.16" osisID="1Cor.15.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If the dead aren’t raised, then Christ hasn’t been raised either. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.17" osisID="1Cor.15.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If Christ hasn’t been raised, then your faith is worthless; you are still in your sins, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.18" osisID="1Cor.15.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and what’s more, those who have died in Christ are gone forever. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.19" osisID="1Cor.15.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If we have a hope in Christ only in this life, then we deserve to be pitied more than anyone else. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.15.20" osisID="1Cor.15.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But in fact Christ has been raised from the dead. He’s the first crop of the harvest<note osisRef="1Cor.15.20" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.20!note.q">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">firstfruits</hi></note> of those who have died. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.21" osisID="1Cor.15.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since death came through a human being, the resurrection of the dead came through one too. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.22" osisID="1Cor.15.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way that everyone dies in Adam, so also everyone will be given life in Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.23" osisID="1Cor.15.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each event will happen in the right order: Christ, the first crop of the harvest,<note osisRef="1Cor.15.23" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.23!note.r">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">firstfruits</hi></note> then those who belong to Christ at his coming, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.24" osisID="1Cor.15.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and then the end, when Christ hands over the kingdom to God the Father, when he brings every form of rule, every authority and power to an end. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.25" osisID="1Cor.15.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It is necessary for him to rule until <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">he puts all enemies under his feet</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.15.25" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.25!note.s">Ps 110:1</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.26" osisID="1Cor.15.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Death is the last enemy to be brought to an end, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.27" osisID="1Cor.15.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">since he has brought everything under control under his feet. When it says that everything has been brought under his control, this clearly means everything except for the one who placed everything under his control. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.28" osisID="1Cor.15.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when all things have been brought under his control, then the Son himself will also be under the control of the one who gave him control over everything so that God may be all in all. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.15.29" osisID="1Cor.15.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Otherwise, what are those who are getting baptized for the dead doing? If the dead aren’t raised, then why are they being baptized for them? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.30" osisID="1Cor.15.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And what about us? Why are we in danger all day every day? </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.31" osisID="1Cor.15.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I swear by the pride I have in you in Christ Jesus our Lord, I’m facing death every day. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.32" osisID="1Cor.15.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From a human point of view, what good does it do me if I fought wild animals in Ephesus? If the dead aren’t raised, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">let’s eat and drink because tomorrow we’ll die</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.15.32" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.32!note.t">Isa 22:13</note> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.33" osisID="1Cor.15.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t be deceived, bad company corrupts good character. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.34" osisID="1Cor.15.34" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Sober up by acting like you should and don’t sin. Some of you are ignorant about God—I say this because you should be ashamed of yourselves! </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.15.35" osisID="1Cor.15.35" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But someone will say, <q type="x-complete">How are the dead raised? What kind of body will they have when they come back?</q> </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.36" osisID="1Cor.15.36" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Look, fool! When you put a seed into the ground, it doesn’t come back to life unless it dies. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.37" osisID="1Cor.15.37" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What you put in the ground doesn’t have the shape that it will have, but it’s a bare grain of wheat or some other seed. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.38" osisID="1Cor.15.38" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God gives it the sort of shape that he chooses, and he gives each of the seeds its own shape. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.39" osisID="1Cor.15.39" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All flesh isn’t alike. Humans have one kind of flesh, animals have another kind of flesh, birds have another kind of flesh, and fish have another kind. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.40" osisID="1Cor.15.40" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There are heavenly bodies and earthly bodies. The heavenly bodies have one kind of glory, and the earthly bodies have another kind of glory. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.41" osisID="1Cor.15.41" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The sun has one kind of glory, the moon has another kind of glory, and the stars have another kind of glory (but one star is different from another star in its glory). </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.42" osisID="1Cor.15.42" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s the same with the resurrection of the dead: a rotting body is put into the ground, but what is raised won’t ever decay. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.43" osisID="1Cor.15.43" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s degraded when it’s put into the ground, but it’s raised in glory. It’s weak when it’s put into the ground, but it’s raised in power. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.44" osisID="1Cor.15.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">It’s a physical body when it’s put into the ground, but it’s raised as a spiritual body. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.15.44" osisID="1Cor.15.44" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">If there’s a physical body, there’s also a spiritual body. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.45" osisID="1Cor.15.45" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So it is also written, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The first human, Adam, became a living person,</hi><note osisRef="1Cor.15.44" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.44!note.u">Gen 2:7</note> and the last Adam became a spirit that gives life. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.46" osisID="1Cor.15.46" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the physical body comes first, not the spiritual one—the spiritual body comes afterward. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.47" osisID="1Cor.15.47" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The first human was from the earth made from dust; the second human is from heaven. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.48" osisID="1Cor.15.48" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The nature of the person made of dust is shared by people who are made of dust, and the nature of the heavenly person is shared by heavenly people. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.49" osisID="1Cor.15.49" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We will look like<note osisRef="1Cor.15.49" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.49!note.v">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">bear the image of</hi></note> the heavenly person in the same way as we have looked like the person made from dust. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.15.50" osisID="1Cor.15.50" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what I’m saying, brothers and sisters: Flesh and blood can’t inherit the kingdom of heaven. Something that rots can’t inherit something that doesn’t decay. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.51" osisID="1Cor.15.51" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen, I’m telling you a secret: All of us won’t die, but we will all be changed—</verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.52" osisID="1Cor.15.52" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">in an instant, in the blink of an eye, at the final trumpet. The trumpet will blast, and the dead will be raised with bodies that won’t decay, and we will be changed. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.53" osisID="1Cor.15.53" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s necessary for this rotting body to be clothed with what can’t decay, and for the body that is dying to be clothed in what can’t die. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.54" osisID="1Cor.15.54" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">And when the rotting body has been clothed in what can’t decay, and the dying body has been clothed in what can’t die, then this statement in scripture will happen: </verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="1Cor.15.54" osisID="1Cor.15.54" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Death has been swallowed up by a victory</hi>.<note osisRef="1Cor.15.54" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.54!note.w">Isa 25:8</note> </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="1Cor.15.55" osisID="1Cor.15.55" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Where is your victory, Death? </hi></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="1Cor.15.55" osisID="1Cor.15.55" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Where is your sting, Death?</hi><note osisRef="1Cor.15.55" placement="inline" osisID="1Cor.15.55!note.x">Hos 13:14</note> </verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText">(<verse sID="1Cor.15.56" osisID="1Cor.15.56" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Death’s sting is sin, and the power of sin is the Law.) </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.57" osisID="1Cor.15.57" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Thanks be to God, who gives us this victory through our Lord Jesus Christ! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.15.58" osisID="1Cor.15.58" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As a result of all this, my loved brothers and sisters, you must stand firm, unshakable, excelling in the work of the Lord as always, because you know that your labor isn’t going to be for nothing in the Lord. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Cor.16" osisID="1Cor.16" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="16"><div scope="1Cor.16.1-1Cor.16.4" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Collection for Jerusalem</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart2"><verse sID="1Cor.16.1" osisID="1Cor.16.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Concerning the collection of money for God’s people: You should do what I have directed the churches in Galatia to do. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.2" osisID="1Cor.16.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the first day of the week, each of you should set aside whatever you can afford from what you earn so that the collection won’t be delayed until I come. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.3" osisID="1Cor.16.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then when I get there, I’ll send whomever you approve to Jerusalem with letters of recommendation to bring your gift. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.4" osisID="1Cor.16.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If it seems right for me to go too, they’ll travel with me. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.16.5-1Cor.16.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Plans to visit</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.16.5" osisID="1Cor.16.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’ll come to you after I go through Macedonia, and because I’m going through Macedonia, </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.6" osisID="1Cor.16.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I may stay with you or even spend the winter there in Corinth so that you can send me on my way to wherever I’m off to next. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.7" osisID="1Cor.16.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I don’t want to make a quick visit to you, since I hope to spend some time with you if the Lord lets it happen. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.8" osisID="1Cor.16.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’ll stay here in Ephesus until the Festival of Pentecost. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.9" osisID="1Cor.16.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In spite of the fact that there are many opponents, a big and productive opportunity has opened up for my mission here. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.16.10" osisID="1Cor.16.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If Timothy comes to you, be sure that he has no reason to be afraid while he’s with you, because he does the work of the Lord just like I do. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.11" osisID="1Cor.16.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So don’t let anyone disrespect him, but send him on in peace so he can join me. I’m waiting for him along with the brothers and sisters. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.12" osisID="1Cor.16.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Concerning Apollos our brother: I strongly encouraged him to visit you with the brothers and sisters, but he didn’t want to go now. He’ll come when he has an opportunity. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Cor.16.13-1Cor.16.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final greeting</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.16.13" osisID="1Cor.16.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Stay awake, stand firm in your faith, be brave, be strong. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.14" osisID="1Cor.16.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everything should be done in love. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.16.15" osisID="1Cor.16.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I encourage you to do something else. You know that the people in Stephanas’ household were the first crop of the harvest to come from the mission to Achaia. They have dedicated themselves to the service of God’s people. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.16" osisID="1Cor.16.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So accept the authority of people like them and of anyone who cooperates and works hard. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.17" osisID="1Cor.16.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m so happy that Stephanas, Fortunatus, and Achaicus have arrived; they’ve made up for my missing you. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.18" osisID="1Cor.16.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Indeed they’ve provided my spirit and yours with a much-needed rest. Therefore, give them proper recognition. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.16.19" osisID="1Cor.16.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The churches in the province of Asia greet you. Aquila and Prisca greet you warmly in the Lord, together with the church that meets in their house. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.20" osisID="1Cor.16.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the brothers and sisters greet you. You in turn should greet each other with a holy kiss. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.21" osisID="1Cor.16.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Here is my greeting in my own handwriting—Paul. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Cor.16.22" osisID="1Cor.16.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A curse on anyone who doesn’t love the Lord. Come, Lord! </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.23" osisID="1Cor.16.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The grace of the Lord Jesus be with you. </verse><verse sID="1Cor.16.24" osisID="1Cor.16.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My love is with all of you in Christ Jesus. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>