<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Galatians</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="Gal"><chapter sID="Gal.1" osisID="Gal.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Galatians</title><div scope="Gal.1.1-Gal.1.5" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Gal.1.1" osisID="Gal.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From Paul, an apostle who is not sent from human authority or commissioned through human agency, but sent through Jesus Christ and God the Father who raised him from the dead; </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.2" osisID="Gal.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">and from all the brothers and sisters with me. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Gal.1.2" osisID="Gal.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">To the churches in Galatia. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Gal.1.3" osisID="Gal.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Grace and peace to you from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.4" osisID="Gal.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He gave himself for our sins, so he could deliver us from this present evil age, according to the will of our God and Father. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.5" osisID="Gal.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">To God be the glory forever and always! Amen. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.1.6-Gal.1.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The gospel challenged in Galatia</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.1.6" osisID="Gal.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m amazed that you are so quickly deserting the one who called you by the grace of Christ to follow another gospel. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.7" osisID="Gal.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s not really another gospel, but certain people are confusing you and they want to change the gospel of Christ. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.8" osisID="Gal.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, even if we ourselves or a heavenly angel should ever preach anything different from what we preached to you, they should be under a curse. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.9" osisID="Gal.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m repeating what we’ve said before: if anyone preaches something different from what you received, they should be under a curse! </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.1.10-Gal.1.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s leadership</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.1.10" osisID="Gal.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Am I trying to win over human beings or God? Or am I trying to please people? If I were still trying to please people, I wouldn’t be Christ’s slave. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.11" osisID="Gal.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I want you to know that the gospel I preached isn’t human in origin. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.12" osisID="Gal.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I didn’t receive it or learn it from a human. It came through a revelation from Jesus Christ. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.1.13" osisID="Gal.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You heard about my previous life in Judaism, how severely I harassed God’s church and tried to destroy it. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.14" osisID="Gal.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I advanced in Judaism beyond many of my peers, because I was much more militant about the traditions of my ancestors. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.15" osisID="Gal.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But God had set me apart from birth and called me through his grace. He was pleased </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.16" osisID="Gal.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">to reveal his Son to me, so that I might preach about him to the Gentiles. I didn’t immediately consult with any human being. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.17" osisID="Gal.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I didn’t go up to Jerusalem to see the men who were apostles before me either, but I went away into Arabia and I returned again to Damascus. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.18" osisID="Gal.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to visit Cephas and stayed with him fifteen days. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.19" osisID="Gal.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But I didn’t see any other of the apostles except James the brother of the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.20" osisID="Gal.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Before God, I’m not lying about the things that I’m writing to you! </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.21" osisID="Gal.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then I went into the regions of Syria and Cilicia, </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.22" osisID="Gal.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but I wasn’t known personally by the Christian churches in Judea. </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.23" osisID="Gal.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They only heard a report about me: <q type="x-complete">The man who used to harass us now preaches the faith that he once tried to destroy.</q> </verse><verse sID="Gal.1.24" osisID="Gal.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So they were glorifying God because of me. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Gal.2" osisID="Gal.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="Gal.2.1-Gal.2.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Confirmation of Paul’s leadership</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Gal.2.1" osisID="Gal.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then after fourteen years I went up to Jerusalem again with Barnabas, and I took Titus along also. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.2" osisID="Gal.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I went there because of a revelation, and I laid out the gospel that I preach to the Gentiles for them. But I did it privately with the influential leaders to make sure that I wouldn’t be working or that I hadn’t worked for nothing. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.3" osisID="Gal.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, not even Titus, who was with me and who was a Greek, was required to be circumcised. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.4" osisID="Gal.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But false brothers and sisters, who were brought in secretly, slipped in to spy on our freedom, which we have in Christ Jesus, and to make us slaves. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.5" osisID="Gal.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We didn’t give in and submit to them for a single moment, so that the truth of the gospel would continue to be with you. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.2.6" osisID="Gal.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The influential leaders didn’t add anything to what I was preaching—and whatever they were makes no difference to me, because God doesn’t show favoritism. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.7" osisID="Gal.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But on the contrary, they saw that I had been given the responsibility to preach the gospel to the people who aren’t circumcised, just as Peter had been to the circumcised. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.8" osisID="Gal.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who empowered Peter to become an apostle to the circumcised empowered me also to be one to the Gentiles. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.9" osisID="Gal.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">James, Cephas, and John, who are considered to be key leaders, shook hands with me and Barnabas as equals when they recognized the grace that was given to me. So it was agreed that we would go to the Gentiles, while they continue to go to the people who were circumcised. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.10" osisID="Gal.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They asked only that we would remember the poor, which was certainly something I was willing to do. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.2.11-Gal.2.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The Jewish-Gentile controversy</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.2.11" osisID="Gal.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when Cephas came to Antioch, I opposed him to his face, because he was wrong. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.12" osisID="Gal.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He had been eating with the Gentiles before certain people came from James. But when they came, he began to back out and separate himself, because he was afraid of the people who promoted circumcision. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.13" osisID="Gal.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And the rest of the Jews also joined him in this hypocrisy so that even Barnabas got carried away with them in their hypocrisy. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.14" osisID="Gal.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when I saw that they weren’t acting consistently with the truth of the gospel, I said to Cephas in front of everyone, <q type="x-complete">If you, though you’re a Jew, live like a Gentile and not like a Jew, how can you require the Gentiles to live like Jews?</q> </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.2.15" osisID="Gal.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We are born Jews—we’re not Gentile sinners. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.16" osisID="Gal.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, we know that a person isn’t made righteous by the works of the Law but rather through the faithfulness of Jesus Christ. We ourselves believed in Christ Jesus so that we could be made righteous by the faithfulness of Christ and not by the works of the Law—because no one will be made righteous by the works of the Law. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.17" osisID="Gal.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if it is discovered that we ourselves are sinners while we are trying to be made righteous in Christ, then is Christ a servant of sin? Absolutely not! </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.18" osisID="Gal.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If I rebuild the very things that I tore down, I show that I myself am breaking the Law. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.19" osisID="Gal.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I died to the Law through the Law, so that I could live for God. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.20" osisID="Gal.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I have been crucified with Christ and I no longer live, but Christ lives in me. And the life that I now live in my body, I live by faith, indeed, by the faithfulness of God’s Son, who loved me and gave himself for me. </verse><verse sID="Gal.2.21" osisID="Gal.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I don’t ignore the grace of God, because if we become righteous through the Law, then Christ died for no purpose. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Gal.3" osisID="Gal.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="Gal.3.1-Gal.3.5" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Works versus the Spirit</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Gal.3.1" osisID="Gal.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You irrational Galatians! Who put a spell on you? Jesus Christ was put on display as crucified before your eyes! </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.2" osisID="Gal.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I just want to know this from you: Did you receive the Spirit by doing the works of the Law or by believing what you heard? </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.3" osisID="Gal.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Are you so irrational? After you started with the Spirit, are you now finishing up with your own human effort? </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.4" osisID="Gal.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Did you experience so much for nothing? I wonder if it really was for nothing. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.5" osisID="Gal.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So does the one providing you with the Spirit and working miracles among you do this by you doing the works of the Law or by you believing what you heard? </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.3.6-Gal.3.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Abraham: an example of righteousness</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.3.6" osisID="Gal.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Understand that in the same way that Abraham <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">believed God and it was credited to him as righteousness,</hi><note osisRef="Gal.3.6" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.3.6!note.a">Gen 15:6</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.7" osisID="Gal.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">those who believe are the children of Abraham. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.8" osisID="Gal.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when it saw ahead of time that God would make the Gentiles righteous on the basis of faith, scripture preached the gospel in advance to Abraham: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">All the Gentiles will be blessed in you</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.3.8" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.3.8!note.b">Gen 12:3</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.9" osisID="Gal.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, those who believe are blessed together with Abraham who believed. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.3.10" osisID="Gal.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All those who rely on the works of the Law are under a curse, because it is written, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Everyone is cursed who does not keep on doing all the things that have been written in the Law scroll</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.3.10" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.3.10!note.c">Deut 27:26</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.11" osisID="Gal.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But since no one is made righteous by the Law as far as God is concerned, it is clear that <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">the righteous one will live on the basis of faith</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.3.11" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.3.11!note.d">Hab 2:4</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.12" osisID="Gal.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Law isn’t based on faith; rather, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">the one doing these things will live by them</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.3.12" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.3.12!note.e">Lev 18:5</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.13" osisID="Gal.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Christ redeemed us from the curse of the Law by becoming a curse for us—because it is written, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Everyone who is hung on a tree is cursed</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.3.13" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.3.13!note.f">Deut 21:23</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.14" osisID="Gal.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He redeemed us so that the blessing of Abraham would come to the Gentiles through Christ Jesus, and that we would receive the promise of the Spirit through faith. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.3.15" osisID="Gal.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, I’ll use an example from human experience. No one ignores or makes additions to a validated will. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.16" osisID="Gal.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The promises were made to Abraham and to his descendant. It doesn’t say, <q type="x-complete">and to the descendants,</q> as if referring to many rather than just one. It says, <q type="x-complete">and to your descendant,</q> who is Christ. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.17" osisID="Gal.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m saying this: the Law, which came four hundred thirty years later, doesn’t invalidate the agreement that was previously validated by God so that it cancels the promise. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.18" osisID="Gal.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If the inheritance were based upon the Law, it would no longer be from the promise. But God has given it graciously to Abraham through a promise. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.3.19-Gal.3.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The Law’s origin and purpose</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.3.19" osisID="Gal.3.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So why was the Law given? It was added because of offenses, until the descendant would come to whom the promise had been made. It was put in place through angels by the hand of a mediator. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.20" osisID="Gal.3.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now the mediator does not take one side; but God is one. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.21" osisID="Gal.3.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So, is the Law against the promises of God? Absolutely not! If a Law had been given that was able to give life, then righteousness would in fact have come from the Law. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.22" osisID="Gal.3.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But scripture locked up all things under sin, so that the promise based on the faithfulness of Jesus Christ might be given to those who have faith. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.23" osisID="Gal.3.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Before faith came, we were guarded under the Law, locked up until faith that was coming would be revealed, </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.24" osisID="Gal.3.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so that the Law became our custodian until Christ so that we might be made righteous by faith. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.3.25-Gal.3.29" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">God’s children are heirs in Christ</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.3.25" osisID="Gal.3.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now that faith has come, we are no longer under a custodian. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.3.26" osisID="Gal.3.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You are all God’s children through faith in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.27" osisID="Gal.3.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All of you who were baptized into Christ have clothed yourselves with Christ. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.28" osisID="Gal.3.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There is neither Jew nor Greek; there is neither slave nor free; nor is there male and female, for you are all one in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="Gal.3.29" osisID="Gal.3.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now if you belong to Christ, then indeed you are Abraham’s descendants, heirs according to the promise. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Gal.4" osisID="Gal.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="Gal.4.1-Gal.4.7" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Gal.4.1" osisID="Gal.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m saying that as long as the heirs are minors, they are no different from slaves, though they really are the owners of everything. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.2" osisID="Gal.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, they are placed under trustees and guardians until the date set by the parents. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.3" osisID="Gal.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, when we were minors, we were also enslaved by this world’s system. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.4" osisID="Gal.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when the fulfillment of the time came, God sent his Son, born through a woman, and born under the Law. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.5" osisID="Gal.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This was so he could redeem those under the Law so that we could be adopted. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.6" osisID="Gal.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because you are sons and daughters, God sent the Spirit of his Son into our hearts, crying, <q type="x-complete">Abba, Father!</q> </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.7" osisID="Gal.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, you are no longer a slave but a son or daughter, and if you are his child, then you are also an heir through God. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.4.8-Gal.4.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s concern for the Galatians</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.4.8" osisID="Gal.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the time, when you didn’t know God, you were enslaved by things that aren’t gods by nature. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.9" osisID="Gal.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now, after knowing God (or rather, being known by God), how can you turn back again to the weak and worthless world system? Do you want to be slaves to it again? </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.10" osisID="Gal.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You observe religious days and months and seasons and years. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.11" osisID="Gal.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m afraid for you! Perhaps my hard work for you has been for nothing. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.4.12" osisID="Gal.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I beg you to be like me, brothers and sisters, because I have become like you! You haven’t wronged me. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.13" osisID="Gal.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know that I first preached the gospel to you because of an illness. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.14" osisID="Gal.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Though my poor health burdened you, you didn’t look down on me or reject me, but you welcomed me as if I were an angel from God, or as if I were Christ Jesus! </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.15" osisID="Gal.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Where then is the great attitude that you had? I swear that, if possible, you would have dug out your eyes and given them to me. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.16" osisID="Gal.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, have I become your enemy by telling you the truth? </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.17" osisID="Gal.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They are so concerned about you, though not with good intentions. Rather, they want to shut you out so that you would run after them. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.18" osisID="Gal.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, it’s always good to have people concerned about you with good intentions, and not just when I’m there with you. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.19" osisID="Gal.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My little children, I’m going through labor pains again until Christ is formed in you. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.20" osisID="Gal.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But I wish I could be with you now and change how I sound, because I’m at a loss about you. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.4.21-Gal.4.31" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Slave versus free</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.4.21" osisID="Gal.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tell me—those of you who want to be under the Law—don’t you listen to the Law? </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.22" osisID="Gal.4.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s written that Abraham had two sons, one by the slave woman and one by the free woman. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.23" osisID="Gal.4.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The son by the slave woman was conceived the normal way, but the son by the free woman was conceived through a promise. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.24" osisID="Gal.4.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These things are an allegory: the women are two covenants. One is from Mount Sinai, which gives birth to slave children; this is Hagar. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.25" osisID="Gal.4.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hagar is Mount Sinai in Arabia, and she corresponds to the present-day Jerusalem, because the city is in slavery with her children. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.26" osisID="Gal.4.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the Jerusalem that is above is free, and she is our mother. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.27" osisID="Gal.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">It’s written: </verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Gal.4.27" osisID="Gal.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Rejoice, barren woman, you who have not given birth</hi>. </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Gal.4.27" osisID="Gal.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Break out with a shout, you who have not suffered labor pains; </hi></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Gal.4.27" osisID="Gal.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">because the woman who has been deserted will have many more children </hi></verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Gal.4.27" osisID="Gal.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">than the woman who has a husband</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.4.27" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.4.27!note.g">Isa 54:1</note> </verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.4.28" osisID="Gal.4.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, you are children of the promise like Isaac. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.29" osisID="Gal.4.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But just as it was then, so it is now also: the one who was conceived the normal way harassed the one who was conceived by the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.30" osisID="Gal.4.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But what does the scripture say? <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Throw out the slave woman and her son, because the slave woman’s son won’t share the inheritance with the free woman’s son</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.4.30" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.4.30!note.h">Gen 21:10</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.4.31" osisID="Gal.4.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, brothers and sisters, we aren’t the slave woman’s children, but we are the free woman’s children. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Gal.5" osisID="Gal.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="Gal.5.1-Gal.5.1" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Gal.5.1" osisID="Gal.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Christ has set us free for freedom. Therefore, stand firm and don’t submit to the bondage of slavery again. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.5.2-Gal.5.15" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Arguments against being circumcised</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.5.2" osisID="Gal.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Look, I, Paul, am telling you that if you have yourselves circumcised, having Christ won’t help you. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.3" osisID="Gal.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Again I swear to every man who has himself circumcised that he is required to do the whole Law. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.4" osisID="Gal.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You people who are trying to be made righteous by the Law have been estranged from Christ. You have fallen away from grace! </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.5" osisID="Gal.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We eagerly wait for the hope of righteousness through the Spirit by faith. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.6" osisID="Gal.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Being circumcised or not being circumcised doesn’t matter in Christ Jesus, but faith working through love does matter. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.5.7" osisID="Gal.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You were running well—who stopped you from obeying the truth? </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.8" osisID="Gal.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This line of reasoning doesn’t come from the one who calls you. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.9" osisID="Gal.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A little yeast works through the whole lump of dough. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.10" osisID="Gal.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m convinced about you in the Lord that you won’t think any other way. But the one who is confusing you will pay the penalty, whoever that may be. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.11" osisID="Gal.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, if I’m still preaching circumcision, why am I still being harassed? In that case, the offense of the cross would be canceled. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.12" osisID="Gal.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I wish that the ones who are upsetting you would castrate themselves! </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.5.13" osisID="Gal.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You were called to freedom, brothers and sisters; only don’t let this freedom be an opportunity to indulge your selfish impulses, but serve each other through love. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.14" osisID="Gal.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the Law has been fulfilled in a single statement: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Love your neighbor as yourself</hi>.<note osisRef="Gal.5.14" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.5.14!note.i">Lev 19:18</note> </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.15" osisID="Gal.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if you bite and devour each other, be careful that you don’t get eaten up by each other! </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.5.16-Gal.5.26" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Two different ways of living</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.5.16" osisID="Gal.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I say be guided by the Spirit and you won’t carry out your selfish desires. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.17" osisID="Gal.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A person’s selfish desires are set against the Spirit, and the Spirit is set against one’s selfish desires. They are opposed to each other, so you shouldn’t do whatever you want to do. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.18" osisID="Gal.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if you are being led by the Spirit, you aren’t under the Law. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.19" osisID="Gal.5.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The actions that are produced by selfish motives are obvious, since they include sexual immorality, moral corruption, doing whatever feels good, </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.20" osisID="Gal.5.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">idolatry, drug use and casting spells, hate, fighting, obsession, losing your temper, competitive opposition, conflict, selfishness, group rivalry, </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.21" osisID="Gal.5.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">jealousy, drunkenness, partying, and other things like that. I warn you as I have already warned you, that those who do these kinds of things won’t inherit God’s kingdom. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.5.22" osisID="Gal.5.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.23" osisID="Gal.5.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">gentleness, and self-control. There is no law against things like this. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.24" osisID="Gal.5.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who belong to Christ Jesus have crucified self with its passions and its desires. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.5.25" osisID="Gal.5.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If we live by the Spirit, let’s follow the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="Gal.5.26" osisID="Gal.5.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Let’s not become arrogant, make each other angry, or be jealous of each other. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Gal.6" osisID="Gal.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="Gal.6.1-Gal.6.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Caring and sharing</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Gal.6.1" osisID="Gal.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, if a person is caught doing something wrong, you who are spiritual should restore someone like this with a spirit of gentleness. Watch out for yourselves so you won’t be tempted too. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.2" osisID="Gal.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Carry each other’s burdens and so you will fulfill the law of Christ. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.3" osisID="Gal.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If anyone thinks they are important when they aren’t, they’re fooling themselves. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.4" osisID="Gal.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each person should test their own work and be happy with doing a good job and not compare themselves with others. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.5" osisID="Gal.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Each person will have to carry their own load. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.6.6" osisID="Gal.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who are taught the word should share all good things with their teacher. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.7" osisID="Gal.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Make no mistake, God is not mocked. A person will harvest what they plant. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.8" osisID="Gal.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who plant only for their own benefit will harvest devastation from their selfishness, but those who plant for the benefit of the Spirit will harvest eternal life from the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.9" osisID="Gal.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Let’s not get tired of doing good, because in time we’ll have a harvest if we don’t give up. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.10" osisID="Gal.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, let’s work for the good of all whenever we have an opportunity, and especially for those in the household of faith. </verse></p></div><div scope="Gal.6.11-Gal.6.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final greeting</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.6.11" osisID="Gal.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Look at the large letters I’m making with my own handwriting! </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.12" osisID="Gal.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whoever wants to look good by human standards will try to get you to be circumcised, but only so they won’t be harassed for the cross of Christ. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.13" osisID="Gal.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who are circumcised don’t observe the Law themselves, but they want you to be circumcised, so they can boast about your physical body.<note osisRef="Gal.6.13" placement="inline" osisID="Gal.6.13!note.j">In Gk the word traditionally rendered as <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">flesh </hi>is rendered here as <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">physical body</hi>, but it has a wide range of meaning. Gal 5:13-25; 6:8, 12 contain nine close occurrences of the same word in Gk, but it is rendered as <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">selfish </hi>in regard to impulses, desires, motives, or benefit, and <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">human standards </hi>in 6:12.</note> </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.6.14" osisID="Gal.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But as for me, God forbid that I should boast about anything except for the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ. The world has been crucified to me through him, and I have been crucified to the world. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.15" osisID="Gal.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Being circumcised or not being circumcised doesn’t mean anything. What matters is a new creation. </verse><verse sID="Gal.6.16" osisID="Gal.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May peace and mercy be on whoever follows this rule and on God’s Israel. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.6.17" osisID="Gal.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From now on, no one should bother me because I bear the marks of Jesus on my body. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Gal.6.18" osisID="Gal.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, may the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>