<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Ephesians</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="Eph"><chapter sID="Eph.1" osisID="Eph.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Ephesians</title><div scope="Eph.1.1-Eph.1.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Eph.1.1" osisID="Eph.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">From Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by God’s will. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Eph.1.1" osisID="Eph.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">To the holy and faithful people in Christ Jesus in Ephesus.<note osisRef="Eph.1.1" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.1.1!note.a">The location of Ephesus was added in some later manuscripts, probably to make the opening of this letter similar to the others in the collection of Paul’s letters.</note> </verse></p><p type="x-CEBOffsetIndent"><verse sID="Eph.1.2" osisID="Eph.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Grace and peace to you from God our Father and our Lord Jesus Christ. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.1.3-Eph.1.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The believers’ blessings</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.1.3" osisID="Eph.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Bless the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ! He has blessed us in Christ with every spiritual blessing that comes from heaven. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.4" osisID="Eph.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God chose us in Christ to be holy and blameless in God’s presence before the creation of the world. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.5" osisID="Eph.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God destined us to be his adopted children through Jesus Christ because of his love. This was according to his goodwill and plan </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.6" osisID="Eph.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and to honor his glorious grace that he has given to us freely through the Son whom he loves. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.7" osisID="Eph.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We have been ransomed through his Son’s blood, and we have forgiveness for our failures based on his overflowing grace, </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.8" osisID="Eph.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">which he poured over us with wisdom and understanding. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.9" osisID="Eph.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God revealed his hidden design<note osisRef="Eph.1.9" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.1.9!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> to us, which is according to his goodwill and the plan that he intended to accomplish through his Son. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.10" osisID="Eph.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what God planned for the climax of all times:<note osisRef="Eph.1.10" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.1.10!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the fullness of times</hi></note> to bring all things together in Christ, the things in heaven along with the things on earth. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.11" osisID="Eph.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We have also received an inheritance in Christ. We were destined by the plan of God, who accomplishes everything according to his design. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.12" osisID="Eph.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We are called to be an honor to God’s glory because we were the first to hope in Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.13" osisID="Eph.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You too heard the word of truth in Christ, which is the good news of your salvation. You were sealed with the promised Holy Spirit because you believed in Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.14" osisID="Eph.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Holy Spirit is the down payment on our inheritance, which is applied toward our redemption as God’s own people, resulting in the honor of God’s glory. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.1.15-Eph.1.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s prayer for the Ephesians</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.1.15" osisID="Eph.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since I heard about your faith in the Lord Jesus and your love for all God’s people, this is the reason that </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.16" osisID="Eph.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I don’t stop giving thanks to God for you when I remember you in my prayers. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.17" osisID="Eph.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I pray that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, will give you a spirit of wisdom and revelation that makes God known to you. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.18" osisID="Eph.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I pray that the eyes of your heart will have enough light to see what is the hope of God’s call, what is the richness of God’s glorious inheritance among believers, </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.19" osisID="Eph.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and what is the overwhelming greatness of God’s power that is working among us believers. This power is conferred by the energy of God’s powerful strength. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.20" osisID="Eph.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God’s power was at work in Christ when God raised him from the dead and sat him at God’s right side in the heavens, </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.21" osisID="Eph.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">far above every ruler and authority and power and angelic power, any power that might be named not only now but in the future. </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.22" osisID="Eph.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God put everything under Christ’s feet and made him head of everything in the church, </verse><verse sID="Eph.1.23" osisID="Eph.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">which is his body. His body, the church, is the fullness of Christ, who fills everything in every way. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Eph.2" osisID="Eph.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="Eph.2.1-Eph.2.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Saved from sin to life</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Eph.2.1" osisID="Eph.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At one time you were like a dead person because of the things you did wrong and your offenses against God. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.2" osisID="Eph.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You used to act like most people in our world do. You followed the rule of a destructive spiritual power. This is the spirit of disobedience to God’s will that is now at work in persons whose lives are characterized by disobedience. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.3" osisID="Eph.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At one time you were like those persons. All of you used to do whatever felt good and whatever you thought you wanted so that you were children headed for punishment just like everyone else. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.2.4" osisID="Eph.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><hi type="super">-</hi></verse><verse sID="Eph.2.5" osisID="Eph.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, God is rich in mercy. He brought us to life with Christ while we were dead as a result of those things that we did wrong. He did this because of the great love that he has for us. You are saved by God’s grace! </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.6" osisID="Eph.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And God raised us up and seated us in the heavens with Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.7" osisID="Eph.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God did this to show future generations the greatness of his grace by the goodness that God has shown us in Christ Jesus. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.2.8" osisID="Eph.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You are saved by God’s grace because of your faith.<note osisRef="Eph.2.8" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.2.8!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">through his faithfulness</hi></note> This salvation is God’s gift. It’s not something you possessed. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.9" osisID="Eph.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s not something you did that you can be proud of. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.10" osisID="Eph.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, we are God’s accomplishment, created in Christ Jesus to do good things. God planned for these good things to be the way that we live our lives. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.2.11-Eph.2.22" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The reconciliation of God’s people</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.2.11" osisID="Eph.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So remember that once you were Gentiles by physical descent, who were called <q type="x-complete">uncircumcised</q> by Jews who are physically circumcised. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.12" osisID="Eph.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At that time you were without Christ. You were aliens rather than citizens of Israel, and strangers to the covenants of God’s promise. In this world you had no hope and no God. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.13" osisID="Eph.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now, thanks to Christ Jesus, you who once were so far away have been brought near by the blood of Christ. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.2.14" osisID="Eph.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Christ is our peace. He made both Jews and Gentiles into one group. With his body, he broke down the barrier of hatred that divided us. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.15" osisID="Eph.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He canceled the detailed rules of the Law so that he could create one new person out of the two groups, making peace. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.16" osisID="Eph.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He reconciled them both as one body to God by the cross, which ended the hostility to God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.2.17" osisID="Eph.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When he came, he announced the good news of peace to you who were far away from God and to those who were near. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.18" osisID="Eph.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We both have access to the Father through Christ by the one Spirit. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.19" osisID="Eph.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So now you are no longer strangers and aliens. Rather, you are fellow citizens with God’s people, and you belong to God’s household. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.20" osisID="Eph.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As God’s household, you are built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets with Christ Jesus himself as the cornerstone. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.21" osisID="Eph.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The whole building is joined together in him, and it grows up into a temple that is dedicated to the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Eph.2.22" osisID="Eph.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Christ is building you into a place where God lives through the Spirit. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Eph.3" osisID="Eph.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="Eph.3.1-Eph.3.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul, apostle to the Gentiles</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Eph.3.1" osisID="Eph.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why I, Paul, am a prisoner of Christ for you Gentiles. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.3.2" osisID="Eph.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You’ve heard, of course, about the responsibility to distribute God’s grace, which God gave to me for you, right? </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.3" osisID="Eph.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God showed me his secret plan<note osisRef="Eph.3.3" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.3.3!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> in a revelation, as I mentioned briefly before (</verse><verse sID="Eph.3.4" osisID="Eph.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">when you read this, you’ll understand my insight into the secret plan<note osisRef="Eph.3.4" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.3.4!note.f">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> about Christ). </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.5" osisID="Eph.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Earlier generations didn’t know this hidden plan that God has now revealed to his holy apostles and prophets through the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.6" osisID="Eph.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This plan is that the Gentiles would be coheirs and parts of the same body, and that they would share with the Jews in the promises of God in Christ Jesus through the gospel. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.7" osisID="Eph.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I became a servant of the gospel because of the grace that God showed me through the exercise of his power. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.3.8" osisID="Eph.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God gave his grace to me, the least of all God’s people, to preach the good news about the immeasurable riches of Christ to the Gentiles. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.9" osisID="Eph.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God sent me to reveal the secret plan<note osisRef="Eph.3.9" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.3.9!note.g">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> that had been hidden since the beginning of time by God, who created everything. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.10" osisID="Eph.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God’s purpose is now to show the rulers and powers in the heavens the many different varieties of his wisdom through the church. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.11" osisID="Eph.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This was consistent with the plan he had from the beginning of time that he accomplished through Christ Jesus our Lord. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.12" osisID="Eph.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In Christ we have bold and confident access to God through faith in him.<note osisRef="Eph.3.12" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.3.12!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">through his faithfulness</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.13" osisID="Eph.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, I ask you not to become discouraged by what I’m suffering for you, which is your glory. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.3.14-Eph.3.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s prayer for the Ephesians</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.3.14" osisID="Eph.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why I kneel before the Father. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.15" osisID="Eph.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Every ethnic group in heaven or on earth is recognized by him. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.16" osisID="Eph.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I ask that he will strengthen you in your inner selves from the riches of his glory through the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.17" osisID="Eph.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I ask that Christ will live in your hearts through faith. As a result of having strong roots in love, </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.18" osisID="Eph.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I ask that you’ll have the power to grasp love’s width and length, height and depth, together with all believers. </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.19" osisID="Eph.3.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I ask that you’ll know the love of Christ that is beyond knowledge so that you will be filled entirely with the fullness of God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.3.20" osisID="Eph.3.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Glory to God, who is able to do far beyond all that we could ask or imagine by his power at work within us; </verse><verse sID="Eph.3.21" osisID="Eph.3.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">glory to him in the church and in Christ Jesus for all generations, forever and always. Amen. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Eph.4" osisID="Eph.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="Eph.4.1-Eph.4.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Unity of the body of Christ</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Eph.4.1" osisID="Eph.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, as a prisoner for the Lord, I encourage you to live as people worthy of the call you received from God. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.2" osisID="Eph.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Conduct yourselves with all humility, gentleness, and patience. Accept each other with love, </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.3" osisID="Eph.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and make an effort to preserve the unity of the Spirit with the peace that ties you together. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.4" osisID="Eph.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You are one body and one spirit, just as God also called you in one hope. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.5" osisID="Eph.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There is one Lord, one faith, one baptism, </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.6" osisID="Eph.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and one God and Father of all, who is over all, through all, and in all. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.7" osisID="Eph.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God has given his grace to each one of us measured out by the gift that is given by Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.8" osisID="Eph.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That’s why scripture says, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">When he climbed up to the heights, he captured prisoners, and he gave gifts to people</hi>.<note osisRef="Eph.4.8" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.4.8!note.i">Ps 68:18</note> </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.9" osisID="Eph.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What does the phrase <q type="x-complete">he climbed up</q> mean if it doesn’t mean that he had first gone down into the lower regions, the earth? </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.10" osisID="Eph.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who went down is the same one who climbed up above all the heavens so that he might fill everything. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.11" osisID="Eph.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He gave some apostles, some prophets, some evangelists, and some pastors and teachers. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.12" osisID="Eph.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">His purpose was to equip God’s people for the work of serving and building up the body of Christ </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.13" osisID="Eph.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">until we all reach the unity of faith and knowledge of God’s Son. God’s goal is for us to become mature adults—to be fully grown, measured by the standard of the fullness of Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.14" osisID="Eph.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As a result, we aren’t supposed to be infants any longer who can be tossed and blown around by every wind that comes from teaching with deceitful scheming and the tricks people play to deliberately mislead others. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.15" osisID="Eph.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, by speaking the truth with love, let’s grow in every way into Christ, </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.16" osisID="Eph.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who is the head. The whole body grows from him, as it is joined and held together by all the supporting ligaments. The body makes itself grow in that it builds itself up with love as each one does their part. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.4.17-Eph.4.32" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The old and new life</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.17" osisID="Eph.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So I’m telling you this, and I insist on it in the Lord: you shouldn’t live your life like the Gentiles anymore. They base their lives on pointless thinking, </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.18" osisID="Eph.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and they are in the dark in their reasoning. They are disconnected from God’s life because of their ignorance and their closed hearts. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.19" osisID="Eph.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They are people who lack all sense of right and wrong, and who have turned themselves over to doing whatever feels good and to practicing every sort of corruption along with greed. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.20" osisID="Eph.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you didn’t learn that sort of thing from Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.21" osisID="Eph.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since you really listened to him and you were taught how the truth is in Jesus, </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.22" osisID="Eph.4.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">change the former way of life that was part of the person you once were, corrupted by deceitful desires. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.23" osisID="Eph.4.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Instead, renew the thinking in your mind by the Spirit </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.24" osisID="Eph.4.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and clothe yourself with the new person created according to God’s image in justice and true holiness. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.25" osisID="Eph.4.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, after you have gotten rid of lying, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Each of you must tell the truth to your neighbor</hi><note osisRef="Eph.4.25" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.4.25!note.j">Zech 8:16</note> because we are parts of each other in the same body. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.26" osisID="Eph.4.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Be angry without sinning.</hi><note osisRef="Eph.4.26" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.4.26!note.k">Ps 4:4</note> Don’t let the sun set on your anger. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.27" osisID="Eph.4.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t provide an opportunity for the devil. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.28" osisID="Eph.4.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Thieves should no longer steal. Instead, they should go to work, using their hands to do good so that they will have something to share with whoever is in need. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.4.29" osisID="Eph.4.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t let any foul words come out of your mouth. Only say what is helpful when it is needed for building up the community so that it benefits those who hear what you say. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.30" osisID="Eph.4.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t make the Holy Spirit of God unhappy—you were sealed by him for the day of redemption. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.31" osisID="Eph.4.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Put aside all bitterness, losing your temper, anger, shouting, and slander, along with every other evil. </verse><verse sID="Eph.4.32" osisID="Eph.4.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Be kind, compassionate, and forgiving to each other, in the same way God forgave you in Christ. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Eph.5" osisID="Eph.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="Eph.5.1-Eph.5.5" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Eph.5.1" osisID="Eph.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, imitate God like dearly loved children. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.2" osisID="Eph.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Live your life with love, following the example of Christ, who loved us and gave himself for us. He was a sacrificial offering that smelled sweet to God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.5.3" osisID="Eph.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Sexual immorality, and any kind of impurity or greed, shouldn’t even be mentioned among you, which is right for holy persons. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.4" osisID="Eph.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Obscene language, silly talk, or vulgar jokes aren’t acceptable for believers. Instead, there should be thanksgiving. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.5" osisID="Eph.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because you know for sure that persons who are sexually immoral, impure, or greedy—which happens when things become gods—those persons won’t inherit the kingdom of Christ and God. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.5.6-Eph.5.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Be children of light</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.5.6" osisID="Eph.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nobody should deceive you with stupid ideas. God’s anger comes down on those who are disobedient because of this kind of thing. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.7" osisID="Eph.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So you shouldn’t have anything to do with them. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.8" osisID="Eph.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You were once darkness, but now you are light in the Lord, so live your life as children of light. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.9" osisID="Eph.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Light produces fruit that consists of every sort of goodness, justice, and truth. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.10" osisID="Eph.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, test everything to see what’s pleasing to the Lord, </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.11" osisID="Eph.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and don’t participate in the unfruitful actions of darkness. Instead, you should reveal the truth about them. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.12" osisID="Eph.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s embarrassing to even talk about what certain persons do in secret. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.13" osisID="Eph.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But everything exposed to the light is revealed by the light. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.14" osisID="Eph.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everything that is revealed by the light is light. Therefore, it says, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Wake up, sleeper!</hi><note osisRef="Eph.5.14" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.5.14!note.l">Isa 26:19; 51:17; 52:1; 60:1</note> <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Get up from the dead,</hi><note osisRef="Eph.5.14" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.5.14!note.m">Isa 26:19</note> <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">and Christ will shine on you.</hi><note osisRef="Eph.5.14" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.5.14!note.n">Isa 60:1</note> </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.5.15-Eph.5.33" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Be filled with the Spirit</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.5.15" osisID="Eph.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So be careful to live your life wisely, not foolishly. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.16" osisID="Eph.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Take advantage of every opportunity because these are evil times. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.17" osisID="Eph.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, don’t be ignorant, but understand the Lord’s will. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.18" osisID="Eph.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t get drunk on wine, which produces depravity. Instead, be filled with the Spirit in the following ways: </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.19" osisID="Eph.5.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">speak to each other with psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs; sing and make music to the Lord in your hearts; </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.20" osisID="Eph.5.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">always give thanks to God the Father for everything in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ; </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.21" osisID="Eph.5.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and submit to each other out of respect for Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.22" osisID="Eph.5.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">For example, wives should submit to their husbands as if to the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.23" osisID="Eph.5.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A husband is the head of his wife like Christ is head of the church, that is, the savior of the body. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.24" osisID="Eph.5.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So wives submit to their husbands in everything like the church submits to Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.25" osisID="Eph.5.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for husbands, love your wives just like Christ loved the church and gave himself for her. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.26" osisID="Eph.5.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did this to make her holy by washing her in a bath of water with the word. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.27" osisID="Eph.5.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He did this to present himself with a splendid church, one without any sort of stain or wrinkle on her clothes, but rather one that is holy and blameless. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.28" osisID="Eph.5.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That’s how husbands ought to love their wives—in the same way as they do their own bodies. Anyone who loves his wife loves himself. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.29" osisID="Eph.5.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one ever hates his own body, but feeds it and takes care of it just like Christ does for the church </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.30" osisID="Eph.5.30" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">because we are parts of his body. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.31" osisID="Eph.5.31" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">This is why a man will leave his father and mother and be united with his wife, and the two of them will be one body</hi>.<note osisRef="Eph.5.31" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.5.31!note.o">Gen 2:24</note> </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.32" osisID="Eph.5.32" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Marriage is a significant allegory,<note osisRef="Eph.5.32" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.5.32!note.p">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> and I’m applying it to Christ and the church. </verse><verse sID="Eph.5.33" osisID="Eph.5.33" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In any case, as for you individually, each one of you should love his wife as himself, and wives should respect<note osisRef="Eph.5.33" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.5.33!note.q">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">fear</hi></note> their husbands. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Eph.6" osisID="Eph.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="Eph.6.1-Eph.6.9" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Eph.6.1" osisID="Eph.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for children, obey your parents in the Lord, because it is right. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.2" osisID="Eph.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The commandment <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Honor your father and mother </hi>is the first one with a promise attached: </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.3" osisID="Eph.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">so that things will go well for you, and you will live for a long time in the land</hi>.<note osisRef="Eph.6.3" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.6.3!note.r">Exod 20:12; Deut 5:16</note> </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.4" osisID="Eph.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for parents, don’t provoke your children to anger, but raise them with discipline and instruction about the Lord. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.6.5" osisID="Eph.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for slaves, obey your human masters with fear and trembling and with sincere devotion to Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.6" osisID="Eph.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t work to make yourself look good and try to flatter people, but act like slaves of Christ carrying out God’s will from the heart. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.7" osisID="Eph.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Serve your owners enthusiastically, as though you were serving the Lord and not human beings. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.8" osisID="Eph.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know that the Lord will reward every person who does what is right, whether that person is a slave or a free person. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.9" osisID="Eph.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for masters, treat your slaves in the same way. Stop threatening them, because you know that both you and your slaves have a master in heaven. He doesn’t distinguish between people on the basis of status. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.6.10-Eph.6.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Put on the armor of God</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.6.10" osisID="Eph.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Finally, be strengthened by the Lord and his powerful strength. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.11" osisID="Eph.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Put on God’s armor so that you can make a stand against the tricks of the devil. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.12" osisID="Eph.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We aren’t fighting against human enemies but against rulers, authorities, forces of cosmic darkness, and spiritual powers of evil in the heavens. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.13" osisID="Eph.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, pick up the full armor of God so that you can stand your ground on the evil day and after you have done everything possible to still stand. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.14" osisID="Eph.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So stand with the belt of truth around your waist, justice as your breastplate, </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.15" osisID="Eph.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and put shoes on your feet so that you are ready to spread the good news of peace. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.16" osisID="Eph.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Above all, carry the shield of faith so that you can extinguish the flaming arrows of the evil one. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.17" osisID="Eph.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Take the helmet of salvation and the sword of the Spirit, which is God’s word. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.6.18" osisID="Eph.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Offer prayers and petitions in the Spirit all the time. Stay alert by hanging in there and praying for all believers. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.19" osisID="Eph.6.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As for me, pray that when I open my mouth, I’ll get a message that confidently makes this secret plan<note osisRef="Eph.6.19" placement="inline" osisID="Eph.6.19!note.s">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> of the gospel known. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.20" osisID="Eph.6.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m an ambassador in chains for the sake of the gospel. Pray so that the Lord will give me the confidence to say what I have to say. </verse></p></div><div scope="Eph.6.21-Eph.6.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final greeting</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.6.21" osisID="Eph.6.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tychicus, my loved brother and faithful servant of the Lord, can inform you about my situation and what I’m doing. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.22" osisID="Eph.6.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’ve sent him for this reason—so that you will know about us. He can reassure you. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Eph.6.23" osisID="Eph.6.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May there be peace with the brothers and sisters as well as love with the faith that comes from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="Eph.6.24" osisID="Eph.6.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May grace be with all those who love our Lord Jesus Christ forever. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>