<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Colossians</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="Col"><chapter sID="Col.1" osisID="Col.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Colossians</title><div scope="Col.1.1-Col.1.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Col.1.1" osisID="Col.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by God’s will, and Timothy our brother. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Col.1.2" osisID="Col.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">To the holy and faithful brothers and sisters in Christ in Colossae. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting">Grace and peace to you from God our Father.</p></div><div scope="Col.1.3-Col.1.14" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Thanksgiving and prayer for the Colossians</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.1.3" osisID="Col.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We always give thanks to God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, when we pray for you. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.4" osisID="Col.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We’ve done this since we heard of your faith in Christ Jesus and your love for all God’s people. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.5" osisID="Col.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You have this faith and love because of the hope reserved for you in heaven. You previously heard about this hope through the true message, the good news, </verse><verse sID="Col.1.6" osisID="Col.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">which has come to you. This message has been bearing fruit and growing among you since the day you heard and truly understood God’s grace, in the same way that it is bearing fruit and growing in the whole world. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.7" osisID="Col.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You learned it from Epaphras, who is the fellow slave we love and Christ’s faithful minister for your sake. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.8" osisID="Col.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He informed us of your love in the Spirit. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.1.9" osisID="Col.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, since the day we heard about you, we haven’t stopped praying for you and asking for you to be filled with the knowledge of God’s will, with all wisdom and spiritual understanding. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.10" osisID="Col.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We’re praying this so that you can live lives that are worthy of the Lord and pleasing to him in every way: by producing fruit in every good work and growing in the knowledge of God; </verse><verse sID="Col.1.11" osisID="Col.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">by being strengthened through his glorious might so that you endure everything and have patience; </verse><verse sID="Col.1.12" osisID="Col.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and by giving thanks with joy to the Father. He made it so you could take part in the inheritance, in light granted to God’s holy people. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.13" osisID="Col.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He rescued us from the control of darkness and transferred us into the kingdom of the Son he loves. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.14" osisID="Col.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He set us free through the Son and forgave our sins. </verse></p></div><div scope="Col.1.15-Col.1.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Hymn about Christ’s work</title><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Col.1.15" osisID="Col.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">The Son is the image of the invisible God, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.15" osisID="Col.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">the one who is first over all creation,<note osisRef="Col.1.15" placement="inline" osisID="Col.1.15!note.a">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">firstborn of all creation</hi></note> </verse></l></lg><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Col.1.16" osisID="Col.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Because all things were created by him: </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.16" osisID="Col.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">both in the heavens and on the earth, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.16" osisID="Col.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">the things that are visible and the things that are invisible. </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText4"><verse sID="Col.1.16" osisID="Col.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">Whether they are thrones or powers, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText4"><verse sID="Col.1.16" osisID="Col.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">or rulers or authorities, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.16" osisID="Col.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">all things were created through him and for him. </verse></l></lg><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Col.1.17" osisID="Col.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He existed before all things, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.17" osisID="Col.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and all things are held together in him. </verse></l></lg><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Col.1.18" osisID="Col.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">He is the head of the body, the church, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Col.1.18" osisID="Col.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">who is the beginning, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.18" osisID="Col.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">the one who is firstborn from among the dead<note osisRef="Col.1.18" placement="inline" osisID="Col.1.18!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">first over the dead</hi></note> </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.18" osisID="Col.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">so that he might occupy the first place in everything. </verse></l></lg><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Col.1.19" osisID="Col.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because all the fullness of God was pleased to live in him, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.20" osisID="Col.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">and he reconciled all things to himself through him—</verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Col.1.20" osisID="Col.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">whether things on earth or in the heavens. </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText4"><verse sID="Col.1.20" osisID="Col.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">He brought peace through the blood of his cross. </verse></l></lg><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.1.21" osisID="Col.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Once you were alienated from God and you were enemies with him in your minds, which was shown by your evil actions. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.22" osisID="Col.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now he has reconciled you by his physical body through death, to present you before God as a people who are holy, faultless, and without blame. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.23" osisID="Col.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you need to remain well established and rooted in faith and not shift away from the hope given in the good news that you heard. This message has been preached throughout all creation under heaven. And I, Paul, became a servant of this good news. </verse></p></div><div scope="Col.1.24-Col.1.29" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s service for the church</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.1.24" osisID="Col.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now I’m happy to be suffering for you. I’m completing what is missing from Christ’s sufferings with my own body. I’m doing this for the sake of his body, which is the church. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.25" osisID="Col.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I became a servant of the church by God’s commission, which was given to me for you, in order to complete God’s word. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.26" osisID="Col.1.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m completing it with a secret plan<note osisRef="Col.1.26" placement="inline" osisID="Col.1.26!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> that has been hidden for ages and generations but which has now been revealed to his holy people. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.27" osisID="Col.1.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God wanted to make the glorious riches of this secret plan<note osisRef="Col.1.27" placement="inline" osisID="Col.1.27!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> known among the Gentiles, which is Christ living in you, the hope of glory. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.28" osisID="Col.1.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is what we preach as we warn and teach every person with all wisdom so that we might present each one mature in Christ. </verse><verse sID="Col.1.29" osisID="Col.1.29" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I work hard and struggle for this goal with his energy, which works in me powerfully. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Col.2" osisID="Col.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="Col.2.1-Col.2.5" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Col.2.1" osisID="Col.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I want you to know how much I struggle for you, for those in Laodicea, and for all who haven’t known me personally. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.2" osisID="Col.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My goal is that their hearts would be encouraged and united together in love so that they might have all the riches of assurance that come with understanding, so that they might have the knowledge of the secret plan<note osisRef="Col.2.2" placement="inline" osisID="Col.2.2!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> of God, namely Christ. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.3" osisID="Col.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the treasures of wisdom and knowledge are hidden in him. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.4" osisID="Col.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m telling you this so that no one deceives you with convincing arguments, </verse><verse sID="Col.2.5" osisID="Col.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">because even though I am absent physically, I’m with you in spirit. I’m happy to see the discipline and stability of your faith in Christ. </verse></p></div><div scope="Col.2.6-Col.2.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Error threatening the church</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.2.6" osisID="Col.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So live in Christ Jesus the Lord in the same way as you received him. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.7" osisID="Col.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Be rooted and built up in him, be established in faith, and overflow with thanksgiving just as you were taught. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.8" osisID="Col.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">See to it that nobody enslaves you with philosophy and foolish deception, which conform to human traditions and the way the world thinks and acts rather than Christ. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.9" osisID="Col.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All the fullness of deity lives in Christ’s body. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.10" osisID="Col.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And you have been filled by him, who is the head of every ruler and authority. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.11" osisID="Col.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You were also circumcised by him. This wasn’t performed by human hands—the whole body was removed through this circumcision by Christ. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.12" osisID="Col.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You were buried with him through baptism and raised with him through faith in the power of God, who raised him from the dead. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.13" osisID="Col.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When you were dead because of the things you had done wrong and because your body wasn’t circumcised, God made you alive with Christ and forgave all the things you had done wrong. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.14" osisID="Col.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He destroyed the record of the debt we owed, with its requirements that worked against us. He canceled it by nailing it to the cross. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.15" osisID="Col.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When he disarmed the rulers and authorities, he exposed them to public disgrace by leading them in a triumphal parade. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.2.16" osisID="Col.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So don’t let anyone judge you about eating or drinking or about a festival, a new moon observance, or sabbaths. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.17" osisID="Col.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These religious practices are only a shadow of what was coming—the body that cast the shadow is Christ. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.18" osisID="Col.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t let anyone who wants to practice harsh self-denial and worship angels rob you of the prize. They go into detail about what they have seen in visions and have become unjustifiably arrogant by their selfish way of thinking. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.19" osisID="Col.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They don’t stay connected to the head. The head nourishes and supports the whole body through the joints and ligaments, so the body grows with a growth that is from God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.2.20" osisID="Col.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If you died with Christ to the way the world thinks and acts, why do you submit to rules and regulations as though you were living in the world? </verse><verse sID="Col.2.21" osisID="Col.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-complete">Don’t handle!</q> <q type="x-complete">Don’t taste!</q> <q type="x-complete">Don’t touch!</q> </verse><verse sID="Col.2.22" osisID="Col.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All these things cease to exist when they are used. Such rules are human commandments and teachings. </verse><verse sID="Col.2.23" osisID="Col.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They look like they are wise with this self-made religion and their self-denial by the harsh treatment of the body, but they are no help against indulging in selfish immoral behavior. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Col.3" osisID="Col.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="Col.3.1-Col.3.25" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Your life hidden in Christ</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Col.3.1" osisID="Col.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, if you were raised with Christ, look for the things that are above where Christ is sitting at God’s right side. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.2" osisID="Col.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Think about the things above and not things on earth. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.3" osisID="Col.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You died, and your life is hidden with Christ in God. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.4" osisID="Col.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When Christ, who is your life, is revealed, then you also will be revealed with him in glory. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.3.5" osisID="Col.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So put to death the parts of your life that belong to the earth, such as sexual immorality, moral corruption, lust, evil desire, and greed (which is idolatry). </verse><verse sID="Col.3.6" osisID="Col.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The wrath of God is coming upon disobedient people because of these things. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.7" osisID="Col.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You used to live this way, when you were alive to these things. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.8" osisID="Col.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now set aside these things, such as anger, rage, malice, slander, and obscene language. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.9" osisID="Col.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t lie to each other. Take off the old human nature with its practices </verse><verse sID="Col.3.10" osisID="Col.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and put on the new nature, which is renewed in knowledge by conforming to the image of the one who created it. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.11" osisID="Col.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In this image there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcised nor uncircumcised, barbarian, Scythian, slave nor free, but Christ is all things and in all people. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.3.12" osisID="Col.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, as God’s choice, holy and loved, put on compassion, kindness, humility, gentleness, and patience. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.13" osisID="Col.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Be tolerant with each other and, if someone has a complaint against anyone, forgive each other. As the Lord forgave you, so also forgive each other. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.14" osisID="Col.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And over all these things put on love, which is the perfect bond of unity. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.15" osisID="Col.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The peace of Christ must control your hearts—a peace into which you were called in one body. And be thankful people. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.16" osisID="Col.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The word of Christ must live in you richly. Teach and warn each other with all wisdom by singing psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs. Sing to God with gratitude in your hearts. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.17" osisID="Col.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whatever you do, whether in speech or action, do it all in the name of the Lord Jesus and give thanks to God the Father through him. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.3.18" osisID="Col.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Wives, submit to your husbands in a way that is appropriate in the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.19" osisID="Col.3.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Husbands, love your wives and don’t be harsh with them. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.20" osisID="Col.3.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Children, obey your parents in everything, because this pleases the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.21" osisID="Col.3.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Parents, don’t provoke your children in a way that ends up discouraging them. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.3.22" osisID="Col.3.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Slaves, obey your masters on earth in everything. Don’t just obey like people pleasers when they are watching. Instead, obey with the single motivation of fearing the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.23" osisID="Col.3.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whatever you do, do it from the heart for the Lord and not for people. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.24" osisID="Col.3.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know that you will receive an inheritance as a reward. You serve the Lord Christ. </verse><verse sID="Col.3.25" osisID="Col.3.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But evildoers will receive their reward for their evil actions. There is no discrimination. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Col.4" osisID="Col.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="Col.4.1-Col.4.6" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Col.4.1" osisID="Col.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Masters, be just and fair to your slaves, knowing that you yourselves have a master in heaven. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.4.2" osisID="Col.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Keep on praying and guard your prayers with thanksgiving. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.3" osisID="Col.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At the same time, pray for us also. Pray that God would open a door for the word so we can preach the secret plan<note osisRef="Col.4.3" placement="inline" osisID="Col.4.3!note.f">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">mystery</hi></note> of Christ—which is why I’m in chains. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.4" osisID="Col.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pray that I might be able to make it as clear as I ought to when I preach. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.5" osisID="Col.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Act wisely toward outsiders, making the most of the opportunity. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.6" osisID="Col.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Your speech should always be gracious and sprinkled with insight so that you may know how to respond to every person. </verse></p></div><div scope="Col.4.7-Col.4.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final greeting</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.4.7" osisID="Col.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tychicus, our dearly loved brother, faithful minister, and fellow slave in the Lord, will inform you about everything that has happened to me. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.8" osisID="Col.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why I sent him to you, so that you’ll know all about us and so he can encourage your hearts. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.9" osisID="Col.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I sent him with Onesimus, our faithful and dearly loved brother, who is one of you. They will let you know about everything here. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.4.10" osisID="Col.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Aristarchus, my fellow prisoner, says hello to you. So does Mark, Barnabas’ cousin (you received instructions about him; if he comes to you, welcome him). </verse><verse sID="Col.4.11" osisID="Col.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jesus, called Justus, also says hello. These are my only fellow workers for God’s kingdom who are Jewish converts. They have been an encouragement to me. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.12" osisID="Col.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Epaphras, who is one of you, says hello. He’s a slave of Christ Jesus who always wrestles for you in prayers so that you will stand firm and be fully mature and complete in the entire will of God. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.13" osisID="Col.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I can vouch for him that he has worked hard for you and for those in Laodicea and Hierapolis. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.14" osisID="Col.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Luke, the dearly loved physician, and Demas say hello. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.4.15" osisID="Col.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Say hello to the brothers and sisters in Laodicea, along with Nympha and the church that meets in her house. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.16" osisID="Col.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After this letter has been read to you publicly, make sure that the church in Laodicea reads it and that you read the one from Laodicea. </verse><verse sID="Col.4.17" osisID="Col.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And tell Archippus, <q type="x-complete">See to it that you complete the ministry that you received in the Lord.</q> </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Col.4.18" osisID="Col.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I, Paul, am writing this greeting personally. Remember that I’m in prison. Grace be with you. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>