<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Thessalonians</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="1Thess"><chapter sID="1Thess.1" osisID="1Thess.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Thessalonians</title><div scope="1Thess.1.1-1Thess.1.1" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Thess.1.1" osisID="1Thess.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">From Paul, Silvanus, and Timothy. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Thess.1.1" osisID="1Thess.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">To the Thessalonians’ church that is in God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Thess.1.1" osisID="1Thess.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Grace and peace to all of you. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.1.2-1Thess.1.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Thanksgiving to God</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.1.2" osisID="1Thess.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We always thank God for all of you when we mention you constantly in our prayers. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.3" osisID="1Thess.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is because we remember your work that comes from faith,<note osisRef="1Thess.1.3" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.1.3!note.a">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">faithfulness</hi></note> your effort that comes from love, and your perseverance that comes from hope in our Lord Jesus Christ in the presence of our God and Father. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.4" osisID="1Thess.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, you are loved by God, and we know that he has chosen you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.5" osisID="1Thess.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We know this because our good news didn’t come to you just in speech but also with power and the Holy Spirit and with deep conviction. You know as well as we do what kind of people we were when we were with you, which was for your sake. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.6" osisID="1Thess.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You became imitators of us and of the Lord when you accepted the message that came from the Holy Spirit with joy in spite of great suffering. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.7" osisID="1Thess.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As a result you became an example to all the believers in Macedonia and Achaia. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.8" osisID="1Thess.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The message about the Lord rang out from you, not only in Macedonia and Achaia but in every place. The news about your faithfulness to God has spread so that we don’t even need to mention it. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.9" osisID="1Thess.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People tell us about what sort of welcome we had from you and how you turned to God from idols. As a result, you are serving<note osisRef="1Thess.1.9" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.1.9!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">to become slaves of</hi></note> the living and true God, </verse><verse sID="1Thess.1.10" osisID="1Thess.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and you are waiting for his Son from heaven. His Son is Jesus, who is the one he raised from the dead and who is the one who will rescue us from the coming wrath. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Thess.2" osisID="1Thess.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="1Thess.2.1-1Thess.2.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s ministry in Thessalonica</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Thess.2.1" osisID="1Thess.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As you yourselves know, brothers and sisters, our visit with you wasn’t a waste of time. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.2" osisID="1Thess.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">On the contrary, we had the courage through God to speak God’s good news in spite of a lot of opposition, although we had already suffered and were publicly insulted, as you know. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.3" osisID="1Thess.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Our appeal isn’t based on false information, the wrong motives, or deception. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.4" osisID="1Thess.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rather, we have been examined and approved by God to be trusted with the good news, and that’s exactly how we speak. We aren’t trying to please people, but we are trying to please God, who continues to examine our hearts. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.5" osisID="1Thess.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As you know, we never used flattery, and God is our witness that we didn’t have greedy motives. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.6" osisID="1Thess.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We didn’t ask for special treatment from people—not from you or from others—</verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.7" osisID="1Thess.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">although we could have thrown our weight around as Christ’s apostles. Instead, we were gentle with you like a nursing mother caring for her own children. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.8" osisID="1Thess.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We were glad to share not only God’s good news with you but also our very lives because we cared for you so much. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.9" osisID="1Thess.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You remember, brothers and sisters, our efforts and hard work. We preached God’s good news to you, while we worked night and day so we wouldn’t be a burden on any of you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.10" osisID="1Thess.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You and God are witnesses of how holy, just, and blameless we were toward you believers. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.11" osisID="1Thess.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Likewise, you know how we treated each of you like a father treats his own children. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.12" osisID="1Thess.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We appealed to you, encouraged you, and pleaded with you to live lives worthy of the God who is calling you into his own kingdom and glory. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.2.13-1Thess.2.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">How the Thessalonians received God’s message</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.2.13" osisID="1Thess.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We also thank God constantly for this: when you accepted God’s word that you heard from us, you welcomed it for what it truly is. Instead of accepting it as a human message, you accepted it as God’s message, and it continues to work in you who are believers. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.14" osisID="1Thess.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, you became imitators of the churches of God in Judea, which are in Christ Jesus. This was because you also suffered the same things from your own people as they did from the Jews. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.15" osisID="1Thess.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They killed both the Lord Jesus and the prophets and drove us out. They don’t please God, and they are hostile to the entire human race </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.16" osisID="1Thess.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">when they try to stop us from speaking to the Gentiles so they can be saved. Their sins are constantly pushing the limit.<note osisRef="1Thess.2.16" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.2.16!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">They constantly fill up the measure of their sin.</hi></note> God’s wrath has caught up with them in the end. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.2.17-1Thess.2.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s desire to visit</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.2.17" osisID="1Thess.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, we were separated from you for a while physically but not in our hearts. We made every effort in our desire to see you again face-to-face. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.18" osisID="1Thess.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We wanted to come to you—I, Paul, tried over and over again—and Satan stopped us. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.19" osisID="1Thess.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What is our hope, joy, or crown that we can brag about in front of our Lord Jesus when he comes? Isn’t it all of you? </verse><verse sID="1Thess.2.20" osisID="1Thess.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You are our glory and joy! </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Thess.3" osisID="1Thess.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="1Thess.3.1-1Thess.3.5" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Thess.3.1" osisID="1Thess.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So when we couldn’t stand it any longer, we thought it was a good idea to stay on in Athens by ourselves, </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.2" osisID="1Thess.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and we sent you Timothy, who is our brother and God’s coworker in the good news about Christ. We sent him to strengthen and encourage you in your faithfulness. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.3" osisID="1Thess.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We didn’t want any of you to be shaken by these problems. You know very well that we were meant to go through this. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.4" osisID="1Thess.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In fact, when we were with you, we kept on predicting that we were going to face problems exactly like what happened, as you know. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.5" osisID="1Thess.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That’s why I sent Timothy to find out about your faithfulness when I couldn’t stand it anymore. I was worried that the tempter might have tempted you so that our work would have been a waste of time. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.3.6-1Thess.3.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Paul’s prayer for the Thessalonians</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.3.6" osisID="1Thess.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now Timothy has returned to us from you and has given us good news about your faithfulness and love! He says that you always have good memories about us and that you want to see us as much as we want to see you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.7" osisID="1Thess.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, brothers and sisters, we were encouraged in all our distress and trouble through your faithfulness. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.8" osisID="1Thess.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">For now we are alive if you are standing your ground in the Lord. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.9" osisID="1Thess.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">How can we thank God enough for you, given all the joy we have because of you before our God? </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.10" osisID="1Thess.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Night and day, we pray more than ever to see all of you in person and to complete whatever you still need for your faith. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.11" osisID="1Thess.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now may our God and Father himself guide us on our way back to you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.12" osisID="1Thess.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May the Lord cause you to increase and enrich your love for each other and for everyone in the same way as we also love you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.3.13" osisID="1Thess.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May the love cause your hearts to be strengthened, to be blameless in holiness before our God and Father when our Lord Jesus comes with all his people. Amen. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Thess.4" osisID="1Thess.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="1Thess.4.1-1Thess.4.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Living that pleases God</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Thess.4.1" osisID="1Thess.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, brothers and sisters, we ask and encourage you in the Lord Jesus to keep living the way you already are and even do better in how you live and please God—just as you learned from us. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.2" osisID="1Thess.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know the instructions we gave you through the Lord Jesus. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.3" osisID="1Thess.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God’s will is that your lives are dedicated to him.<note osisRef="1Thess.4.3" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.4.3!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">holy, sanctified</hi></note> This means that you stay away from sexual immorality </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.4" osisID="1Thess.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and learn how to control your own body in a pure<note osisRef="1Thess.4.3" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.4.3!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">holy, sanctified</hi></note> and respectable way. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.5" osisID="1Thess.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t be controlled by your sexual urges like the Gentiles who don’t know God. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.6" osisID="1Thess.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one should mistreat or take advantage of their brother or sister in this issue. The Lord punishes people for all these things, as we told you before and sternly warned you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.7" osisID="1Thess.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God didn’t call us to be immoral but to be dedicated to him.<note osisRef="1Thess.4.3" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.4.3!note.f">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">holy, sanctified</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.8" osisID="1Thess.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, whoever rejects these instructions isn’t rejecting a human authority. They are rejecting God, who gives his Holy Spirit to you. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.4.9" osisID="1Thess.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You don’t need us to write about loving your brothers and sisters because God has already taught you to love each other. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.10" osisID="1Thess.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In fact, you are doing loving deeds for all the brothers and sisters throughout Macedonia. Now we encourage you, brothers and sisters, to do so even more. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.11" osisID="1Thess.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Aim to live quietly, mind your own business, and earn your own living, just as I told you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.12" osisID="1Thess.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">That way you’ll behave appropriately toward outsiders, and you won’t be in need. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.4.13-1Thess.4.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Believers who have died</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.4.13" osisID="1Thess.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, we want you to know about people who have died<note osisRef="1Thess.4.3" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.4.3!note.g">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">fallen asleep</hi></note> so that you won’t mourn like others who don’t have any hope. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.14" osisID="1Thess.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since we believe that Jesus died and rose, so we also believe that God will bring with him those who have died in Jesus. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.15" osisID="1Thess.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What we are saying is a message from the Lord: we who are alive and still around at the Lord’s coming definitely won’t go ahead of those who have died. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.16" osisID="1Thess.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is because the Lord himself will come down from heaven with the signal of a shout by the head angel and a blast on God’s trumpet. First, those who are dead in Christ will rise. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.17" osisID="1Thess.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then, we who are living and still around will be taken up together with them in the clouds to meet with the Lord in the air. That way we will always be with the Lord. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.4.18" osisID="1Thess.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So encourage each other with these words. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Thess.5" osisID="1Thess.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="1Thess.5.1-1Thess.5.11" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">The Lord’s coming</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Thess.5.1" osisID="1Thess.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We don’t need to write to you about the timing and dates, brothers and sisters. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.2" osisID="1Thess.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know very well that the day of the Lord is going to come like a thief in the night. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.3" osisID="1Thess.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they are saying, <q type="x-complete">There is peace and security,</q> at that time sudden destruction will attack them, like labor pains start with a pregnant woman, and they definitely won’t escape. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.4" osisID="1Thess.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you aren’t in darkness, brothers and sisters, so the day won’t catch you by surprise like a thief. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.5" osisID="1Thess.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">All of you are children of light and children of the day. We don’t belong to night or darkness. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.6" osisID="1Thess.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So then, let’s not sleep like the others, but let’s stay awake and stay sober. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.7" osisID="1Thess.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People who sleep sleep at night, and people who get drunk get drunk at night. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.8" osisID="1Thess.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since we belong to the day, let’s stay sober, wearing faithfulness and love as a piece of armor that protects our body<note osisRef="1Thess.4.3" placement="inline" osisID="1Thess.4.3!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">breastplate</hi></note> and the hope of salvation as a helmet. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.9" osisID="1Thess.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God didn’t intend for us to suffer his wrath but rather to possess salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.10" osisID="1Thess.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Jesus died for us so that, whether we are awake or asleep, we will live together with him. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.11" osisID="1Thess.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So continue encouraging each other and building each other up, just like you are doing already. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.5.12-1Thess.5.24" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final instructions and blessing</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.5.12" osisID="1Thess.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, we ask you to respect those who are working with you, leading you, and instructing you. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.13" osisID="1Thess.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Think of them highly with love because of their work. Live in peace with each other. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.14" osisID="1Thess.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, we urge you to warn those who are disorderly. Comfort the discouraged. Help the weak. Be patient with everyone. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.15" osisID="1Thess.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Make sure no one repays a wrong with a wrong, but always pursue the good for each other and everyone else. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.16" osisID="1Thess.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Rejoice always. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.17" osisID="1Thess.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pray continually. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.18" osisID="1Thess.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Give thanks in every situation because this is God’s will for you in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.19" osisID="1Thess.5.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t suppress the Spirit. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.20" osisID="1Thess.5.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t brush off Spirit-inspired messages, </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.21" osisID="1Thess.5.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">but examine everything carefully and hang on to what is good. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.22" osisID="1Thess.5.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Avoid every kind of evil. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.23" osisID="1Thess.5.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now, may the God of peace himself cause you to be completely dedicated to him; and may your spirit, soul, and body be kept intact and blameless at our Lord Jesus Christ’s coming. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.24" osisID="1Thess.5.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who is calling you is faithful and will do this. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Thess.5.25-1Thess.5.28" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final greeting</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Thess.5.25" osisID="1Thess.5.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, pray for us. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.26" osisID="1Thess.5.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Greet all the brothers and sisters with a holy kiss. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.27" osisID="1Thess.5.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">By the Lord’s authority, I order all of you to have this letter read aloud to all the brothers and sisters. </verse><verse sID="1Thess.5.28" osisID="1Thess.5.28" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with all of you. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>