<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Timothy</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="1Tim"><chapter sID="1Tim.1" osisID="1Tim.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">1 Timothy</title><div scope="1Tim.1.1-1Tim.1.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Tim.1.1" osisID="1Tim.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From Paul, who is an apostle of Jesus Christ by the command of God our savior and of Christ Jesus our hope. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Tim.1.2" osisID="1Tim.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">To Timothy, my true child in the faith. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="1Tim.1.2" osisID="1Tim.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and from Christ Jesus our Lord. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.1.3-1Tim.1.11" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Timothy’s purpose in Ephesus</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.1.3" osisID="1Tim.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When I left for Macedonia, I asked you to stay behind in Ephesus so that you could instruct certain individuals not to spread wrong teaching. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.4" osisID="1Tim.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They shouldn’t pay attention to myths and endless genealogies. Their teaching only causes useless guessing games instead of faithfulness to God’s way of doing things. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.5" osisID="1Tim.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The goal of instruction is love from a pure heart, a good conscience, and a sincere faith. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.6" osisID="1Tim.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because they missed this goal, some people have been distracted by talk that doesn’t mean anything. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.7" osisID="1Tim.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They want to be teachers of Law without understanding either what they are saying or what they are talking about with such confidence. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.8" osisID="1Tim.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now we know that the Law is good if used appropriately. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.9" osisID="1Tim.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We understand this: the Law isn’t established for a righteous person but for people who live without laws and without obeying any authority. They are the ungodly and the sinners. They are people who are not spiritual, and nothing is sacred to them. They kill their fathers and mothers, and murder others. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.10" osisID="1Tim.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They are people who are sexually unfaithful, and people who have intercourse with the same sex. They are kidnappers,<note osisRef="1Tim.1.10" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.1.10!note.a">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">slave dealers</hi></note> liars, individuals who give false testimonies in court, and those who do anything else that is opposed to sound teaching. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.11" osisID="1Tim.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Sound teaching agrees with the glorious gospel of the blessed God that has been trusted to me. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.1.12-1Tim.1.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Thanksgiving</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.1.12" osisID="1Tim.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I thank Christ Jesus our Lord, who has given me strength because he considered me faithful. So he appointed me to ministry </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.13" osisID="1Tim.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">even though I used to speak against him, attack his people, and I was proud. But I was shown mercy because I acted in ignorance and without faith. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.14" osisID="1Tim.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Our Lord’s favor poured all over me along with the faithfulness and love that are in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.15" osisID="1Tim.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This saying is reliable and deserves full acceptance: <q type="x-complete">Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners</q>—and I’m the biggest sinner of all. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.16" osisID="1Tim.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But this is why I was shown mercy, so that Christ Jesus could show his endless patience to me first of all. So I’m an example for those who are going to believe in him for eternal life. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.17" osisID="1Tim.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now to the king of the ages, to the immortal, invisible, and only God, may honor and glory be given to him forever and always! Amen. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.1.18-1Tim.1.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Importance of faith and a good conscience</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.1.18" osisID="1Tim.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Timothy, my child, I’m giving you these instructions based on the prophecies that were once made about you. So if you follow them, you can wage a good war </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.19" osisID="1Tim.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">because you have faith and a good conscience. Some people have ruined their faith because they refused to listen to their conscience, </verse><verse sID="1Tim.1.20" osisID="1Tim.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">such as Hymenaeus and Alexander. I’ve handed them over to Satan so that they can be taught not to speak against God. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Tim.2" osisID="1Tim.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="1Tim.2.1-1Tim.2.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Prayer for everyone</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Tim.2.1" osisID="1Tim.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">First of all, then, I ask that requests, prayers, petitions, and thanksgiving be made for all people. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.2" osisID="1Tim.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pray for kings and everyone who is in authority so that we can live a quiet and peaceful life in complete godliness and dignity. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.3" osisID="1Tim.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is right and it pleases God our savior, </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.4" osisID="1Tim.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who wants all people to be saved and to come to a knowledge of the truth. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.5" osisID="1Tim.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There is one God and one mediator between God and humanity, the human Christ Jesus, </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.6" osisID="1Tim.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who gave himself as a payment to set all people free. This was a testimony that was given at the right time. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.7" osisID="1Tim.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I was appointed to be a preacher and apostle of this testimony—I’m telling the truth and I’m not lying! I’m a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and truth. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.2.8-1Tim.2.15" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Instructions for men and women</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.2.8" osisID="1Tim.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, I want men to pray everywhere by lifting up hands that are holy, without anger or argument. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.9" osisID="1Tim.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, I want women to enhance their appearance with clothing that is modest and sensible, not with elaborate hairstyles, gold, pearls, or expensive clothes. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.10" osisID="1Tim.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They should make themselves attractive by doing good, which is appropriate for women who claim to honor God. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.2.11" osisID="1Tim.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A wife<note osisRef="1Tim.2.11" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.2.11!note.b">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a woman</hi></note> should learn quietly with complete submission. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.12" osisID="1Tim.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I don’t allow a wife<note osisRef="1Tim.2.12" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.2.12!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a woman</hi></note> to teach or to control her husband.<note osisRef="1Tim.2.12" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.2.12!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a man</hi></note> Instead, she should be a quiet listener. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.13" osisID="1Tim.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Adam was formed first, and then Eve. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.14" osisID="1Tim.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Adam wasn’t deceived, but rather his wife<note osisRef="1Tim.2.14" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.2.14!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">the woman</hi></note> became the one who stepped over the line because she was completely deceived. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.2.15" osisID="1Tim.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But a wife<note osisRef="1Tim.2.15" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.2.15!note.f">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">a woman</hi></note> will be brought safely through giving birth to their children,<note osisRef="1Tim.2.15" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.2.15!note.g">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">saved through childbearing</hi></note> if they both continue in faith, love, and holiness, together with self-control. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Tim.3" osisID="1Tim.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="1Tim.3.1-1Tim.3.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Supervisors in God’s household</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Tim.3.1" osisID="1Tim.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This saying is reliable: if anyone has a goal to be a supervisor<note osisRef="1Tim.3.1" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.3.1!note.h">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">bishop, overseer</hi></note> in the church, they want a good thing. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.2" osisID="1Tim.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the church’s supervisor must be without fault. They should be faithful to their spouse, sober, modest, and honest. They should show hospitality and be skilled at teaching. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.3" osisID="1Tim.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They shouldn’t be addicted to alcohol or a bully. Instead, they should be gentle, peaceable, and not greedy. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.4" osisID="1Tim.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They should manage their own household well—they should see that their children are obedient with complete respect, </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.5" osisID="1Tim.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">because if they don’t know how to manage their own household, how can they take care of God’s church? </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.6" osisID="1Tim.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They shouldn’t be new believers so that they won’t become proud and fall under the devil’s spell. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.7" osisID="1Tim.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They should also have a good reputation with those outside the church so that they won’t be embarrassed and fall into the devil’s trap. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.3.8-1Tim.3.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Servants in God’s household</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.3.8" osisID="1Tim.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, servants<note osisRef="1Tim.3.8" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.3.8!note.i">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">deacons</hi></note> in the church should be dignified, not two-faced, heavy drinkers, or greedy for money. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.9" osisID="1Tim.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They should hold on to the faith that has been revealed with a clear conscience. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.10" osisID="1Tim.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They should also be tested and then serve if they are without fault. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.11" osisID="1Tim.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, women who are servants<note osisRef="1Tim.3.11" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.3.11!note.j">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">wives</hi>, omit <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">who are servants</hi></note> in the church should be dignified and not gossip. They should be sober and faithful in everything they do. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.12" osisID="1Tim.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Servants<note osisRef="1Tim.3.12" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.3.11!note.k">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">deacons</hi></note> must be faithful to their spouse and manage their children and their own households well. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.13" osisID="1Tim.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who have served well gain a good standing and considerable confidence in the faith that is in Christ Jesus. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.3.14-1Tim.3.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Leading God’s household</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.3.14" osisID="1Tim.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I hope to come to you quickly. But I’m writing these things to you so that </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.15" osisID="1Tim.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">if I’m delayed, you’ll know how you should behave in God’s household. It is the church of the living God and the backbone and support of the truth. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.3.16" osisID="1Tim.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Without question, the mystery of godliness is great: he was revealed as a human, declared righteous by the Spirit, seen by angels, preached throughout the nations, believed in around the world, and taken up in glory. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Tim.4" osisID="1Tim.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="1Tim.4.1-1Tim.4.7" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Tim.4.1" osisID="1Tim.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Spirit clearly says that in latter times some people will turn away from the faith. They will pay attention to spirits that deceive and to the teaching of demons. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.2" osisID="1Tim.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They will be controlled by the pretense of lying, and their own consciences will be seared. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.3" osisID="1Tim.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They will prohibit marriage and eating foods that God created—and he intended them to be accepted with thanksgiving by those who are faithful and have come to know the truth. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.4" osisID="1Tim.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everything that has been created by God is good, and nothing that is received with thanksgiving should be rejected. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.5" osisID="1Tim.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These things are made holy by God’s word and prayer. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.6" osisID="1Tim.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If you point these things out to the believers, you will be a good servant of Christ Jesus who has been trained by the words of faith and the good teaching that you’ve carefully followed. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.7" osisID="1Tim.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">But stay away from the godless myths that are passed down from the older women. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.4.8-1Tim.4.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Practices of spiritual leadership</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.4.7" osisID="1Tim.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Train yourself for a holy life! </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.8" osisID="1Tim.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">While physical training has some value, training in holy living is useful for everything. It has promise for this life now and the life to come. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.9" osisID="1Tim.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This saying is reliable and deserves complete acceptance. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.10" osisID="1Tim.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We work and struggle for this: <q type="x-complete">Our hope is set on the living God, who is the savior of all people, especially those who believe.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.11" osisID="1Tim.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Command these things. Teach them. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.12" osisID="1Tim.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t let anyone look down on you because you are young. Instead, set an example for the believers through your speech, behavior, love, faith, and by being sexually pure. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.13" osisID="1Tim.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Until I arrive, pay attention to public reading, preaching, and teaching. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.14" osisID="1Tim.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t neglect the spiritual gift in you that was given through prophecy when the elders laid hands on you. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.15" osisID="1Tim.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Practice these things, and live by them so that your progress will be visible to all. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.4.16" osisID="1Tim.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Focus on working on your own development and on what you teach. If you do this, you will save yourself and those who hear you. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Tim.5" osisID="1Tim.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="1Tim.5.1-1Tim.5.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Caring for God’s family</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Tim.5.1" osisID="1Tim.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t correct an older man, but encourage him like he’s your father; treat younger men like your brothers, </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.2" osisID="1Tim.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">treat older women like your mother, and treat younger women like your sisters with appropriate respect. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.5.3" osisID="1Tim.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Take care of widows who are truly needy. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.4" osisID="1Tim.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if a particular widow has children or grandchildren, they should first learn to respect their own family and repay their parents, because this pleases God. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.5" osisID="1Tim.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A widow who is truly needy and all alone puts her hope in God and keeps on going with requests and prayers, night and day. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.6" osisID="1Tim.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But a widow who tries to live a life of luxury is dead even while she is alive. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.7" osisID="1Tim.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Teach these things so that the families<note osisRef="1Tim.5.7" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.5.7!note.l">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">they</hi></note> will be without fault. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.8" osisID="1Tim.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But if someone doesn’t provide for their own family, and especially for a member of their household, they have denied the faith. They are worse than those who have no faith. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.5.9" osisID="1Tim.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Put a widow on the list who is older than 60 years old and who was faithful to her husband. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.10" osisID="1Tim.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">She should have a reputation for doing good: raising children, providing hospitality to strangers, washing the feet of the saints, helping those in distress, and dedicating herself to every kind of good thing. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.11" osisID="1Tim.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But don’t accept younger widows for the list. When their physical desires distract them from Christ, they will want to get married. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.12" osisID="1Tim.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then they will be judged for setting aside their earlier commitment. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.13" osisID="1Tim.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Also, they learn to be lazy by going from house to house. They are not only lazy, but they also become gossips and busybodies, talking about things they shouldn’t. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.14" osisID="1Tim.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So I want younger widows to marry, have children, and manage their homes so that they won’t give the enemy any reason to slander us. (</verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.15" osisID="1Tim.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some have already turned away to follow Satan.) </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.16" osisID="1Tim.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If any woman who is a believer has widows in her family, she should take care of them and not burden the church, so that it can help other widows who are truly needy. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.5.17-1Tim.5.25" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Instructions for elders</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.5.17" osisID="1Tim.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elders who lead well should be paid double, especially those who work with public speaking and teaching. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.18" osisID="1Tim.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The scripture says, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Don’t put a muzzle on an ox while it treads grain</hi>,<note osisRef="1Tim.5.18" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.5.18!note.m">Deut 25:4</note> and <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Workers deserve their pay</hi>.<note osisRef="1Tim.5.18" placement="inline" osisID="1Tim.5.18!note.n">Luke 10:7</note> </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.19" osisID="1Tim.5.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t accept an accusation made against an elder unless it is confirmed by two or three witnesses. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.20" osisID="1Tim.5.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Discipline those who are sinning in front of everyone so that all the others will be afraid. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.21" osisID="1Tim.5.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I charge you before God and Christ Jesus and the elect angels to follow these practices without bias, and without playing favorites. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.22" osisID="1Tim.5.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t rush to commission anyone to leadership, and don’t participate in the sins of others. Keep yourself morally pure. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.5.23" osisID="1Tim.5.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t drink water anymore, but use a little wine because of your stomach problems and your frequent illnesses. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.24" osisID="1Tim.5.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The sins of some people are obvious, and the sins are judged before the people must face judgment, but the sins of other people show up later. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.5.25" osisID="1Tim.5.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, the good that people do is also obvious and can’t be hidden. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="1Tim.6" osisID="1Tim.6" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="6"><div scope="1Tim.6.1-1Tim.6.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Conduct of Christian slaves</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="1Tim.6.1" osisID="1Tim.6.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who are under the bondage of slavery should consider their own masters as worthy of full respect so that God’s name and our teaching won’t get a bad reputation. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.2" osisID="1Tim.6.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">And those who have masters who are believers shouldn’t look down on them because they are brothers. Instead, they should serve them more faithfully, because the people who benefit from your good service are believers who are loved. Teach and encourage these things. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.6.3-1Tim.6.16" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Warning about false teachers</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.6.3" osisID="1Tim.6.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If anyone teaches anything different and doesn’t agree with sound teaching about our Lord Jesus Christ and teaching that is consistent with godliness, </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.4" osisID="1Tim.6.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">that person is conceited. They don’t understand anything but have a sick obsession with debates and arguments. This creates jealousy, conflict, verbal abuse, and evil suspicions. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.5" osisID="1Tim.6.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There is constant bickering between people whose minds are ruined and who have been robbed of the truth. They think that godliness is a way to make money! </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.6" osisID="1Tim.6.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Actually, godliness is a great source of profit when it is combined with being happy with what you already have. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.7" osisID="1Tim.6.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We didn’t bring anything into the world and so we can’t take anything out of it: </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.8" osisID="1Tim.6.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">we’ll be happy with food and clothing. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.9" osisID="1Tim.6.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But people who are trying to get rich fall into temptation. They are trapped by many stupid and harmful passions that plunge people into ruin and destruction. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.10" osisID="1Tim.6.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The love of money is the root of all kinds of evil. Some have wandered away from the faith and have impaled themselves with a lot of pain because they made money their goal. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.6.11" osisID="1Tim.6.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But as for you, man of God, run away from all these things. Instead, pursue righteousness, holy living, faithfulness, love, endurance, and gentleness. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.12" osisID="1Tim.6.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Compete in the good fight of faith. Grab hold of eternal life—you were called to it, and you made a good confession of it in the presence of many witnesses. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.13" osisID="1Tim.6.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I command you in the presence of God, who gives life to all things, and Christ Jesus, who made the good confession when testifying before Pontius Pilate. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.14" osisID="1Tim.6.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Obey this order without fault or failure until the appearance of our Lord Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.15" osisID="1Tim.6.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The timing of this appearance is revealed by God alone, who is the blessed and only master, the King of kings and Lord of lords. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.16" osisID="1Tim.6.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He alone has immortality and lives in light that no one can come near. No human being has ever seen or is able to see him. Honor and eternal power belong to him. Amen. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.6.17-1Tim.6.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Wealth of good works</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.6.17" osisID="1Tim.6.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tell people who are rich at this time not to become egotistical and not to place their hope on their finances, which are uncertain. Instead, they need to hope in God, who richly provides everything for our enjoyment. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.18" osisID="1Tim.6.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Tell them to do good, to be rich in the good things they do, to be generous, and to share with others. </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.19" osisID="1Tim.6.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When they do these things, they will save a treasure for themselves that is a good foundation for the future. That way they can take hold of what is truly life. </verse></p></div><div scope="1Tim.6.20-1Tim.6.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Protect the tradition</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.6.20" osisID="1Tim.6.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Timothy, protect what has been given to you in trust. Avoid godless and pointless discussions and the contradictory claims of so-called <q type="x-complete">knowledge.</q> </verse><verse sID="1Tim.6.21" osisID="1Tim.6.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">When some people adopted this false knowledge, they missed the goal of faith. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="1Tim.6.21" osisID="1Tim.6.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">May grace be with you all. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>