<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">2 Timothy</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="2Tim"><chapter sID="2Tim.1" osisID="2Tim.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">2 Timothy</title><div scope="2Tim.1.1-2Tim.1.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="2Tim.1.1" osisID="2Tim.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">From Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by God’s will, to promote the promise of life that is in Christ Jesus. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="2Tim.1.2" osisID="2Tim.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">To Timothy, my dear child. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting">Grace, mercy, and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.</p></div><div scope="2Tim.1.3-2Tim.1.7" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Thanksgiving and prayer</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.1.3" osisID="2Tim.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m grateful to God, whom I serve with a good conscience as my ancestors did. I constantly remember you in my prayers day and night. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.4" osisID="2Tim.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When I remember your tears, I long to see you so that I can be filled with happiness. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.5" osisID="2Tim.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m reminded of your authentic faith, which first lived in your grandmother Lois and your mother Eunice. I’m sure that this faith is also inside you. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.6" osisID="2Tim.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Because of this, I’m reminding you to revive God’s gift that is in you through the laying on of my hands. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.7" osisID="2Tim.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God didn’t give us a spirit that is timid but one that is powerful, loving, and self-controlled. </verse></p></div><div scope="2Tim.1.8-2Tim.1.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Don’t be ashamed of the testimony</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.1.8" osisID="2Tim.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So don’t be ashamed of the testimony about the Lord or of me, his prisoner. Instead, share the suffering for the good news, depending on God’s power. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.9" osisID="2Tim.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God is the one who saved and called us with a holy calling. This wasn’t based on what we have done, but it was based on his own purpose and grace that he gave us in Christ Jesus before time began. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.10" osisID="2Tim.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Now his grace is revealed through the appearance of our savior, Christ Jesus. He destroyed death and brought life and immortality into clear focus through the good news. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.11" osisID="2Tim.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I was appointed a messenger, apostle, and teacher of this good news. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.12" osisID="2Tim.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is also why I’m suffering the way I do, but I’m not ashamed. I know the one in whom I’ve placed my trust. I’m convinced that God is powerful enough to protect what he has placed in my trust until that day. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.13" osisID="2Tim.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Hold on to the pattern of sound teaching that you heard from me with the faith and love that are in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.14" osisID="2Tim.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Protect this good thing that has been placed in your trust through the Holy Spirit who lives in us. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.1.15" osisID="2Tim.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You know that everyone in Asia has turned away from me, including Phygelus and Hermogenes. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.16" osisID="2Tim.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May the Lord show mercy to Onesiphorus’ household, because he supported me many times and he wasn’t ashamed of my imprisonment. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.17" osisID="2Tim.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After I arrived in Rome, he quickly looked for me and found me. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.1.18" osisID="2Tim.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May the Lord allow him to find his mercy on that day (and you know very well how much he served me in Ephesus). </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Tim.2" osisID="2Tim.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="2Tim.2.1-2Tim.2.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Pass on the message and share suffering</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Tim.2.1" osisID="2Tim.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So, my child, draw your strength from the grace that is in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.2" osisID="2Tim.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Take the things you heard me say in front of many other witnesses and pass them on to faithful people who are also capable of teaching others. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.2.3" osisID="2Tim.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Accept your share of suffering like a good soldier of Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.4" osisID="2Tim.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Nobody who serves in the military gets tied up with civilian matters, so that they can please the one who recruited them. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.5" osisID="2Tim.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Also in the same way, athletes don’t win unless they follow the rules. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.6" osisID="2Tim.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">A hardworking farmer should get the first share of the crop. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.7" osisID="2Tim.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Think about what I’m saying; the Lord will give you understanding about everything. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.2.8" osisID="2Tim.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Remember Jesus Christ, who was raised from the dead and descended from David. This is my good news. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.9" osisID="2Tim.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is the reason I’m suffering to the point that I’m in prison like a common criminal. But God’s word cannot be imprisoned. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.10" osisID="2Tim.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is why I endure everything for the sake of those who are chosen by God so that they too may experience salvation in Christ Jesus with eternal glory. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.11" osisID="2Tim.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">This saying is reliable: </verse></p><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="2Tim.2.11" osisID="2Tim.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-start">If we have died together, we will also live together.</q> </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="2Tim.2.12" osisID="2Tim.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-continuation">If we endure, we will also rule together.</q> </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="2Tim.2.12" osisID="2Tim.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end"><q type="x-continuation">If we deny him, he will also deny us.</q> </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="2Tim.2.13" osisID="2Tim.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start"><q type="x-end">If we are disloyal, he stays faithful</q> </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText2"><verse sID="2Tim.2.13" osisID="2Tim.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">because he can’t be anything else than what he is. </verse></l></lg></div><div scope="2Tim.2.14-2Tim.2.21" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Speak, instruct, and act correctly</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.2.14" osisID="2Tim.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Remind them of these things and warn them in the sight of God not to engage in battles over words that aren’t helpful and only destroy those who hear them. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.15" osisID="2Tim.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Make an effort to present yourself to God as a tried-and-true worker, who doesn’t need to be ashamed but is one who interprets the message of truth correctly. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.16" osisID="2Tim.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Avoid their godless discussions, because they will lead many people into ungodly behavior, </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.17" osisID="2Tim.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and their ideas will spread like an infection. This includes Hymenaeus and Philetus, </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.18" osisID="2Tim.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">who have deviated from the truth by claiming that the resurrection has already happened. This has undermined some people’s faith. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.2.19" osisID="2Tim.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God’s solid foundation is still standing with this sign: <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">The Lord knows the people who belong to him,</hi><note osisRef="2Tim.2.19" placement="inline" osisID="2Tim.2.19!note.a">Num 16:5 LXX</note> and <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Everyone who confesses the Lord’s name must avoid wickedness.</hi><note osisRef="2Tim.2.19" placement="inline" osisID="2Tim.2.19!note.b">Possibly modeled on Isa 26:13</note> </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.20" osisID="2Tim.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In a mansion, there aren’t just gold and silver bowls but also some bowls that are made of wood and clay. Some are meant for special uses, some for garbage.<note osisRef="2Tim.2.20" placement="inline" osisID="2Tim.2.20!note.c">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">dishonorable purposes</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.21" osisID="2Tim.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So if anyone washes filth off themselves, they will be set apart as a <q type="x-complete">special bowl.</q> They will be useful to the owner of the mansion for every sort of good work. </verse></p></div><div scope="2Tim.2.22-2Tim.2.26" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Avoid conflict with opponents</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.2.22" osisID="2Tim.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Run away from adolescent cravings. Instead, pursue righteousness, faith, love, and peace together with those who confess the Lord with a clean heart. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.23" osisID="2Tim.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Avoid foolish and thoughtless discussions, since you know that they produce conflicts. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.24" osisID="2Tim.2.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">God’s slave shouldn’t be argumentative but should be kind toward all people, able to teach, patient, </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.25" osisID="2Tim.2.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">and should correct opponents with gentleness. Perhaps God will change their mind and give them a knowledge of the truth. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.2.26" osisID="2Tim.2.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They may come to their senses and escape from the devil’s trap that holds them captive to do his will. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Tim.3" osisID="2Tim.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="2Tim.3.1-2Tim.3.9" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Avoid people like this</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Tim.3.1" osisID="2Tim.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Understand that the last days will be dangerous times. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.2" osisID="2Tim.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People will be selfish and love money. They will be the kind of people who brag and who are proud. They will slander others, and they will be disobedient to their parents. They will be ungrateful, unholy, </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.3" osisID="2Tim.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">unloving, contrary, and critical. They will be without self-control and brutal, and they won’t love what is good. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.4" osisID="2Tim.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They will be people who are disloyal, reckless, and conceited. They will love pleasure instead of loving God. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.5" osisID="2Tim.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They will look like they are religious but deny God’s power. Avoid people like this. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.6" osisID="2Tim.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Some will slither into households and control immature women who are burdened with sins and driven by all kinds of desires. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.7" osisID="2Tim.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These women are always learning, but they can never arrive at an understanding of the truth. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.8" osisID="2Tim.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These people oppose the truth in the same way that Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses. Their minds are corrupt and their faith is counterfeit. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.9" osisID="2Tim.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But they won’t get very far. Their foolishness will become obvious to everyone like those others. </verse></p></div><div scope="2Tim.3.10-2Tim.3.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Take Paul as your model</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.3.10" osisID="2Tim.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you have paid attention to my teaching, conduct, purpose, faithfulness, patience, love, and endurance. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.11" osisID="2Tim.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You have seen me experience physical abuse and ordeals in places such as Antioch, Iconium, and Lystra. I put up with all sorts of abuse, and the Lord rescued me from it all! </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.12" osisID="2Tim.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In fact, anyone who wants to live a holy life in Christ Jesus will be harassed. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.13" osisID="2Tim.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But evil people and swindlers will grow even worse, as they deceive others while being deceived themselves. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.3.14" osisID="2Tim.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you must continue with the things you have learned and found convincing. You know who taught you. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.15" osisID="2Tim.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Since childhood you have known the holy scriptures that help you to be wise in a way that leads to salvation through faith that is in Christ Jesus. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.16" osisID="2Tim.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Every scripture is inspired by God and is useful for teaching, for showing mistakes, for correcting, and for training character, </verse><verse sID="2Tim.3.17" osisID="2Tim.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">so that the person who belongs to God can be equipped to do everything that is good. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="2Tim.4" osisID="2Tim.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="2Tim.4.1-2Tim.4.8" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Timothy’s commission and Paul’s departure</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="2Tim.4.1" osisID="2Tim.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m giving you this commission in the presence of God and of Christ Jesus, who is coming to judge the living and the dead, and by his appearance and his kingdom. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.2" osisID="2Tim.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Preach the word. Be ready to do it whether it is convenient or inconvenient. Correct, confront, and encourage with patience and instruction. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.3" osisID="2Tim.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There will come a time when people will not tolerate sound teaching. They will collect teachers who say what they want to hear because they are self-centered. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.4" osisID="2Tim.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They will turn their back on the truth and turn to myths. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.5" osisID="2Tim.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you must keep control of yourself in all circumstances. Endure suffering, do the work of a preacher of the good news, and carry out your service fully. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.4.6" osisID="2Tim.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I’m already being poured out like a sacrifice to God, and the time of my death is near. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.7" osisID="2Tim.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I have fought the good fight, finished the race, and kept the faith. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.8" osisID="2Tim.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">At last the champion’s wreath that is awarded for righteousness<note osisRef="2Tim.4.8" placement="inline" osisID="2Tim.4.8!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">justice</hi></note> is waiting for me. The Lord, who is the righteous<note osisRef="2Tim.4.8" placement="inline" osisID="2Tim.4.8!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">just</hi></note> judge, is going to give it to me on that day. He’s giving it not only to me but also to all those who have set their heart on waiting for his appearance. </verse></p></div><div scope="2Tim.4.9-2Tim.4.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final instructions</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.4.9" osisID="2Tim.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Do your best to come to me quickly. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.10" osisID="2Tim.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Demas has fallen in love with the present world and has deserted me and has gone to Thessalonica. Crescens has gone to Galatia, and Titus has gone to Dalmatia. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.11" osisID="2Tim.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Only Luke is with me. Get Mark, and bring him with you. He has been a big help to me in the ministry. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.12" osisID="2Tim.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I sent Tychicus to Ephesus. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.13" osisID="2Tim.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When you come, bring along the coat I left with Carpus in Troas. Also bring the scrolls and especially the parchments. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.14" osisID="2Tim.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Alexander, the craftsman who works with metal, has really hurt me. The Lord will pay him back for what he has done. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.15" osisID="2Tim.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But watch out for him, because he opposes our teaching. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.4.16" osisID="2Tim.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one took my side at my first court hearing. Everyone deserted me. I hope that God doesn’t hold it against them! </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.17" osisID="2Tim.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But the Lord stood by me and gave me strength, so that the entire message would be preached through me and so all the nations could hear it. I was also rescued from the lion’s mouth! </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.18" osisID="2Tim.4.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Lord will rescue me from every evil action and will save me for his heavenly kingdom. To him be the glory forever and always. Amen. </verse></p></div><div scope="2Tim.4.19-2Tim.4.22" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final greetings</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.4.19" osisID="2Tim.4.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Say hello to Prisca and Aquila and the household of Onesiphorus. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.20" osisID="2Tim.4.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Erastus stayed in Corinth, and I left Trophimus in Miletus because of his illness. </verse><verse sID="2Tim.4.21" osisID="2Tim.4.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Try hard to come to me before winter. Eubulus, Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brothers and sisters say hello. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="2Tim.4.22" osisID="2Tim.4.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The Lord be with your spirit. Grace be with you all. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>