<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">James</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="Jas"><chapter sID="Jas.1" osisID="Jas.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">James</title><div scope="Jas.1.1-Jas.1.1" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Jas.1.1" osisID="Jas.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">From James, a slave of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Jas.1.1" osisID="Jas.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">To the twelve tribes who are scattered outside the land of Israel. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Jas.1.1" osisID="Jas.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Greetings! </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.1.2-Jas.1.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Stand firm</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.2" osisID="Jas.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, think of the various tests you encounter as occasions for joy. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.3" osisID="Jas.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">After all, you know that the testing of your faith produces endurance. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.4" osisID="Jas.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Let this endurance complete its work so that you may be fully mature, complete, and lacking in nothing. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.5" osisID="Jas.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But anyone who needs wisdom should ask God, whose very nature is to give to everyone without a second thought, without keeping score. Wisdom will certainly be given to those who ask. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.6" osisID="Jas.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Whoever asks shouldn’t hesitate. They should ask in faith, without doubting. Whoever doubts is like the surf of the sea, tossed and turned by the wind. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.7" osisID="Jas.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People like that should never imagine that they will receive anything from the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.8" osisID="Jas.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They are double-minded, unstable in all their ways. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.9" osisID="Jas.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters who are poor should find satisfaction in their high status. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.10" osisID="Jas.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who are wealthy should find satisfaction in their low status, because they will die off like wildflowers. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.11" osisID="Jas.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The sun rises with its scorching heat and dries up the grass so that its flowers fall and its beauty is lost. Just like that, in the midst of their daily lives, the wealthy will waste away. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.12" osisID="Jas.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who stand firm during testing are blessed. They are tried and true. They will receive the life God has promised to those who love him as their reward. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.1.13-Jas.1.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Our cravings versus God’s gifts</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.13" osisID="Jas.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one who is tested should say, <q type="x-complete">God is tempting me!</q> This is because God is not tempted by any form of evil, nor does he tempt anyone. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.14" osisID="Jas.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Everyone is tempted by their own cravings; they are lured away and enticed by them. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.15" osisID="Jas.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Once those cravings conceive, they give birth to sin; and when sin grows up, it gives birth to death. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.16" osisID="Jas.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t be misled, my dear brothers and sisters. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.17" osisID="Jas.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Every good gift, every perfect gift, comes from above. These gifts come down from the Father, the creator of the heavenly lights, in whose character there is no change at all. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.18" osisID="Jas.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He chose to give us birth by his true word, and here is the result: we are like the first crop from the harvest of everything he created. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.1.19-Jas.1.27" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Welcoming and doing the word</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.19" osisID="Jas.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Know this, my dear brothers and sisters: everyone should be quick to listen, slow to speak, and slow to grow angry. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.20" osisID="Jas.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is because an angry person doesn’t produce God’s righteousness. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.21" osisID="Jas.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, with humility, set aside all moral filth and the growth of wickedness, and welcome the word planted deep inside you—the very word that is able to save you. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.22" osisID="Jas.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You must be doers of the word and not only hearers who mislead themselves. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.23" osisID="Jas.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who hear but don’t do the word are like those who look at their faces in a mirror. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.24" osisID="Jas.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They look at themselves, walk away, and immediately forget what they were like. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.25" osisID="Jas.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But there are those who study the perfect law, the law of freedom, and continue to do it. They don’t listen and then forget, but they put it into practice in their lives. They will be blessed in whatever they do. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.1.26" osisID="Jas.1.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If those who claim devotion to God don’t control what they say, they mislead themselves. Their devotion is worthless. </verse><verse sID="Jas.1.27" osisID="Jas.1.27" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">True devotion, the kind that is pure and faultless before God the Father, is this: to care for orphans and widows in their difficulties and to keep the world from contaminating us. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Jas.2" osisID="Jas.2" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="2"><div scope="Jas.2.1-Jas.2.13" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Don’t show favoritism</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Jas.2.1" osisID="Jas.2.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, when you show favoritism you deny the faithfulness of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has been resurrected in glory. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.2" osisID="Jas.2.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Imagine two people coming into your meeting. One has a gold ring and fine clothes, while the other is poor, dressed in filthy rags. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.3" osisID="Jas.2.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Then suppose that you were to take special notice of the one wearing fine clothes, saying, <q type="x-complete">Here’s an excellent place. Sit here.</q> But to the poor person you say, <q type="x-complete">Stand over there</q>; or, <q type="x-complete">Here, sit at my feet.</q> </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.4" osisID="Jas.2.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Wouldn’t you have shown favoritism among yourselves and become evil-minded judges? </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.2.5" osisID="Jas.2.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My dear brothers and sisters, listen! Hasn’t God chosen those who are poor by worldly standards to be rich in terms of faith? Hasn’t God chosen the poor as heirs of the kingdom he has promised to those who love him? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.6" osisID="Jas.2.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you have dishonored the poor. Don’t the wealthy make life difficult for you? Aren’t they the ones who drag you into court? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.7" osisID="Jas.2.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Aren’t they the ones who insult the good name spoken over you at your baptism? </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.2.8" osisID="Jas.2.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You do well when you really fulfill the royal law found in scripture, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Love your neighbor as yourself.</hi><note osisRef="Jas.2.8" placement="inline" osisID="Jas.2.8!note.a">Lev 19:18</note> </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.9" osisID="Jas.2.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But when you show favoritism, you are committing a sin, and by that same law you are exposed as a lawbreaker. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.10" osisID="Jas.2.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Anyone who tries to keep all of the Law but fails at one point is guilty of failing to keep all of it. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.11" osisID="Jas.2.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The one who said, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Don’t commit adultery</hi>, also said, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Don’t commit murder</hi>.<note osisRef="Jas.2.11" placement="inline" osisID="Jas.2.11!note.b">Exod 20:13, 15 LXX (English: 20:13-14); Deut 5:17–18</note> So if you don’t commit adultery but do commit murder, you are a lawbreaker. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.12" osisID="Jas.2.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In every way, then, speak and act as people who will be judged by the law of freedom. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.13" osisID="Jas.2.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There will be no mercy in judgment for anyone who hasn’t shown mercy. Mercy overrules judgment. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.2.14-Jas.2.26" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Showing faith</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.2.14" osisID="Jas.2.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, what good is it if people say they have faith but do nothing to show it? Claiming to have faith can’t save anyone, can it? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.15" osisID="Jas.2.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Imagine a brother or sister who is naked and never has enough food to eat. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.16" osisID="Jas.2.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What if one of you said, <q type="x-complete">Go in peace! Stay warm! Have a nice meal!</q>? What good is it if you don’t actually give them what their body needs? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.17" osisID="Jas.2.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, faith is dead when it doesn’t result in faithful activity. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.2.18" osisID="Jas.2.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Someone might claim, <q type="x-complete">You have faith and I have action.</q> But how can I see your faith apart from your actions? Instead, I’ll show you my faith by putting it into practice in faithful action. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.19" osisID="Jas.2.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It’s good that you believe that God is one. Ha! Even the demons believe this, and they tremble with fear. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.20" osisID="Jas.2.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Are you so slow? Do you need to be shown that faith without actions has no value at all? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.21" osisID="Jas.2.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What about Abraham, our father? Wasn’t he shown to be righteous through his actions when he offered his son Isaac on the altar? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.22" osisID="Jas.2.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">See, his faith was at work along with his actions. In fact, his faith was made complete by his faithful actions. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.23" osisID="Jas.2.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So the scripture was fulfilled that says, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">Abraham believed God, and God regarded him as righteous</hi>.<note osisRef="Jas.2.23" placement="inline" osisID="Jas.2.23!note.c">Gen 15:6</note> What is more, Abraham was called God’s friend. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.24" osisID="Jas.2.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">So you see that a person is shown to be righteous through faithful actions and not through faith alone. </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.25" osisID="Jas.2.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, wasn’t Rahab the prostitute shown to be righteous when she received the messengers as her guests and then sent them on by another road? </verse><verse sID="Jas.2.26" osisID="Jas.2.26" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">As the lifeless body is dead, so faith without actions is dead. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Jas.3" osisID="Jas.3" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="3"><div scope="Jas.3.1-Jas.3.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Taming the tongue</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Jas.3.1" osisID="Jas.3.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, not many of you should become teachers, because we know that we teachers will be judged more strictly. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.2" osisID="Jas.3.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">We all make mistakes often, but those who don’t make mistakes with their words have reached full maturity. Like a bridled horse, they can control themselves entirely. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.3" osisID="Jas.3.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">When we bridle horses and put bits in their mouths to lead them wherever we want, we can control their whole bodies. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.3.4" osisID="Jas.3.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Consider ships: they are so large that strong winds are needed to drive them. But pilots direct their ships wherever they want with a little rudder. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.5" osisID="Jas.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">In the same way, even though the tongue is a small part of the body, it boasts wildly. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.3.5" osisID="Jas.3.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">Think about this: a small flame can set a whole forest on fire. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.6" osisID="Jas.3.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The tongue is a small flame of fire, a world of evil at work in us. It contaminates our entire lives. Because of it, the circle of life is set on fire. The tongue itself is set on fire by the flames of hell. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.3.7" osisID="Jas.3.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">People can tame and already have tamed every kind of animal, bird, reptile, and fish. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.8" osisID="Jas.3.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">No one can tame the tongue, though. It is a restless evil, full of deadly poison. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.9" osisID="Jas.3.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">With it we both bless the Lord and Father and curse human beings made in God’s likeness. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.10" osisID="Jas.3.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Blessing and cursing come from the same mouth. My brothers and sisters, it just shouldn’t be this way! </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.3.11" osisID="Jas.3.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Both fresh water and salt water don’t come from the same spring, do they? </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.12" osisID="Jas.3.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, can a fig tree produce olives? Can a grapevine produce figs? Of course not, and fresh water doesn’t flow from a saltwater spring either. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.3.13-Jas.3.18" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Wisdom from above</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.3.13" osisID="Jas.3.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Are any of you wise and understanding? Show that your actions are good with a humble lifestyle that comes from wisdom. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.14" osisID="Jas.3.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">However, if you have bitter jealousy and selfish ambition in your heart, then stop bragging and living in ways that deny the truth. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.15" osisID="Jas.3.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">This is not the wisdom that comes down from above. Instead, it is from the earth, natural and demonic. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.16" osisID="Jas.3.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Wherever there is jealousy and selfish ambition, there is disorder and everything that is evil. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.17" osisID="Jas.3.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What of the wisdom from above? First, it is pure, and then peaceful, gentle, obedient, filled with mercy and good actions, fair, and genuine. </verse><verse sID="Jas.3.18" osisID="Jas.3.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Those who make peace sow the seeds of justice by their peaceful acts. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Jas.4" osisID="Jas.4" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="4"><div scope="Jas.4.1-Jas.4.12" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Conflict with people and God</title><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Jas.4.1" osisID="Jas.4.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">What is the source of conflict among you? What is the source of your disputes? Don’t they come from your cravings that are at war in your own lives? </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.2" osisID="Jas.4.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You long for something you don’t have, so you commit murder. You are jealous for something you can’t get, so you struggle and fight. You don’t have because you don’t ask. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.3" osisID="Jas.4.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You ask and don’t have because you ask with evil intentions, to waste it on your own cravings. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.4.4" osisID="Jas.4.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You unfaithful people! Don’t you know that friendship with the world makes you an enemy of God? </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.5" osisID="Jas.4.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Or do you suppose that scripture is meaningless? Doesn’t God long for our faithfulness in<note osisRef="Jas.4.5" placement="inline" osisID="Jas.4.5!note.d">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">jealously longs for</hi></note> the life he has given to us?<note osisRef="Jas.4.5" placement="inline" osisID="Jas.4.5!note.e">Or <hi type="x-CEBFootnoteItalic">Doesn’t the spirit that God placed in us have jealous desires?</hi></note> </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.6" osisID="Jas.4.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But he gives us more grace. This is why it says, <hi type="x-CEBBodyItalic">God stands against the proud, but favors the humble</hi>.<note osisRef="Jas.4.6" placement="inline" osisID="Jas.4.6!note.f">Prov 3:34</note> </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.7" osisID="Jas.4.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, submit to God. Resist the devil, and he will run away from you. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.8" osisID="Jas.4.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Come near to God, and he will come near to you. Wash your hands, you sinners. Purify your hearts, you double-minded. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.9" osisID="Jas.4.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Cry out in sorrow, mourn, and weep! Let your laughter become mourning and your joy become sadness. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.10" osisID="Jas.4.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Humble yourselves before the Lord, and he will lift you up. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.4.11" osisID="Jas.4.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, don’t say evil things about each other. Whoever insults or criticizes a brother or sister insults and criticizes the Law. If you find fault with the Law, you are not a doer of the Law but a judge over it. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.12" osisID="Jas.4.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">There is only one lawgiver and judge, and he is able to save and to destroy. But you who judge your neighbor, who are you? </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.4.13-Jas.4.17" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Warning the proud and wealthy</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.4.13" osisID="Jas.4.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pay attention, you who say, <q type="x-complete">Today or tomorrow we will go to such-and-such a town. We will stay there a year, buying and selling, and making a profit.</q> </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.14" osisID="Jas.4.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You don’t really know about tomorrow. What is your life? You are a mist that appears for only a short while before it vanishes. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.15" osisID="Jas.4.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Here’s what you ought to say: <q type="x-complete">If the Lord wills, we will live and do this or that.</q> </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.16" osisID="Jas.4.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But now you boast and brag, and all such boasting is evil. </verse><verse sID="Jas.4.17" osisID="Jas.4.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">It is a sin when someone knows the right thing to do and doesn’t do it. </verse></p></div></chapter><chapter sID="Jas.5" osisID="Jas.5" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="5"><div scope="Jas.5.1-Jas.5.6" type="section"><p type="x-CEBChapterStart"><verse sID="Jas.5.1" osisID="Jas.5.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Pay attention, you wealthy people! Weep and moan over the miseries coming upon you. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.2" osisID="Jas.5.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Your riches have rotted. Moths have destroyed your clothes. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.3" osisID="Jas.5.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Your gold and silver have rusted, and their rust will be evidence against you. It will eat your flesh like fire. Consider the treasure you have hoarded in the last days. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.4" osisID="Jas.5.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Listen! Hear the cries of the wages of your field hands. These are the wages you stole from those who harvested your fields. The cries of the harvesters have reached the ears of the Lord of heavenly forces. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.5" osisID="Jas.5.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You have lived a self-satisfying life on this earth, a life of luxury. You have stuffed your hearts in preparation for the day of slaughter. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.6" osisID="Jas.5.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You have condemned and murdered the righteous one, who doesn’t oppose you. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.5.7-Jas.5.11" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Courageous patience</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.5.7" osisID="Jas.5.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Therefore, brothers and sisters, you must be patient as you wait for the coming of the Lord. Consider the farmer who waits patiently for the coming of rain in the fall and spring, looking forward to the precious fruit of the earth. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.8" osisID="Jas.5.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">You also must wait patiently, strengthening your resolve, because the coming of the Lord is near. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.9" osisID="Jas.5.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Don’t complain about each other, brothers and sisters, so that you won’t be judged. Look! The judge is standing at the door! </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.5.10" osisID="Jas.5.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Brothers and sisters, take the prophets who spoke in the name of the Lord as an example of patient resolve and steadfastness. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.11" osisID="Jas.5.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Look at how we honor those who have practiced endurance. You have heard of the endurance of Job. And you have seen what the Lord has accomplished, for the Lord is full of compassion and mercy. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jas.5.12-Jas.5.20" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Final instructions</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.5.12" osisID="Jas.5.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Most important, my brothers and sisters, never make a solemn pledge—neither by heaven nor earth, nor by anything else. Instead, speak with a simple <q type="x-complete">Yes</q> or <q type="x-complete">No,</q> or else you may fall under judgment. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.5.13" osisID="Jas.5.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If any of you are suffering, they should pray. If any of you are happy, they should sing. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.14" osisID="Jas.5.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">If any of you are sick, they should call for the elders of the church, and the elders should pray over them, anointing them with oil in the name of the Lord. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.15" osisID="Jas.5.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Prayer that comes from faith will heal the sick, for the Lord will restore them to health. And if they have sinned, they will be forgiven. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.16" osisID="Jas.5.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">For this reason, confess your sins to each other and pray for each other so that you may be healed. The prayer of the righteous person is powerful in what it can achieve. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.17" osisID="Jas.5.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Elijah was a person just like us. When he earnestly prayed that it wouldn’t rain, no rain fell for three and a half years. </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.18" osisID="Jas.5.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">He prayed again, God sent rain, and the earth produced its fruit. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jas.5.19" osisID="Jas.5.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">My brothers and sisters, if any of you wander from the truth and someone turns back the wanderer, </verse><verse sID="Jas.5.20" osisID="Jas.5.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">recognize that whoever brings a sinner back from the wrong path will save them from death and will bring about the forgiveness of many sins. </verse></p></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>