<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ABUCO_VIEW.XSL"?><osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace osisCore.2.1.1.xsd"><osisText osisIDWork="thiswork" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en"><header><work osisWork="thisWork"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Jude</title><type type="OSIS">Bible</type><identifier type="OSIS"></identifier><rights type="x-copyright"></rights><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work><work osisWork="bible"><refSystem>Bible</refSystem></work></header><div><div type="book" osisID="Jude"><chapter sID="Jude.1" osisID="Jude.1" type="x-CEBChapterNo" n="1"><title type="x-CEBBookTitle">Jude</title><div scope="Jude.1.1-Jude.1.2" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Greeting</title><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Jude.1.1" osisID="Jude.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">Jude, a slave of Jesus Christ and brother of James. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Jude.1.1" osisID="Jude.1.1" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">To those who are called, loved by God the Father and kept safe by Jesus Christ. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBGreeting"><verse sID="Jude.1.2" osisID="Jude.1.2" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">May you have more and more mercy, peace, and love. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jude.1.3-Jude.1.10" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Certain judgment of the false teachers</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.3" osisID="Jude.1.3" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Dear friends, I wanted very much to write to you concerning the salvation we share. Instead, I must write to urge you to fight for the faith delivered once and for all to God’s holy people. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.4" osisID="Jude.1.4" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Godless people have slipped in among you. They turn the grace of our God into unrestrained immorality and deny our only master and Lord, Jesus Christ. Judgment was passed against them a long time ago. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.5" osisID="Jude.1.5" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I want to remind you of something you already know very well. The Lord, who once saved a people out of Egypt, later destroyed those who didn’t maintain their faith. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.6" osisID="Jude.1.6" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">I remind you too of the angels who didn’t keep their position of authority but deserted their own home. The Lord has kept them in eternal chains in the underworld until the judgment of the great day. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.7" osisID="Jude.1.7" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">In the same way, Sodom and Gomorrah and neighboring towns practiced immoral sexual relations and pursued other sexual urges. By undergoing the punishment of eternal fire, they serve as a warning. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.8" osisID="Jude.1.8" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Yet, even knowing this, these dreamers in the same way pollute themselves, reject authority, and slander the angels. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.9" osisID="Jude.1.9" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">The archangel Michael, when he argued with the devil about Moses’ body, did not dare charge him with slander. Instead, he said, <q type="x-complete">The Lord rebuke you!</q> </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.10" osisID="Jude.1.10" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But these people slander whatever they don’t understand. They are destroyed by what they know instinctively, as though they were irrational animals. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jude.1.11-Jude.1.19" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Prophecies about the false teachers</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.11" osisID="Jude.1.11" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They are damned, for they follow in the footsteps of Cain. For profit they give themselves over to Balaam’s error. They are destroyed in the uprising of Korah. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.12" osisID="Jude.1.12" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These people who join your love feasts are dangerous. They feast with you without reverence. They care only for themselves. They are waterless clouds carried along by the winds; fruitless autumn trees, twice dead, uprooted; </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.13" osisID="Jude.1.13" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">wild waves of the sea foaming up their own shame; wandering stars for whom the darkness of the underworld is reserved forever. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.14" osisID="Jude.1.14" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Enoch, who lived seven generations after Adam, prophesied about these people when he said, <q type="x-start">See, the Lord comes with his countless holy ones,</q> </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.15" osisID="Jude.1.15" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete"><q type="x-end">to execute judgment on everyone and to convict everyone about every ungodly deed they have committed in their ungodliness as well as all the harsh things that sinful ungodly people have said against him.</q> </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.16" osisID="Jude.1.16" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These are faultfinding grumblers, living according to their own desires. They speak arrogant words and they show partiality to people when they want a favor in return. </verse></p><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.17" osisID="Jude.1.17" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you, dear friends, remember the words spoken beforehand by the apostles of our Lord Jesus Christ. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.18" osisID="Jude.1.18" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">They said to you, <q type="x-complete">In the end time scoffers will come living according to their own ungodly desires.</q> </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.19" osisID="Jude.1.19" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">These people create divisions. Since they don’t have the Spirit, they are worldly. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jude.1.20-Jude.1.23" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">A strategy for the faithful</title><p type="x-CEBBodyText"><verse sID="Jude.1.20" osisID="Jude.1.20" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">But you, dear friends: build each other up on the foundation of your most holy faith, pray in the Holy Spirit, </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.21" osisID="Jude.1.21" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">keep each other in the love of God, wait for the mercy of our Lord Jesus Christ, who will give you eternal life. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.22" osisID="Jude.1.22" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Have mercy on those who doubt. </verse><verse sID="Jude.1.23" osisID="Jude.1.23" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-complete">Save some by snatching them from the fire. Fearing God, have mercy on some, hating even the clothing contaminated by their sinful urges. </verse></p></div><div scope="Jude.1.24-Jude.1.25" type="section"><title type="x-CEBPericopeHead">Blessing</title><lg><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Jude.1.24" osisID="Jude.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">To the one who is able to protect you from falling, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Jude.1.24" osisID="Jude.1.24" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">and to present you blameless and rejoicing before his glorious presence, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText1"><verse sID="Jude.1.25" osisID="Jude.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-start">to the only God our savior, through Jesus Christ our Lord, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText3"><verse sID="Jude.1.25" osisID="Jude.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-continuation">belong glory, majesty, power, and authority, </verse></l><l type="x-CEBPoetryText4"><verse sID="Jude.1.25" osisID="Jude.1.25" type="x-CEBVerseNo" subType="x-end">before all time, now and forever. Amen. </verse></l></lg></div></chapter></div></div></osisText></osis>